<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;somAkhyAdi on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/MT/somAkhyAdi/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;somAkhyAdi on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/MT/somAkhyAdi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The visitation on the</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/MT/somAkhyAdi/2024-04-21_the-visitation-on-the-knoll/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/MT/somAkhyAdi/2024-04-21_the-visitation-on-the-knoll/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2024/04/21/the-visitation-on-the-knoll/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The visitation on the knoll&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It was the time Somakhya and Indrasena were by themselves — without their companions — for that is close to the ultimate test of a man. At that point, they were working on the mysterious three-gene system coding for an ATPase that had evolved from a GTPase, a mystery protein, and a RNase. While they had made an initial incision they were being rebuffed by it and it was testing Indrasena’s skills to the utmost. To clear their minds, they decided to go out for a walk in the solitude among the knolls. Just before Indrasena could join Somakhya, he got a call regarding an emergency in the lab and he had to head there to inspect the situation. Somakhya nevertheless decided to continue alone for, after all, the final reckoning of a man comes when he is all by himself. Thus, he walked the gently rising paths against the backdrop of the mild spring sun — the benign symbol in the intermediate heavens of the great god Savitṛ whose laws none violate. The following incantation came to his mind: “adābhyo bhuvanāni pracākaśad vratāni devaḥ savitābhi rakṣate ।”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The crossover with Dabba</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/MT/somAkhyAdi/2024-03-10_the-chrossover-with-dabba-seTThiputta/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/MT/somAkhyAdi/2024-03-10_the-chrossover-with-dabba-seTThiputta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2024/03/10/the-crossover-with-dabba-se%e1%b9%ad%e1%b9%adhiputta/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The crossover with Dabba Seṭṭhīputta&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;ash&#34;&gt;Ash&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It was a Śivarātrī. Vidrum accompanied his friends Somakhya and Lootika to visit the small shrine of Rudra in the cemetery beside his house. It was one of the rare days when the normally deserted cemetery was fairly busy with many a votary streaming in to pay homage at the shrine. Vidrum milled around a bit as his friends performed some japa at the side of the circumambulatory circuit of the shrine. There were vendors of flowers and bilva leaves whose wares the votaries bought to offer to The god (sa devaḥ). A pleasant breeze blew through the cemetery, making howling noises reminiscent of ghosts and also reminding the cognizant votary of the presence of the The god of the Vrātya-s who “blows here”. As if to bring back that picture from a bygone Aryan age, a tall śaiva ascetic suddenly strode into the shrine. He carried a trident, a large pair of iron tongs slung from his shoulder, and was beating a ḍamaru as he cycled through the recitation of the pañcabrahma-mantra-s. He sat down at one corner and started singing a stotra attributed to the demon-king of Laṅkā. Seeing him, Vidrum came back and sat beside his friends. The śaiva ascetic then arose again and started making circumambulations, resuming the muttering of brahma-mantra-s. As reached the Bahurūpī-ṛk, the ascetic suddenly darted towards Somakhya and smeared ashes on his forehead. As he continued with his circumambulation, at one point, when he was reciting the Vāmadeva-ṛk, he did the same to Lootika. He then went inside the garbhagṛha and started muttering some mantra-s. While he was uttering them in a low tone that the lay devotees would make no sense of, Lootika realized what he was uttering and caught Somakhya’s eye. Somakhya, too, had simultaneously figured out his incantation and whispered to Lootika: “I’m surprised — it is the Mahākāla-hṛdaya, a rare mantra from the root of Śambhu-para Uttarāmnāya, known to very few!” L: “Indeed!”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Dalāl who became a</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/MT/somAkhyAdi/2024-01-16_the-dalal-who-became-a-poltergeist/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/MT/somAkhyAdi/2024-01-16_the-dalal-who-became-a-poltergeist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2024/01/16/the-dalal-who-became-a-poltergeist/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Dalāl who became a poltergeist&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Lootika had returned from a scientific competition, which had been held in the dreadful city of Mahāvisphoṭaka, like the victorious Roman army after sacking the towns of West Asian counter-religionists. To both celebrate and to educate the class her teacher had organized an evening of sky-watching where Lootika was to introduce her often unruly classmates to the basics of astronomy. She knew well that beauty and success inspired anger and envy in many and that such a session could descend into the unsavory or worse quickly. Hence, she roped in Somakhya and convinced her teacher that he should take the lead in the session, though he had stayed out of the competition and let her claim the glory. She almost felt he had been like Zeus letting Herakles gain the glory at contests of the Olympic games. She faced her share of scowls and intentional interruptions from the more begrudging and rowdy classmates, but for the most part, it went well as Somakhya handled much of the show. Thus, after the session, they decided to take advantage of the situation and partake in the joys of dinner at a restaurant with some of their classmates — something their parents heavily disapproved of. For this purpose, they decided to meet at Vidrum’s house and then proceed to a nearby eating place. That way, Lootika could get back home in time without arousing any suspicions that might trigger her parents’ espionage regime.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The death of Miss Lizzie</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/MT/somAkhyAdi/2022-05-02_the-death-of-miss-lizzie-willink/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/MT/somAkhyAdi/2022-05-02_the-death-of-miss-lizzie-willink/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2022/05/02/the-death-of-miss-lizzie-willink/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The death of Miss Lizzie Willink&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Late that spring, Somakhya and Lootika were visited by their mleccha friend Irmhild. Letting her sleep off the jet lag, they left for work. Given the good weather, Lootika returned early to check on their friend and go out with her prospecting spiders in the nearby woods for their work on endosymbionts. L: “Hope you had some good sleep and are all set to lead our battle-charge? Let me get you something to eat and we’ll head out when the sun goes down a bit. Somakhya and a student will join us in the woods.” Even as Lootika brought Irmhild some snacks, she said: “Restful, but strange. At least I can confess this to you without any embarrassment — After a while, I had a visitation from Lizzie — I’m sure you have heard of her from Somakhya and your folks. In any case, it may be a good sign given what we intend to do.” L: “Ah! they mentioned her in passing, but my recollection is they were not successful in getting her to say anything.” Ir: “I would not be so negative — I learned her name from that really exciting sitting they arranged.” L: “I’d like to hear it straight from your mouth — ain’t it interesting we never got to talk about that in length?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The strange case of the</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/MT/somAkhyAdi/2021-11-27_the-strange-case-of-the-apastamba-sprite/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/MT/somAkhyAdi/2021-11-27_the-strange-case-of-the-apastamba-sprite/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2021/11/27/the-strange-case-of-the-apastamba-sprite/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The strange case of the Āpastamba sprite&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;problem-manifests&#34;&gt;Problem manifests&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is the second of the two stories that arose from incidents during&#xA;the visit of Yaśaśravas, Somakhya’s cousin. With the autumnal vacations,&#xA;Somakhya was having a good time with his visiting cousin, giving him&#xA;lectures on the theory and the practice of the study of variable stars.&#xA;During the day, they spent their time with numerical solutions of&#xA;differential equations that modeled the pulsations of stars. At night,&#xA;they observed the stars in good view from Somakhya’s terrace with the&#xA;smog of the fireworks having lifted. Additionally, as instructed by&#xA;Somakhya’s father, he was also teaching Yashashravas sections of the&#xA;hautra mantra-pāṭha. The on the second day of his cousin’s visit, the&#xA;two of them were doing their evening saṃdhyā rituals together when&#xA;Somakhya was disturbed by a peculiar behavior evinced by his cousin. In&#xA;the midst of his prāṇāyāma or arghya, Yashashravas suddenly uttered the&#xA;word Āpastamba-sūtra almost randomly a few times with a peculiar&#xA;affectation and cadence. Somakhya was taken aback, but remembering his&#xA;father’s words of never getting disturbed in his performance, he ignored&#xA;it and continued to the end. Somakhya: “Yashashravas, what is wrong with&#xA;you — have you gone crazy? Why were you randomly saying&#xA;“Āpastamba-sūtra” in the course of your saṃdhyāvandana? I know you are&#xA;of that school, but it makes no sense to pepper your upāsana with&#xA;utterances of that word, moreover voiced in that strange manner.”&#xA;Yashashravas felt as if some weight had lifted off his head and told&#xA;Somakhya a strange tale. Somakhya was shocked by it, but once he had&#xA;gathered himself, he said they should wait until his friend Lootika&#xA;visited before taking any further action.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
