<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;kAntAra on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/kAntAra/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;kAntAra on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/kAntAra/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>pankaj review</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/kAntAra/pankaj-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/kAntAra/pankaj-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://threadreaderapp.com/thread/1582615110958612481.html&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When Gods Wake Up – What the movie ‘#Kantara’ means for Hindus. Raw! Visceral! Existential! Unprecedented! And flagrantly Hindu! That is what Kantara is, and oh how! It is a celebration of ‘Being Hindu’. It is a movie made by the Deva himself. This is how.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Kantara completely inverts the way the colonized Hindus have been interpreting their own world, culture and civilization to the world in the past 200 years and inverts it to bring it back to its original position – fearless, unconscious recognition of the Divine all around us! It is not a story told by humans about the Devas. It is a story which the Deva tells to humans, from a divine point of view. Since our contact with the West, Hindus have been trying to ‘interpret’ their dharma, rituals, customs &amp;amp; tradition in the language of the colonizers. We have become accustomed to say, ‘it is a Hindu ‘belief’…’, ‘according to Hindu beliefs…’ almost completely convinced ourselves that our stories are just fairy tales imagined by illiterate, superstitious and ignorant ancestors, which need ‘scientific interpretation’. Slowly, we became so used to this constant cultural translation in our minds that we ourselves started believing that our stories are just stories with no existence on any plane of consciousness. We became ‘rational’ and bought into the Judeo-Christian/ Enlightenment paradigm.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
