<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;2 Book Two on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;2 Book Two on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>057</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/057/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/057/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To the realists.&lt;/em&gt; – You sober people who feel armed against passion and phantastical conceptions and would like to make your emptiness a matter of pride and an ornament – you call yourself realists and insinuate that the world really is the way it appears to you: before you alone reality stands unveiled, and you yourselves are perhaps the best part of it – oh, you beloved images of Sais!1 But aren’t you too in your unveiled condition still most passionate and dark creatures, compared to fish, and still all too similar to an artist in love? And what is ‘reality’ to an artist in love! You still carry around the valuations of things that originate in the passions and loves of former centuries! Your sobriety still contains a secret and inextirpable drunkenness! Your love of ‘reality’, for example – oh, that is an old, ancient ‘love’! In every experience, in every sense impression there is a piece of this old love; and some fantasy, some prejudice, some irrationality, some ignorance, some fear, and whatever else, has worked on and contributed to it. That mountain over there! That cloud over there! What is ‘real’ about that? Subtract just once the phantasm and the whole human &lt;em&gt;contribution&lt;/em&gt; from it, you sober ones! Yes, if you could do &lt;em&gt;that!&lt;/em&gt; If you could forget your background, your past, your nursery school – all of your humanity and animality! There is no ‘reality’ for us – and not for you either, you sober ones – we are not nearly as strange to one another as you think, and perhaps our good will to transcend drunkenness is just as respectable as your belief that you are altogether &lt;em&gt;incapable&lt;/em&gt; of drunkenness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>058</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/058/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/058/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Only as creators!&lt;/em&gt; – This has caused me the greatest trouble and still does always cause me the greatest trouble: to realize that &lt;em&gt;what things are called&lt;/em&gt; is unspeakably more important than what they are. The reputation, name, and appearance, the worth, the usual measure and weight of a thing – originally almost always something mistaken and arbitrary, thrown over things like a dress and quite foreign to their nature and even to their skin – has, through the belief in it and its growth from generation to generation, slowly grown onto and into the thing and has become its very body: what started as appearance in the end nearly always becomes essence and &lt;em&gt;effectively acts&lt;/em&gt; as its essence! What kind of a fool would believe that it is enough to point to this origin and this misty shroud of delusion in order to &lt;em&gt;destroy&lt;/em&gt; the world that counts as ‘real’, so-called ‘reality’! Only as creators can we destroy! – But let us also not forget that in the long run it is enough to create new names and valuations and appearances of truth in order to create new ‘things’.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>059</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/059/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/059/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We artists.&lt;/em&gt; – When we love a woman, we easily come to hate nature because of all the repulsive natural functions to which every woman is subject; we prefer not to think about it at all, but when our soul for once brushes against these matters, it shrugs impatiently and, as just said, casts a contemptuous look at nature: we feel insulted; nature seems to intrude on our property and with the most profane hands at that. In cases like this one refuses to hear anything about physiology and decrees secretly to oneself, ‘I will hear nothing of the idea that the human being is anything other than soul and form!’ ‘The human being under the skin’ is an abomination and unthinkable to all lovers, a blasphemy against God and love. Now, the way lovers still feel about nature and naturalness is how every worshipper of God and his ‘holy omnipotence’ formerly felt: in everything that was said about nature by astronomers, geologists, physiologists, and doctors, he saw an intrusion on his choicest property and thus an attack – and a shameless one at that! Even the ‘law of nature’ sounded to him like a slander against God; he would basically much rather have seen all of mechanics traced back to moral acts of will and choice – but since no one could do him that service, he &lt;em&gt;concealed&lt;/em&gt; nature and mechanics from himself as best he could and lived in a dream. Oh, these people of former times knew how to &lt;em&gt;dream,&lt;/em&gt; and didn’t even need to fall asleep first! – and we men of today also still know it all too well, despite all our good will towards waking and the day! We need only to love, to hate, to desire, simply to feel – &lt;em&gt;at once&lt;/em&gt; the spirit and power of the dream comes over us, and we climb with open eyes, impervious to all danger, up the most dangerous paths, onto the roofs and towers of fantasy, and without any vertigo, as though born to climb – we sleepwalkers of the day! We artists! We who conceal naturalness! We who are moon- and God-struck! We untiring wanderers, silent as death, on heights that we see not as heights but as our plains, as our safety.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>060</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/060/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/060/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Women and their action at a distance.&lt;/em&gt; – Do I still have ears? Am I all ear and nothing else? Here I stand amidst the fire of the surf, whose white flames are licking at my feet: from all sides it is howling, threatening, screaming, shrieking at me, while the old earth-rattler2 sings his aria in the lowest of depths, deep as a roaring bull, while pounding such an earth-rattling beat that the hearts of even these weather-beaten monsters of the rocks are trembling in their bodies. Suddenly, as if born out of nothingness, there appears before the gate of this hellish labyrinth only a few fathoms away a large sailing ship, gliding along as silently as a ghost. Oh, this ghostly beauty! How magically it touches me! What? Has all the calm and silence of the world embarked here? Is my happiness itself sitting in this quiet place – my happier self, my second, immortalized self?3 Not yet to be dead, but also no longer alive? As a spiritlike, silent, watching, gliding, hovering intermediate being? As though I were that ship that moves over the dark sea with its white sails like an enormous butterfly! Yes! To move &lt;em&gt;over&lt;/em&gt; existence! That’s it! That would be it! – It seems as though the noise here has made me into a dreamer? All great noise makes us place happiness in silence and distance. When a man stands in the midst of &lt;em&gt;his own&lt;/em&gt; noise, in the midst of his own surf of projects and plans, he is also likely to see gliding past him silent, magical creatures whose happiness and seclusion he yearns for – &lt;em&gt;women.&lt;/em&gt; He almost believes that his better self lives there amongst the women: in these quiet regions even the loudest surf turns into deathly silence and life itself into a dream about life. Yet! Yet! My noble enthusiast, even on the most beautiful sailing ship there is so much sound and noise, and unfortunately so much small, petty noise! The magic and the most powerful effect of women is, to speak the language of the philosophers, action at a distance, *actio in distans:*4 but that requires, first and foremost – &lt;em&gt;distance!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>061</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/061/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/061/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In honour of friendship.&lt;/em&gt; – That the feeling of friendship was in antiquity considered the highest feeling, even higher than the most celebrated pride of the self-sufficient sage, indeed, as it were, as its sole and even holier sibling: this is very well expressed in the story of the Macedonian king who gave a world-despising Athenian philosopher a talent and got it back. ‘What?’ said the king, ‘Has he then no friend?’5 He meant: ‘I honour this pride of the wise and independent man, but I would honour his humanity even more highly if the friend in him had won over his pride. The philosopher has lowered himself before me by showing that he doesn’t know one of the two highest feelings – and the higher one at that.’&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>062</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/062/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/062/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Love.&lt;/em&gt; – Love forgives the beloved even his lust.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>063</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/063/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/063/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The woman in music.&lt;/em&gt; – Why do warm and rainy winds also bring on a musical mood and the inventive pleasure of melody? Are they not the same winds that fill the churches and give women thoughts of love?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>064</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/064/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/064/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sceptics.&lt;/em&gt; – I am afraid that old women in their most secret heart of hearts are more sceptical than all men: they believe the superficiality of existence to be its essence, and all virtue and depth is to them merely a veil over this ‘truth’, the very desirable veil over a pudendum – in other words, a matter of decency and shame, and no more!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>065</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/065/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/065/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Devotion.&lt;/em&gt; – There are noble women with a certain poverty of spirit who know no other way to &lt;em&gt;express&lt;/em&gt; their deepest devotion than to offer their virtue and sense of shame: it is what they hold as their highest possession. And often this gift is accepted without incurring as profound an obligation as the donors suppose – a very melancholy story!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>066</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/066/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/066/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The strength of the weak.&lt;/em&gt; – All women are subtle at exaggerating their weaknesses; indeed they are inventive at weaknesses in order to appear as utterly fragile ornaments that are harmed by even a speck of dust: their way of living is supposed to remind men of their clumsiness and burden their conscience with this. Thus they defend themselves against the strong and ‘the law of the jungle’.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>067</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/067/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/067/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Feigning oneself.&lt;/em&gt; – She loves him now and gazes ahead with such calm confidence, like a cow. But alas! What bewitched him was precisely that she seemed utterly changeable and unfathomable! He already had too much steady weather in himself! Wouldn’t she do well to feign her old character? To feign lovelessness? Isn’t that the counsel of – love? *Vivat comoedia!*6&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>068</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/068/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/068/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Will and willingness.&lt;/em&gt; – Someone took a youth to a wise man and said: ‘Look, he is being corrupted by women!’ The wise man shook his head and smiled. ‘It is men who corrupt women’, he exclaimed, ‘and the failings of women should be atoned for and set right in men – for man makes for himself the image (&lt;em&gt;Bild&lt;/em&gt;) of woman, and woman shapes herself (&lt;em&gt;bildet sich&lt;/em&gt;) according to this image (Bild)’. ‘You are too gentle towards women’, said one in the company; ‘you do not know them!’ The wise man replied, ‘The way of men is will; the way of women is willingness – that is the law of the sexes; truly a hard law for women! All human beings are innocent of their existence; women, however, are doubly innocent. Who could have oil and mercy enough for them?’ ‘Forget oil! Forget gentleness!’ shouted someone else from the crowd; ‘one has to raise women better!’ ‘One has to raise men better’, said the wise man and beckoned to the youth to follow him. – But the youth did not follow him.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>069</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/069/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/069/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Capacity for revenge.&lt;/em&gt; – That someone cannot defend himself and therefore also does not want to – this is not enough to disgrace him in our eyes; but we have a low regard for anyone who has neither the capacity nor the good will for revenge – regardless of whether it is a man or a woman. Would a woman be able to hold us (or ‘enthrall’ us, as they say) if we did not consider her able under certain circumstances to wield a dagger deftly (any kind of dagger) &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; us? Or against herself – which in certain cases would be the more severe revenge (Chinese revenge).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>070</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/070/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/070/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The women who master the masters.&lt;/em&gt; – A deep and powerful alto voice, such as one sometimes hears in the theatre, suddenly raises the curtain upon possibilities that we usually do not believe in. All at once we believe that somewhere in the world there could be women with lofty, heroic, royal souls, capable of and ready for grandiose retorts, resolutions, and sacrifices, capable of and ready for mastery over men, because in them the best of man aside from his sex has become an incarnate ideal. To be sure, the intention of the theatre is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; at all that such voices convey this concept of women; normally they are supposed to represent the ideal male lover, for example a Romeo; but to judge from my experience, the theatre quite regularly miscalculates on this point, as does the composer who expects such effects from such a voice. One does not believe in &lt;em&gt;these&lt;/em&gt; lovers: such voices always retain a motherly and housewifely colouring, and most of all when love is in their tone.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>071</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/071/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/071/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On female chastity.&lt;/em&gt; – There is something quite amazing and monstrous in the upbringing of upper-class women; indeed, maybe there is nothing more paradoxical. The whole world agrees that they should be brought up as ignorant as possible about matters erotic, and that one has to impart in their souls a deep shame in the face of such things and the most extreme impatience and flight at the merest suggestion of them. Really, in this matter alone the ‘honour’ of a woman in its entirety is at risk: what else would one not forgive them? But here they are supposed to remain ignorant deep in their hearts: they are supposed to have neither eyes, nor ears, nor words, nor thoughts for this their ‘evil’; yes, even knowledge is here an evil. And then to be hurled as if by a gruesome lightning bolt into reality and knowledge, with marriage – and precisely by the man they love and esteem the most: to catch love and shame in a contradiction and to have to experience all at once delight, surrender, duty, pity, terror at the unexpected proximity of god and beast, and who knows what else! There one has tied a psychic knot that may have no equal. Even the compassionate curiosity of the wisest connoisseur of human psychology (&lt;em&gt;Menschenkenner&lt;/em&gt;) is insufficient for guessing how this or that woman manages to accommodate herself to this solution of the riddle and to this riddle of a solution, and what dreadful, far-reaching suspicions must stir in her poor, unhinged soul; indeed, how the ultimate philosophy and scepticism of woman casts anchor at this point! Afterwards, the same deep silence as before, and often a silence directed at herself; she closes her eyes to herself. Young women try very hard to appear superficial and thoughtless; the most refined among them simulate a kind of impertinence. Women easily experience their men as a question-mark regarding their honour and their children as an apology or atonement – they need children and wish for them in an altogether different way from that in which a man wishes for children. In sum, one cannot be too gentle towards women!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>072</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/072/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/072/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mothers.&lt;/em&gt; – Animals think differently about females than humans do; they consider the female to be the productive being. There is no paternal love among them, only something like love for the children of a beloved and a getting used to them. In their children females have a satisfaction of their desire to dominate, a possession, an occupation, something that is totally intelligible to them and can be prattled with: all this taken together is motherly love – it is to be compared to the love of an artist for his work. Pregnancy has made women gentler, more patient, more timid, more pleased to submit; and just so does spiritual pregnancy produce the character of the contemplative type, to which the female character is related: these are male mothers. – Among animals the male sex is considered the beautiful one.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>073</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/073/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/073/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Holy cruelty.&lt;/em&gt; – A man holding a newborn in his hand approached a holy man. ‘What should I do with this child?’ he asked; ‘it is wretched, misshapen, and doesn’t have life enough to die’. ‘Kill it!’ shouted the holy man with a terrible voice; ‘kill it and hold it in your arms for three days and three nights to create a memory for yourself: thus you will never again beget a child when it is not time for you to beget’. When the man had heard this, he walked away disappointed; and many people reproached the holy man because he had advised a cruelty; for he had advised killing the child. ‘But is it not crueller to let it live?’ said the holy man.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>074</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/074/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/074/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The unsuccessful.&lt;/em&gt; – Those poor women are always unsuccessful who, in the presence of the one they love, become restless and insecure and talk too much: for men are most surely seduced by a certain secret and phlegmatic tenderness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>075</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/075/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/075/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The third sex.&lt;/em&gt; – ‘A small man is a paradox, but still a man; but small women seem to me, when compared to tall women, to belong to another sex’, said an old dancing master. A small woman is never beautiful – said old Aristotle.7&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>076</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/076/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/076/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The greatest danger.&lt;/em&gt; – Had there not always been a majority of men who felt the discipline of their heads – their ‘rationality’ – to be their pride, their obligation, their virtue, and who were embarrassed or ashamed by all fantasizing and debauchery of thought, being the friends of ‘healthy common sense’, humanity would have perished long ago! The greatest danger that hovered and still hovers over humanity is the outbreak of &lt;em&gt;madness&lt;/em&gt; – that is, the outbreak of arbitrariness in feeling, seeing, and hearing; the enjoyment in the lack of discipline of the head, the joy in human unreason. The opposite of the world of the madman is not truth and certainty but the generality and universal bindingness of a faith; in short, the non-arbitrary in judgement. And man’s greatest labour so far has been to reach agreement about very many things and to lay down a &lt;em&gt;law of agreement&lt;/em&gt; – regardless of whether these things are true or false. This is the discipline of the head which has preserved humanity – but the counter-drives are still so powerful that it is basically with little confidence that one may speak of the future of humanity. The picture of things still moves and shifts continually, and perhaps more and faster from now on than ever before; continually, the most select minds bristle at this universal bindingness – the explorers of &lt;em&gt;truth&lt;/em&gt; above all! Continually this faith, as a commonplace belief shared by everyone, breeds nausea and a new lust in subtler minds; and the slow tempo for all spiritual processes which this faith makes necessary, this imitation of the tortoise that is recognized as the norm here, would by itself be sufficient to turn artists and poets into deserters: it is these impatient minds in whom a veritable delight in madness breaks out, because madness has such a cheerful tempo! What is needed, then, are virtuous intellects – oh, I’ll use the most unambiguous word – what is needed is &lt;em&gt;virtuous stupidity;&lt;/em&gt; what is needed are unwavering beat-keepers of the &lt;em&gt;slow&lt;/em&gt; spirit, so that the believers of the great common faith stay together and go on dancing their dance: it is an exigency of the first order which commands and demands. &lt;em&gt;We others are the exception and the danger&lt;/em&gt; – we stand eternally in need of defence! – Now there is certainly something to be said for the exception, &lt;em&gt;provided it never wants to become the rule.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>077</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/077/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/077/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The animal with a good conscience.&lt;/em&gt; – The vulgar element in everything that pleases in Southern Europe – be it Italian opera (e.g. Rossini and Bellini)8 or the Spanish adventure novel (most readily accessible to us in the French disguise of Gil Blas)9 – does not escape me; but it does not offend me, just as little as does the vulgarity that one encounters on a walk through Pompeii and basically even when reading any ancient book.10 Why is this? Is it because there is no shame and everything vulgar acts as confidently and self-assuredly as anything noble, lovely, and passionate in the same kind of music or novel? ‘The animal has its own right, just like the human being; let it run about freely – and you too, my dear fellow man, are still an animal despite everything!’ – That seems to me to be the moral of the story and the peculiarity of Southern humanity. Bad taste has its right just as good taste does – and even a prior right if it answers to a great need, provides guaranteed satisfaction and as it were a universal language, an unconditionally intelligible mask and gesture; good, refined taste, on the contrary, is always somewhat searching, deliberate, not altogether sure how it is to be understood: it is not and never was popular! What is and remains popular is the &lt;em&gt;mask!&lt;/em&gt; So let them all continue to go their way, all those masklike elements in the melodies and cadenzas, in the leaps and gaieties of the rhythm of these operas! Ancient life, too! What can one understand about it when one does not understand the delight in the mask, the good conscience in everything mask-like! Here is the bath and the recreation of the ancient spirit – and maybe the rare and sublime natures of the old world needed this bath more than the vulgar. A vulgar turn in Northern works, for example in German music, on the other hand, offends me unspeakably. Here there is &lt;em&gt;shame;&lt;/em&gt; the artist has lowered himself in his own eyes and could not even help blushing: we are ashamed with him and are so offended because we suspect that he believed he had to lower himself for our sakes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>078</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/078/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/078/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What we should be grateful for.&lt;/em&gt; – Only artists, and especially those of the theatre, have given men eyes and ears to see and hear with some pleasure what each himself is, himself experiences, himself wants; only they have taught us to value the hero that is hidden in each of these everyday characters and taught the art of regarding oneself as a hero, from a distance and as it were simplified and transfigured – the art of ‘putting oneself on stage’ before oneself. Only thus can we get over certain lowly details in ourselves. Without this art we would be nothing but foreground, and would live entirely under the spell of that perspective which makes the nearest and most vulgar appear tremendously big and as reality itself. Maybe there is a similar sort of merit in that religion which bade one to see the sinfulness of every individual through a magnifying glass and turned the sinner into a great, immortal criminal: by describing eternal perspectives around him, it taught man to view himself from a distance and as something past and whole.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>079</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/079/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/079/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The attraction of imperfection.&lt;/em&gt; – I see here a poet who, like some people, exerts a greater attraction through his imperfections than through all that reaches completion and perfection under his hand – indeed, his advantage and fame are due much more to his ultimate incapacity than to his ample strength. His work never wholly expresses what he really would like to express, what he &lt;em&gt;would like to have seen:&lt;/em&gt; it seems as if he has had the foretaste of a vision, but never the vision itself – yet a tremendous lust for this vision remains in his soul, and it is from this that he derives his equally tremendous eloquence of desire and craving. With it he lifts his listener above his work and all ‘works’ and lends him wings to rise to heights which listeners otherwise never reach; and so, having themselves become poets and seers, they give the creator of their happiness their due admiration, as if he had led them immediately to the vision of what was for him holiest and most ultimate; as if he had really attained his goal and really &lt;em&gt;seen&lt;/em&gt; and communicated his vision. The fact that he never reached his goal benefits his fame.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>080</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/080/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/080/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Art and nature.&lt;/em&gt; – The Greeks (or at least the Athenians) liked to hear good speech; indeed, they had a greedy craving for it which distinguishes them more than anything else from the non-Greeks. And so they demanded even of passion on stage that it speak well, and submitted with delight to the unnaturalness of dramatic verse – after all, in nature, passion is so taciturn! So mute and bashful! Or when it finds words, so confused and irrational and a shame to itself! Now thanks to the Greeks, we have all grown accustomed to this unnaturalness on stage, just as we endure and gladly endure that other unnaturalness, &lt;em&gt;singing&lt;/em&gt; passion, thanks to the Italians. We have developed a need that we cannot satisfy in reality: to hear people in the most difficult situations speak well and at length; it delights us now when the tragic hero still finds words, reasons, eloquent gestures, and altogether a radiant spirit where life approaches the abyss and a real human being would usually lose his head and certainly his fine language. This kind of &lt;em&gt;deviation from nature&lt;/em&gt; is perhaps the most pleasant meal for human pride; for its sake man loves art as the expression of a lofty, heroic unnaturalness and convention. We rightly reproach a dramatic poet if he does not transform everything into reason and words but always retains in his hand a residue of &lt;em&gt;silence&lt;/em&gt; – just as one is dissatisfied with the musician at the opera who cannot find a melody for the highest affect but only a sentimental ‘natural’ stammering and screaming. For here nature is &lt;em&gt;supposed&lt;/em&gt; to be contradicted! Here the vulgar charm of illusion is &lt;em&gt;supposed&lt;/em&gt; to give way to a higher charm! The Greeks go far, far on this road – terrifyingly far! Just as they make the stage as narrow as possible and forbid themselves all effects through deep backgrounds; just as they make facial expressions and easy movement impossible for the actor and transform him into a solemn, stiff, masked puppet, so they also have deprived passion itself of any deep background and dictated to it a law of beautiful speech; yes, on the whole they have done everything to counteract the elemental effect of images that arouse fear and compassion – &lt;em&gt;for fear and compassion were precisely what they did not want.&lt;/em&gt; With all due respect to Aristotle, he certainly didn’t hit the nail, let alone on the head, when he discussed the final purpose of Greek tragedy.11 Just consider the Greek tragic poets and what most stimulated their industriousness, their sensitivity, their competitiveness – certainly not the aim of overwhelming the spectator with emotions. The Athenian went to the theatre &lt;em&gt;to hear pleasing speech!&lt;/em&gt; Pleasing speeches were what preoccupied Sophocles12 – pardon the heresy! It is quite different with &lt;em&gt;serious opera.&lt;/em&gt; All of its masters try to keep the audience from understanding the characters. Occasionally catching a word might help the inattentive listener, but on the whole the situation must explain itself – the speeches don’t matter! This is how they all think and have pulled their pranks with words. Maybe they only lacked the courage to express fully their ultimate disregard for words: with just a little more impudence, Rossini13 would have had everyone sing nothing but la-la-la-la – and that would have made good sense. One shouldn’t believe the words of characters in opera, but rather their sound! That is the difference, that is the beautiful &lt;em&gt;unnaturalness&lt;/em&gt; for the sake of which one goes to the opera. Even the &lt;em&gt;recitativo&lt;/em&gt; secco14 is not really meant to be heard as word and text: this kind of half-music is rather supposed initially to give the musical ear a short rest (rest from the &lt;em&gt;melody&lt;/em&gt; as the most sublime and therefore also the most challenging pleasure of this art) – but very soon also something else, namely, a growing impatience, a growing aversion, a new desire for &lt;em&gt;whole&lt;/em&gt; music, for melody. How are things with Richard Wagner’s art,15 considered from this perspective? Is it the same, perhaps? Perhaps different? Often it has seemed to me as if one had to memorize the words &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; music of his creations before the performance, for otherwise – so it appeared to me – one &lt;em&gt;would hear&lt;/em&gt; neither the words nor even the music.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>081</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/081/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/081/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Greek taste.&lt;/em&gt; – ‘What is beautiful about that?’ said the surveyor after a performance of &lt;em&gt;Iphigenia.&lt;/em&gt; ‘Nothing is proved in it!’16 Were the Greeks that far away from this taste? In Sophocles, at least, ‘everything is proved’.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>082</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/082/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/082/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Esprit17 as un-Greek.&lt;/em&gt; – The Greeks are indescribably logical and simple in all their thought; at least in their long good age they never wearied of this, as so often do the French, who all too gladly take a little leap into the opposite and actually only endure the spirit of logic when, through a series of such small leaps into the opposite, it betrays its &lt;em&gt;sociable&lt;/em&gt; civility, its sociable self-denial. Logic strikes them as necessary, like bread and water, but also, like these, as a kind of prisoners’ food as soon as it is enjoyed pure and plain. In good company one must never want to be entirely and solely right, which is what all pure logic wants; hence the small dose of unreason in all French &lt;em&gt;esprit.&lt;/em&gt; The Greeks’ sense of sociability was far less developed than that of the French is and was; that is why there is so little &lt;em&gt;esprit&lt;/em&gt; in even their most spirited men; that is why there is so little humour in even their humorists; that is why – oh! One will not even believe these sentences of mine, and how many more of the same sort are yet on my mind! – &lt;em&gt;Est res magna tacere&lt;/em&gt;18 – says Martial along with all garrulous people.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>083</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/083/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/083/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Translations.&lt;/em&gt; – One can estimate the degree of an age’s historical sense from the way it makes &lt;em&gt;translations&lt;/em&gt; and seeks to absorb past ages and books. The French of Corneille’s age19 as well as those of the Revolution seized Roman antiquity in a way we no longer dare to – thanks to our higher historical sense. And Roman antiquity itself: how violently and yet naively it laid its hand on everything good and lofty in the older Greek antiquity! How they translated things into the Roman present! How deliberately and insouciantly they brushed the dust off the wings of that butterfly called ‘The-Twinkling-of-an-Eye’! In this way Horace translated Alcaeus or Archilochus20 now and then, as did Propertius with Callimachus and Philetas (poets of the same rank as Theocritus,21if we &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; judge): what did they care that the real creator had experienced this and that and written the signs of it into his poem! As poets they were averse to the antiquarian inquisitiveness that precedes the sense for history; as poets, they did not accept these utterly personal things and names and all those things that serve as the mask and costume of a city, coast, century. Rather they quickly replaced them with what was contemporary and Roman. They seem to ask us: ‘Should we not make new for ourselves what is old and put &lt;em&gt;ourselves&lt;/em&gt; into it? Should we not be allowed to breathe our soul into their dead body? For it is dead, after all: how ugly everything dead is!’ They did not know the pleasure of a sense for history; what was past and alien was embarrassing to them; and as Romans, they saw it as an incentive for a Roman conquest. In fact at that time one conquered by translating – not merely by leaving out the historical, but also by adding allusions to the present and, above all, crossing out the name of the poet and replacing it with one’s own – not with any sense of theft but with the very best conscience of the *imperium Romanum.*22&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>084</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/084/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/084/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On the origin of poetry.&lt;/em&gt; – The lovers of what is fantastic in humans, who also advocate the view that morality is instinctive, reason as follows: ‘Supposing that usefulness has always been venerated as the supreme deity, then where in all the world does poetry come from? This act of making speech rhythm counteracts rather than contributes to the clarity of communication, and yet it has shot up and is still shooting up all over the earth like a mockery of all useful expediency! The wildly beautiful irrationality of poetry refutes you, you utilitarians! Precisely to want to &lt;em&gt;get away&lt;/em&gt; from usefulness for once – that is what has elevated humanity; that is what has inspired it to morality and art!’ Now, in this case I must side with the utilitarians for once – after all, they are so seldom right, it is pitiful! In those ancient times that called poetry into being, one really did aim at utility, and a very great utility at that; back then, when one let rhythm penetrate speech – that rhythmic force that reorganizes all the atoms of a sentence, bids one to select one’s words and gives thoughts a new colour and makes them darker, stranger, more distant: a &lt;em&gt;superstitious utility,&lt;/em&gt; of course! Rhythm was supposed to make a human request impress the gods more deeply after it was noticed that humans remember a verse better than ordinary speech; one also thought one could make oneself audible over greater distances with the rhythmic tick-tock; the rhythmic prayer seemed to get closer to the ears of the gods. Above all, one wanted to take advantage of that elemental overpowering force that humans experience in themselves when listening to music: rhythm is a compulsion; it engenders an unconquerable desire to yield, to join in; not only the stride of the feet but also the soul itself gives in to the beat – probably also, one inferred, the souls of the gods! By means of rhythm one thus tried to &lt;em&gt;compel&lt;/em&gt; them and to exercise a power over them: one cast poetry around them like a magical snare. There was another, stranger notion, and it may be precisely what contributed most powerfully to the origin of poetry. Among the Pythagoreans23 it appears as a philosophical doctrine and as an educational contrivance; but even long before there were philosophers, one acknowledged music to have the power to discharge the emotions, to cleanse the soul, to soothe the &lt;em&gt;ferocia animi&lt;/em&gt;24 – and indeed precisely through its rhythmic quality. When one had lost the proper tension and harmony of the soul, one had to &lt;em&gt;dance&lt;/em&gt; to the beat of the singer – that was the prescription of this healing art. With it, Terpander quelled an uprising; with it, Empedocles pacified a lunatic; with it, Damon purged a youth who was languishing from love; with it, one also sought to appease the ferocious, vindictive gods.25 One began by driving the giddiness and exuberance of their passions to their peak, that is, one drove the madman wild, made the vindictive person drunk with lust for revenge. All orgiastic cults wanted to discharge the &lt;em&gt;ferocia&lt;/em&gt;26 of some deity all at once and turn it into an orgy so that the deity would feel freer and calmer afterwards and leave man in peace. Etymologically, &lt;em&gt;melos&lt;/em&gt;27 means a tranquillizer, not because it is itself tranquil, but because its effect makes one tranquil. And not only in the cult song, but also in the mundane song of the most ancient times there is the presumption that rhythmic quality exercises a magical force; when bailing water, for instance, or rowing, the song is a bewitchment of the demons believed to be at work here; it makes them compliant, unfree, and a tool of humans. And whenever one acts, one has an occasion to sing – &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; action is tied to the assistance of spirits: incantation and conjuration seem to be the primordial form of poetry. When verse was used in oracles – the Greeks said that the hexameter was invented at Delphi – rhythm was also supposed to exercise a compulsion.28 To ask for a prophecy – that meant originally (according to the derivation of the Greek word that seems most probable to me) to have something determined: one thought one could force the future by gaining Apollo’s favour – he who according to the oldest views is much more than a god of foresight. The way the formula is pronounced, with literal and rhythmic precision, is how it binds the future; the formula, however, is the invention of Apollo, who as god of rhythm can also bind the goddesses of fate. In short: was there anything more &lt;em&gt;useful&lt;/em&gt; than rhythm to the old superstitious type of human being? One could do everything with it: promote some work magically; compel a god to appear, to be near, to listen; mould the future according to one’s own will; discharge some excess (of fear, of mania, of pity, of vengefulness) from one’s soul, and not only one’s own soul but also that of the most evil demon. Without verse one was nothing; through verse one almost became a god. Such a basic feeling cannot be completely eradicated – and still today, after millennia of work at fighting such superstition, even the wisest of us occasionally becomes a fool for rhythm, if only in so far as he &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; a thought to be &lt;em&gt;truer&lt;/em&gt; when it has a metric form and presents itself with a divine hop, skip, and jump. Is it not amusing that the most serious philosophers, strict as they otherwise are in all matters of certainty, still appeal to &lt;em&gt;the sayings of poets&lt;/em&gt; to lend their thoughts force and credibility? And yet it is more dangerous for a truth when a poet agrees with it than when he contradicts it! For as Homer says: ‘The bards tell many a lie’.29&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>085</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/085/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/085/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The good and the beautiful.&lt;/em&gt; – Artists constantly &lt;em&gt;glorify&lt;/em&gt; – they do nothing else – and in particular all those states and things reputed to give man the occasion for once to feel good, or great, or drunk, or merry, or well and wise. These &lt;em&gt;select&lt;/em&gt; things and states, whose value for human &lt;em&gt;happiness&lt;/em&gt; is considered certain and well-defined, are the artists’ objects: artists always lie in wait to discover such things and to draw them into the realm of art. I want to say: they are not themselves the appraisers of happiness and of the happy man, but they always crowd around these appraisers with the greatest curiosity and the urge to make immediate use of their appraisals. They become like this because in addition to their impatience they also have the big lungs of heralds and the feet of runners, and are always among the first to glorify the &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; good, and often &lt;em&gt;appear&lt;/em&gt; to be the first to name it good and to appraise it as good. This, however, as I already said, is a mistake: they are only quicker and louder than the real appraisers. – But who &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; the real appraisers? – The rich and the idle.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>086</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/086/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/086/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On theatre.&lt;/em&gt; – This day I had strong and elevated feelings again, and if on its eve I could have music and art, I know very well what music and art I would &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; like to have, namely, the kind that tries to intoxicate its audience and &lt;em&gt;drive it to the height&lt;/em&gt; of a moment of strong and elevated feelings – an art for those everyday souls who in the evening look not like victors on triumphal chariots but rather like tired mules who have been whipped somewhat too often by life. What would those people know of ‘higher moods’ were there no intoxicating substances and whip-lashes of ideals! – and so they have their inspirers as they have their wines. But what is their drink and their drunkenness &lt;em&gt;to me!&lt;/em&gt; What is wine to the inspired! He looks instead with a sort of disgust at the means and the mediators that are supposed to produce an effect without sufficient reason – aping the high tide of the soul! What? One gives the mole wings and proud conceits – before bedtime, before he crawls into his hole? One sends him to the theatre and puts big glasses before his blind and tired eyes? People whose lives are not a ‘dramatic action’ but a business sit before the stage and look at strange creatures for whom life is more than a business? ‘It’s proper that way’, you say; ‘it’s entertaining that way; it’s culture!’ Well then! In that case I all too often lack culture, for this sight is all too often disgusting to me. Whoever has enough tragedy and comedy in himself probably does best to stay away from the theatre; or, should there be an exception, the entire event – including theatre and audience and poet – becomes the actual tragic and comic spectacle to him, so that the piece that is performed means little to him by comparison. What do the Fausts and Manfreds30 of the theatre matter to someone who is himself somewhat like Faust and Manfred? – whereas the fact &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; such figures are brought on stage is certainly something for him to think about. The &lt;em&gt;strongest&lt;/em&gt; thoughts and passions are there presented before those who are capable not of thought and passion – but of &lt;em&gt;intoxication!&lt;/em&gt; And the &lt;em&gt;former&lt;/em&gt; as a means to the latter! And theatre and music as the hashish-smoking and betel-chewing of the European! Oh, who will tell us the entire history of narcotics? – It is nearly the history of ‘culture’, our so-called higher culture!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>087</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/087/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/087/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On the vanity of artists.&lt;/em&gt; – I believe that artists often do not know what they can do best because they are too vain and have set their minds on something prouder than these small plants seem to be that are new, strange, and beautiful and really capable of growing to perfection on their soil. That which in the last instance is good in their own garden and vineyard is not fully appreciated by them, and their love and insight are not of the same order. Here is a musician who, more than any other musician, is master at finding the tones from the realm of suffering, dejected, tormented souls and at giving speech even to the mute animals. Nobody equals him at the colours of late autumn, at the indescribably moving happiness of a last, very last, very briefest enjoyment; he knows a tone for those secret, uncanny midnights of the soul, where cause and effect seem to have gone awry and something can come to be ‘from nothing’ at any moment; more happily than anyone else, he draws from the very bottom of human happiness and so to speak from its drained cup, where the most bitter and repulsive drops have merged, for better or for worse, with the sweetest ones; he knows how the soul wearily drags itself along when it can no longer leap and fly, nor even walk; he has the shy glance of concealed pain, of understanding without solace, of taking farewell without confession; yes, as the Orpheus31 of all secret misery he is greater than anyone, and he has incorporated into art some things that seemed inexpressible and even unworthy of art, and which could only be scared away and not be grasped by words in particular – some very small and microscopic features of the soul: yes, he is master at the very small. But he doesn’t &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to be! His &lt;em&gt;character&lt;/em&gt; likes great walls and bold frescoes much better! It escapes him that his &lt;em&gt;spirit&lt;/em&gt; has a different taste and disposition and likes best of all to sit quietly in the corners of collapsed houses – there, hidden, hidden from himself, he paints his real masterpieces, which are all very short, often only a bar long – only there does he become wholly good, great, and perfect; perhaps only there. – But he doesn’t know it! He is too vain to know it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>088</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/088/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/088/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Being serious about truth.&lt;/em&gt; – Being serious about truth! How differently people understand these words! The very same opinions and types of proof and scrutiny that a thinker may consider a frivolity in himself to which he has, to his shame, succumbed on this or that occasion – these very same views may give an artist who encounters them and lives with them for a while the feeling that he has now become deeply serious about truth and that it is admirable that he, as an artist, has at the same time the most serious desire for the opposite of appearance. So it can happen that it is precisely with his ardent seriousness that someone betrays how shallow and undemanding his mind has been in playing the field of knowledge so far. – And does not everything that we take to be &lt;em&gt;important&lt;/em&gt; betray us? It shows us what sort of thing has weight for us and for what sort of thing we have no weights.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>089</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/089/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/089/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Now and formerly.&lt;/em&gt; – What do all our art of artworks matter if we lose that higher art, the art of festivals! Formerly, all artworks were displayed on the great festival road of humanity, as commemorations and memorials of high and happy moments. Now one uses artworks to lure poor, exhausted, and sick human beings to the side of humanity’s road of suffering for a short lascivious moment; one offers them a little intoxication and madness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>090</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/090/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/090/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lights and shadows.&lt;/em&gt; – Books and drafts mean different things to different thinkers: one has collected in a book the lights that he was able swiftly to steal and carry home from the rays of some insight that dawned on him; another is able to convey only the shadows, the after-images in grey and black, of that which built itself up in his soul the day before.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>091</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/091/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/091/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Caution.&lt;/em&gt; – As is well known, Alfieri32 lied very much when he told his amazed contemporaries his life story. He lied from that despotism against himself which he also revealed in the way he created his own language and tyrannized himself into becoming a poet – he had finally found a severe form of sublimity into which he &lt;em&gt;pressed&lt;/em&gt; his life and his memory: no doubt there was much agony in all this. – I also would not believe a life story of Plato, written by himself – any more than that of Rousseau33 or the &lt;em&gt;vita nuova&lt;/em&gt;34 of Dante.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>092</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/092/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/092/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Prose and poetry.&lt;/em&gt; – It is remarkable that the great masters of prose have almost always also been poets, be it publicly or only in secret, in the ‘closet’; and verily, one writes good prose only &lt;em&gt;face to face with poetry!&lt;/em&gt; For this is an uninterrupted, courteous war with poetry: all its attractions depend on the fact that poetry is constantly evaded and contradicted; everything abstract wants to be presented as a prank against poetry and as if with a mocking voice; everything dry and cool is supposed to drive the lovely goddess into lovely despair; often there are &lt;em&gt;rapprochements,&lt;/em&gt; reconciliations for a moment, and then a sudden leap back and derisive laugh; often the curtain is raised and a harsh light is let in just as the goddess is enjoying her dusks and muted colours; often the word is taken out of her mouth and sung according to a melody that makes her cover her refined ears with her refined hands – and so there are a thousand delights of this war, including defeat, of which the unpoetic, the so-called men of prose, know nothing at all – which is why they write and speak only bad prose! *War is the father of all good things;*35 war is also the father of good prose! In this century, four very strange and truly poetic persons attained a mastery of prose, for which this century is otherwise not made – out of a lack of poetry, as I have suggested. Excluding Goethe, who may fairly be claimed by the century that produced him, I see Giacomo Leopardi, Prosper Mérimée, Ralph Waldo Emerson, and Walter Savage Landor, the author of &lt;em&gt;Imaginary Conversations&lt;/em&gt;,36 as worthy of being called masters of prose.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>093</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/093/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/093/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;But then why do you write?&lt;/em&gt; – A: I am not one of those who &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; with a wet quill in hand; much less one of those who abandon themselves to their passions right before the open inkwell, sitting on their chair and staring at the paper. I am annoyed or ashamed by all writing; to me, writing is nature’s call – to speak of it even in simile is repugnant to me. B: But why, then, do you write? – A: Well, my friend, I say this in confidence: until now I have found no other means of getting &lt;em&gt;rid&lt;/em&gt; of my thoughts. – B: And why do you want to get rid of them? – A: Why do I want to? Do I want to? I have to. – B: Enough! Enough!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>094</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/094/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/094/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Growth after death.&lt;/em&gt; – Those audacious little words about moral matters that Fontenelle threw out in his immortal &lt;em&gt;Dialogues of the Dead&lt;/em&gt;37 were considered in his time to be paradoxes and games of a not wholly innocent wit; even the highest judges of taste and of the mind saw nothing more in it – indeed, maybe not even Fontenelle himself. Now something incredible transpires: these thoughts become truths! Science proves them! The game gets serious! And we read these dialogues with a different feeling than Voltaire38 and Helvétius39 read them, and involuntarily we promote their creators to a different and &lt;em&gt;much higher&lt;/em&gt; rank of mind than they did. Rightly? Wrongly?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>095</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/095/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/095/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chamfort.40&lt;/em&gt; – That someone who knew humanity and the masses as well as Chamfort still joined the masses and did not stand aside in philosophical renunciation and defence, I can only explain as follows: one instinct in him was stronger than his wisdom and was never satisfied: his hatred of all nobility of blood; perhaps his mother’s old hatred, which was only too easy to explain and which he had sanctified through love of his mother – an instinct for revenge harking back to his boyhood, waiting for the hour to avenge his mother. And now his life and his genius – and alas! no doubt mostly the paternal blood in his veins – had seduced him to join the ranks of this nobility as an equal, for many, many years! But eventually he could no longer stand the sight of himself, the sight of the ‘old type of man’ under the old regime; he was gripped with a violent passion of repentance which led him to put on the clothes of the mob, as &lt;em&gt;his&lt;/em&gt; kind of hairshirt! His bad conscience was his failure to take revenge. If Chamfort had remained just a little bit more a philosopher, the Revolution would not have had its tragic wit and sharpest sting: it would be considered a much stupider event and would not seduce so many minds. But Chamfort’s hatred and revenge educated a whole generation, and the most illustrious human beings passed through this school. Note that Mirabeau41 looked up to Chamfort as to his higher and older self from which he expected and endured impulses, warnings, and verdicts – Mirabeau, who as a human being belongs to a quite different order of greatness than even the foremost statesmen of yesterday and today. It is peculiar that despite such a friend and advocate – after all, we have Mirabeau’s letters to Chamfort – this wittiest of all moralists has remained a stranger to the French, no less than Stendhal,42 who has perhaps had the most thoughtful eyes and ears of all Frenchmen of &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; century. Is it that the latter basically had too much of the Dutchman or Englishman within himself to be tolerable to the Parisians? Whereas Chamfort, a man who was rich in depths and backgrounds of the soul – gloomy, suffering, ardent – a thinker who found laughter necessary as a remedy against life and who nearly considered himself lost on those days when he had not laughed – seems much more like an Italian, related to Dante and Leopardi, than a Frenchman! We know Chamfort’s last words: ‘Ah! mon ami’, he said to Sieyès,43 ‘je m’en vais enfin de ce monde, ou il faut que le creur se brise ou se bronze –’.44 Those are surely not the words of a dying Frenchman.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>096</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/096/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/096/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Two speakers.&lt;/em&gt; – Of these two speakers, the one can show the full rationality of his cause only when he abandons himself to passion: this alone pumps enough blood and heat into his brain to force his lofty intellect to reveal itself. The other attempts the same thing now and then – to present his cause with the help of passion, sonorously, violently, and captivatingly – but usually with little success. He then quite soon starts speaking obscurely and confusedly; he exaggerates, makes omissions, and arouses mistrust about the rationality of his cause; indeed, he himself comes to feel this mistrust, and this explains sudden leaps into the coldest and most repugnant tones which make the audience doubt whether his whole passion was genuine. In his case, passion inundates the mind every time – maybe because it is stronger than in the first speaker. But he is at the peak of his strength when he resists the pressing storm of his feeling and virtually derides it: only then does his mind completely step out of its hiding place – a logical, mocking, playful, and yet terrifying mind.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>097</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/097/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/097/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On the garrulousness of writers.&lt;/em&gt; – There is a garrulousness of rage – frequent in Luther, also in Schopenhauer. A garrulousness due to an exceedingly large supply of conceptual formulations, as in Kant. A garrulousness due to a delight in ever-new twists of the same thing: one finds this in Montaigne. A garrulousness of spiteful natures: whoever reads the publications of our time will recall two writers here. A garrulousness from a delight in good words and forms of language: not rare in Goethe’s prose. A garrulousness from an inner pleasure in noise and confusion of feelings: for example in Carlyle.45&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>098</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/098/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/098/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In praise of Shakespeare.&lt;/em&gt; – The most beautiful thing I can say in praise of Shakespeare &lt;em&gt;as a human being&lt;/em&gt; is this: he believed in Brutus and didn’t cast a speck of suspicion on this type of virtue! To him he devoted his best tragedy – it is still called by the wrong name46 – to him and to the most dreadful epitome of lofty morality. Independence of soul! That’s what’s at stake here! No sacrifice can be too great for that: one has to be capable of sacrificing even one’s dearest friend for it, even if he should be the most marvellous human being, the ornament of the world, the genius without peer – if one loves freedom as the freedom of great souls and &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; freedom is endangered because of him: that is what Shakespeare must have felt! The height at which he places Caesar is the finest honour he could bestow on Brutus: only thus does he raise Brutus’ inner problem to immense proportions as well as the strength of mind that was able to cut &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; knot! And was it really political freedom that drove this poet to sympathize with Brutus – and turned him into Brutus’ accomplice? Or was political freedom only a symbolism for something inexpressible? Could it be that we confront some unknown dark event and adventure from the poet’s own soul about which he wanted to speak only in signs? What is all of Hamlet’s melancholy compared to that of Brutus! And perhaps Shakespeare knew the latter as he knew the former – through first-hand experience! Maybe he also had his dark hour and his evil angel, like Brutus! But whatever such similarities and secret references there may have been: before the whole figure and virtue of Brutus, Shakespeare threw himself to the ground and felt unworthy and distant – he wrote the evidence for this into his tragedy. Twice in the tragedy he introduced a poet,47 and twice he poured such impatient and ultimate contempt upon him that it sounds like a cry – like the cry of self-contempt. Brutus, even Brutus loses patience when the poet enters – conceited, pathetic, obtrusive, as poets usually are – as a being who appears to be bursting with possibilities of greatness, even moral greatness, although in the philosophy of deed and life he rarely attains even a passable integrity. ‘When he knows his time, &lt;em&gt;I’ll know his humour.&lt;/em&gt; / What should the wars do with these jiggling fools? / Companion, hence!’48 shouts Brutus. This should be translated back into the soul of the poet who wrote it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>099</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/099/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/099/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Schopenhauer’s followers.&lt;/em&gt; – What happens when people of a higher culture and barbarians come into contact: the lower culture usually takes on the vices, weaknesses, and excesses of the higher culture, on which basis it feels a certain attraction to that culture and finally, by way of the acquired vices and weaknesses, accepts some overflow of the valuable force of the higher culture – one can also observe this nearby and without travelling to barbarian peoples, to be sure in a form that is somewhat over-refined and intellectualized and not so easily palpable. And what do &lt;em&gt;Schopenhauer’s&lt;/em&gt; German followers usually take over at first from their master? In relation to his higher culture, they must feel barbarous enough to be at first barbarously fascinated and seduced by him. Is it his sense for hard facts, his good will to clarity and reason, that so often makes him appear so English and so un-German? Or is it the strength of his intellectual conscience, which &lt;em&gt;endured&lt;/em&gt; a life-long contradiction between being and willing and forced him to contradict himself continually and on almost every point in his writings? Or is it his cleanliness in matters of the church and of the Christian god? – for here his cleanliness was unprecedented among German philosophers, so that he lived and died ‘as a Voltairean’.49 Or was it his immortal doctrine of the intellectuality of intuition, of the a priori nature of the causal law, of the instrumental nature of the intellect and the unfreedom of the will?50 No, all this does not enchant and is not felt to be enchanting; but Schopenhauer’s mystical embarrassments and evasions in those places where the factual thinker let himself be seduced and corrupted by the vain urge to be the unriddler of the world; the indemonstrable doctrine of &lt;em&gt;One Will&lt;/em&gt; (‘all causes are merely occasional causes of the appearance of the will at this time and this place’; ‘the will to life is present wholly and undividedly in every being, even the least, as completely as in all beings that have ever been, are, and shall be, taken together’),51 the &lt;em&gt;denial of the individual&lt;/em&gt; (‘all lions are at bottom only one lion’; ‘the plurality of individuals is an illusion’,52 just as &lt;em&gt;development&lt;/em&gt; is only an illusion – he calls Lamarck’s thoughts ‘an ingenious, absurd error’),53 his ecstatic reveries on &lt;em&gt;genius&lt;/em&gt; (‘in aesthetic intuition the individual is no longer individual but pure, will-less, painless, timeless subject of knowledge’; ‘the subject, in being wholly taken up in the object it intuits, has become the object itself’),54 the nonsense about &lt;em&gt;compassion&lt;/em&gt; and how, as the source of all morality, it enables one to make the break through the *principium individuationis;*55 and also such claims as ‘death is actually the purpose of existence’,56 ‘one cannot deny &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; the possibility that a magical effect cannot also emanate from someone who has already died’ – these and other such &lt;em&gt;excesses&lt;/em&gt; and vices of the philosopher are always what is accepted first of all and made into a matter of faith – for vices and excesses are the easiest to imitate and require no extensive preparatory practice. But let us discuss the most famous of living Schopenhauerians, Richard Wagner. What happened to him has happened to other artists: he misinterpreted the characters he created and misunderstood the philosophy that was implicit in his own art. Until the middle of his life, Richard Wagner let himself be misled by Hegel; he repeated this mistake when he started reading Schopenhauer’s doctrine into his characters and began expressing himself in terms of ‘will’, ‘genius’, and ‘compassion’. Nevertheless it will remain true that nothing goes so directly against the spirit of Schopenhauer as what is genuinely Wagnerian in Wagner’s heroes: I mean the innocence of the utmost selfishness; the faith in great passion as the good in itself, in a word, what is Siegfried-like57 in the countenances of his heroes. ‘All of this smells even more like Spinoza than like me’, Schopenhauer might say. Although Wagner would have good reason to look for some other philosopher than Schopenhauer, the enchantment to which he succumbed with regard to this thinker has blinded him not only to other philosophers but also to science; his entire art increasingly wants to present itself as a companion piece and supplement to Schopenhauer’s philosophy, and with increasing explicitness it renounces the loftier ambition of becoming a companion piece and supplement to human knowledge and science. And not only is it the whole secretive splendour of this philosophy – which would also have attracted a Cagliostro58 – that draws him to this, but the particular gestures and affects of the philosophers were always seducers as well! Wagner is Schopenhauerian, for example, in his exasperation over the corruption of the German language;59 even, however, if one should approve of Wagner’s imitation of Schopenhauer in this point, one must not conceal the fact that Wagner’s style itself suffers rather seriously from all those ulcers and tumours whose sight so enraged Schopenhauer. Regarding the Wagnerians who write German, Wagnerianism is starting to prove as dangerous as any Hegelianism ever has. Wagner is Schopenhauerian in his hatred of the Jews, to whom he is unable to do justice even in their greatest deed; after all, the Jews are the inventors of Christianity.60 Wagner is Schopenhauerian in his attempt to conceive of Christianity as a seed of Buddhism that has drifted far and to prepare a Buddhistic age for Europe, with an occasional reconciliation with Catholic-Christian formulas and sentiments.61 Wagner is Schopenhauerian when he preaches mercy in our relations with animals; as we know, Schopenhauer’s predecessor in this was Voltaire, who may also, like his successors, have known to disguise his hatred of certain things and persons as mercy towards animals.62 At least Wagner’s hatred of science, which finds expression in his preaching, certainly does not come from a spirit of mercy and goodness – any more, obviously, than it does from any &lt;em&gt;spirit&lt;/em&gt; at all. In the end, the philosophy of an artist is of little significance if it is merely an afterthought (&lt;em&gt;eine nachträgliche Philosophie&lt;/em&gt;) and does not harm the art itself. One cannot be too careful to avoid bearing ill will against an artist for an occasional, perhaps very unfortunate and presumptuous masquerade; let us not forget that, without exception, our dear artists are to some extent actors and have to be, and that without acting they would hardly be able to hold out very long. Let us remain faithful to Wagner in what is &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; and original in him – and especially, as his disciples, by remaining faithful to ourselves in what is true and original in us. Let us leave him his intellectual tempers and cramps; let us, in all fairness, ask what strange kinds of nourishment and needs an art like his may &lt;em&gt;require&lt;/em&gt; in order to be able to live and grow! It doesn’t matter that as a thinker he is so often wrong; justice and patience are not for him. Enough that his life is justified before itself and remains justified – this life which shouts at every one of us: ‘Be a man and do not follow me – but yourself! Yourself!’63 &lt;em&gt;Our&lt;/em&gt; life, too, shall be justified before ourselves! We too shall freely and fearlessly, in innocent selfishness, grow and blossom from ourselves! And as I contemplate such a person, the following sentences still come to mind today as they did before: ‘That passion is better than Stoicism and hypocrisy; that being honest even in evil is better than losing oneself to the morality of tradition; that the free man can be good as well as evil, but the unfree man is a disgrace to nature and has no share in heavenly or earthly comfort; finally that &lt;em&gt;everyone who wants to be free must become so through himself,&lt;/em&gt; and that freedom does not fall into anyone’s lap as a wondrous gift’ (&lt;em&gt;Richard Wagner in Bayreuth,&lt;/em&gt; p. 94).64&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>100</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/100/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/100/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Learning how to pay homage.&lt;/em&gt; – Men have to learn to pay homage just as they have to learn to feel contempt. Anyone who breaks new paths and has led many people onto new paths discovers with amazement how clumsy and poor those many are at expressing their gratitude; indeed, how seldom gratitude &lt;em&gt;is able&lt;/em&gt; to express itself at all. It is as though whenever gratitude wants to speak, something gets caught in her throat so that she just clears her throat and falls silent clearing her throat. The way in which a thinker comes to sense the effects of his thoughts and their reorganizing and unsettling power is almost a comedy; it seems at times as if those who have been affected basically feel insulted and can only express what they take to be their threatened independence through a welter of incivilities. Entire generations are needed to invent merely a polite convention for thanks; and only very late comes that time when even gratitude has acquired a kind of spirit and genius; by then, someone is usually also around to be the great recipient of the gratitude, not only for what good he himself has done, but mostly for what his predecessors have slowly heaped up as a treasure of the highest and best.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>101</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/101/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/101/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;*Voltaire.*65 – Wherever there was a court, there were laws of good speech and thus also laws of style for all who wrote. The language of the court, however, is the language of the courtier, &lt;em&gt;who has no area of expertise&lt;/em&gt; and who forbids himself convenient technical expressions even in conversation about scientific matters because they smack of areas of expertise; that is why, in countries with a courtly culture, technical expressions and everything that betrays a specialist is considered a &lt;em&gt;stylistic blemish.&lt;/em&gt; Now that all courts have become caricatures of past and present, one is amazed to find even Voltaire unspeakably inflexible and punctilious on this point (for example in his judgement of such stylists as Fontenelle66and Montesquieu67) – for we are all emancipated from courtly taste, while Voltaire &lt;em&gt;perfected&lt;/em&gt; it!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>102</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/102/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/102/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A word to the philologists.&lt;/em&gt; – That there are books so valuable and regal that entire generations of scholars are well employed when, through their efforts, these books are preserved in a pure and intelligible state – philology exists to reinforce this faith again and again. It presupposes that there is no dearth of those rare human beings (even if one doesn’t see them right away) who really know how to use such valuable books – probably those who themselves write or could write such books. I mean that philology presupposes a noble faith – that for the sake of a few who always ‘will come’ but are not there, a very great deal of painstaking, even unclean work first needs to be done: it is all work &lt;em&gt;in usum Delphinorum&lt;/em&gt;.68&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>103</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/103/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/103/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On German music.&lt;/em&gt; – Today German music is, more than any other, the music of Europe only because it alone has given expression to the transformation that Europe underwent through the Revolution: only German composers know how to lend expression to animated masses of people; how to create that enormous artificial noise that doesn’t even have to be very loud – whereas for example Italian opera knows only choruses of servants or soldiers, but not ‘people’.69 Moreover, in all German music one can hear a deep bourgeois envy of nobility, especially of &lt;em&gt;esprit&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;élégance&lt;/em&gt; as expressions of a courtly, knightly, old, self-assured society. This music is not like that of Goethe’s singer before the gate, which also pleases ‘in the great hall’ and actually pleases the king; the idea is not ‘The knights looked bravely thither, and the fair down at their laps’.70 Even grace (&lt;em&gt;Grazie&lt;/em&gt;) does not appear in German music without pangs of conscience; only in the presence of native charm (&lt;em&gt;Anmut),&lt;/em&gt; the rustic sister of grace, does the German begin to feel wholly moral – and from that point on increasingly so, all the way up to his rapturous, erudite, often gruff ‘sublimity’, the sublimity of Beethoven. If you want to picture the human being for &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; music, well, just imagine Beethoven as he appears beside Goethe – say, at their encounter at Teplitz:71 as semi-barbarism beside culture, as the people beside nobility, as the good-natured human being next to the good and more than merely ‘good’ human being, as the visionary beside the artist, as the man in need of comfort next to the man who is comforted, as the exaggerating and suspicious man next to the fair-minded, as the moody self-tormentor, the foolishly ecstatic, the blissfully unhappy, the guilelessly immoderate, as the presumptuous and crude – and all in all, the ‘untamed human being’:72 that is how Goethe himself experienced and characterized him – Goethe, the exception among Germans for whom no music of equal rank has yet been found! Consider finally whether the ever more widely reaching contempt for melody and the atrophy of the melodic sense among Germans can be understood as a democratic boorishness and after-effect of the Revolution. For melody has such an open joy in lawfulness and such a revulsion towards everything that is inchoate, unformed, and arbitrary that it sounds like a strain from the &lt;em&gt;old&lt;/em&gt; order of things European and like a seduction and return to it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>104</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/104/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/104/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On the sound of the German language.&lt;/em&gt; – We know where the German comes from that for a few centuries has been accepted as literary German. The Germans, with their reverence for everything that came from &lt;em&gt;the court,&lt;/em&gt; have deliberately taken the chanceries as their model in everything they had to &lt;em&gt;write,&lt;/em&gt; such as letters, documents, wills, and so forth. To write in the style of the chanceries was to write like the courts and the government – that was something distinguished compared to the German spoken in the city in which one happened to live. Eventually one drew the consequences and started to speak the way one wrote – thus one became even more discriminating in word formations, in the choice of words and phrases, and finally also in sound: one affected a courtly tone when speaking, and in the end the affectation became natural. Perhaps nothing like this has happened anywhere else: the triumph of written style over speech and the affectation and pomposity of a whole people as the foundation of a common language that is no longer a mere conjunction of dialects. I believe that the sound of the German language in the middle ages, and especially in the time after the middle ages, was deeply rustic and vulgar; in the last few centuries it has become a bit more refined, primarily because one felt compelled to imitate so many French, Italian, and Spanish sounds – particularly on the part of the German (and Austrian) nobility, which could in no way be content with the mother tongue. But despite this exercise, German must have sounded unbearably vulgar to Montaigne or even Racine; and to this day, in the mouth of travellers even in the midst of an Italian rabble, it sounds very coarse and hoarse, as if it originated in the back woods in smoky cabins and rude regions. I note today that among the former admirers of the chanceries a similar yearning for refinement of sound is spreading, and that the Germans are starting to obey a most peculiar ‘acoustic spell’ which could, in the long run, become a real danger to the German language – for one would seek in vain to find more abhorrent sounds in Europe. Something scornful, cold, indifferent, careless in one’s voice: that is what sounds ‘refined’ to Germans today – and I hear the good will to this refinement in the voices of young officials, teachers, women, merchants; even little girls are starting to imitate this officers’ German. For the officer – specifically the Prussian officer – is the inventor of these sounds: this same officer who as military man and specialist possesses that admirable tact of modesty which all Germans could stand to learn (including German professors and musicians!). But as soon as he speaks and moves, the German officer is the most immodest and distasteful figure in old Europe – quite unselfconsciously, without any doubt! Nor are the good Germans conscious of this when they admire him as the man of the foremost and most distinguished society and gladly let him ‘set the tone’. And so he does! First it is the sergeants and the noncommissioned officers who imitate and coarsen his tone. Just listen to the shouted commands that positively surround German cities with a roar now that they drill outside all the gates: what presumptuousness, what raging sense of authority, what scornful coldness reverberates from this roar! Are the Germans really supposed to be a musical people? It is certain that the Germans are becoming militarized in the sound of their language; it is probable that once they have got used to speaking in a military tone, they will eventually also start writing that way. For being used to certain sounds has a profound effect on character – one soon has the words and phrases, and finally also the thoughts that fit this sound! Maybe the Germans already write like officers; maybe I just read too little of what is written in Germany. But one thing I know more certainly: the public German proclamations that also reach other countries are inspired not by German music but by this new sound of a distasteful presumptuousness. In almost every speech of the foremost German statesman, and even when he lets himself be heard only through his imperial mouthpiece,73 is an accent that repels with revulsion the ear of a foreigner. But the Germans endure it – they endure themselves.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>105</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/105/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/105/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Germans as artists.&lt;/em&gt; – When the German really works up a passion (and not merely the usual good will to passion!), he behaves as he must, and thinks no further about his behaviour. But the truth is that his behaviour is then very clumsy and ugly, as if lacking in tact and melody, so that the spectators merely have their own feelings of embarrassment or pathos and nothing more – &lt;em&gt;unless&lt;/em&gt; he elevates himself into that state of sublimity and rapture, of which many passions are capable. Then even the German becomes &lt;em&gt;beautiful!&lt;/em&gt; An idea of &lt;em&gt;the height at which&lt;/em&gt; beauty first begins to pour its magic even over Germans drives the German artists into the heights and superheights and excesses of passion: in other words, a genuinely deep desire to rise beyond, at least look beyond, the ugliness and clumsiness – to a better, lighter, more southern, sunnier world. And so their cramps are often just indications that they would like to &lt;em&gt;dance:&lt;/em&gt; these poor bears in which hidden nymphs and sylvan gods are at work – and at times still higher deities!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>106</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/106/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/106/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Music as advocate&lt;/em&gt; – ‘I am thirsting for a master composer’, said an innovator to his disciple, ‘who can learn my thoughts from me and hereafter speak them in his language: that way I will better penetrate into people’s ears and hearts. With tones one can seduce people into every error and every truth: who could &lt;em&gt;refute&lt;/em&gt; a tone?’ – ‘So you would like to be considered irrefutable?’ said his disciple. The innovator replied: ‘I wish for the sprout to become a tree. For a teaching to become a tree, it has to be believed for a good while; for it to be believed, it has to be considered irrefutable. The tree needs storms, doubts, worms, and malice in order to reveal the nature and strength of its sprout; may it break if it is not strong enough! But a sprout can only be destroyed – not refuted!’ When he had said that, his disciple cried impetuously: ‘But I believe in your cause and consider it so strong that I will say everything, everything that I still have on my mind against it’. The innovator laughed to himself and wagged a finger at him. ‘This kind of discipleship’, he said, ‘is the best, but it is dangerous and not every kind of teaching can withstand it’.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>107</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/107/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/2_Book_Two/107/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our ultimate gratitude to art.&lt;/em&gt; – Had we not approved of the arts and invented this type of cult of the untrue, the insight into general untruth and mendacity that is now given to us by science – the insight into delusion and error as a condition of cognitive and sensate existence – would be utterly unbearable. &lt;em&gt;Honesty&lt;/em&gt; would lead to nausea and suicide. But now our honesty has a counterforce that helps us avoid such consequences: art, as the &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; will to appearance. We do not always keep our eyes from rounding off, from finishing off the poem; and then it is no longer eternal imperfection that we carry across the river of becoming – we then feel that we are carrying a &lt;em&gt;goddess,&lt;/em&gt; and are proud and childish in performing this service. As an aesthetic phenomenon existence is still &lt;em&gt;bearable&lt;/em&gt; to us, and art furnishes us with the eye and hand and above all the good conscience to be &lt;em&gt;able&lt;/em&gt; to make such a phenomenon of ourselves. At times we need to have a rest from ourselves by looking at and down at ourselves and, from an artistic distance, laughing &lt;em&gt;at&lt;/em&gt; ourselves or crying &lt;em&gt;at&lt;/em&gt; ourselves; we have to discover the &lt;em&gt;hero&lt;/em&gt; no less than the &lt;em&gt;fool&lt;/em&gt; in our passion for knowledge; we must now and then be pleased about our folly in order to be able to stay pleased about our wisdom! And precisely because we are at bottom grave and serious human beings and more weights than human beings, nothing does us as much good as the &lt;em&gt;fool’s cap:&lt;/em&gt; we need it against ourselves – we need all exuberant, floating, dancing, mocking, childish, and blissful art lest we lose that &lt;em&gt;freedom over things&lt;/em&gt; that our ideal demands of us. It would be a &lt;em&gt;relapse&lt;/em&gt; for us, with our irritable honesty, to get completely caught up in morality and, for the sake of the overly severe demands that we there make on ourselves, to become virtuous monsters and scarecrows. We have also to &lt;em&gt;be able&lt;/em&gt; to stand &lt;em&gt;above&lt;/em&gt; morality – and not just to stand with the anxious stiffness of someone who is afraid of slipping and falling at any moment, but also to float and play above it! How then could we possibly do without art and with the fool? – And as long as you are in any way &lt;em&gt;ashamed&lt;/em&gt; of yourselves, you do not yet belong amongst us!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
