<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Leviathan 99 on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/leviathan_99/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Leviathan 99 on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/leviathan_99/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/leviathan_99/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/leviathan_99/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Call me Ishmael.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ishmael? In this year 2099 when strange new ships head beyond the stars instead of merely toward them? Attack the stars instead of fearing them? A name like Ishmael?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Yes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My parents flew with the first brave ones to Mars. Turned less than brave, gone sick for Earth, they returned home. Conceived on that journey, I was born in space.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My father knew his Bible and recalled another outcast who wandered dead seas long years before Christ.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/leviathan_99/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/leviathan_99/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Oh, the logistics of the rocket. Computerize the billion and one decisions. Ten thousand nursing bottles filled with super-homogenized gunk for space children. Fresh air produced by glass-enclosed botanical gardens. Sweat recycled into sweet water by machines.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ring all the bells and klaxons. Flash the lights and prepare the thunders. Men and women run.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Quell and I stood by the gantry, staring up at the giant ship. It had been a week since our strange encounter with Elijah, seven days filled with intense activity as the &lt;em&gt;Cetus 7&lt;/em&gt; crew, of which we were now members, prepared the ship for voyage.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/leviathan_99/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/leviathan_99/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A voice boomed over the loudspeakers. “The captain is in quarters, prepare for countdown.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The crew all hurried to their assigned stations, suited up and strapped in. The great doors were shut and sealed, the gantries rolled away, the engines fired up.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Minus one and counting.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We lay waiting for the fire-wind to seize and throw us at the sky.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And seize and throw it did.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Oh my God, I thought. Help me to shout, “We rise, we rise.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/leviathan_99/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/leviathan_99/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I backed off and returned to my cabin, deeply distressed. I barely slept the hours remaining till dawn, instead tossing and turning in my bunk, while Quell lay undisturbed, dreaming who knows what alien dreams.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At the first bell, I rose and made my way to the communications deck. There I found crewman Small, bent over his console.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Do you know that a rocket feeds itself in space?” he asked.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/leviathan_99/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/leviathan_99/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From Small’s console came dim voices, cloaked in static, from untold miles away: “&lt;em&gt;Lightfall 1&lt;/em&gt; calling &lt;em&gt;Cetus 7. Lightfall&lt;/em&gt; here. Inbound from twelve years out. &lt;em&gt;Cetus 7,&lt;/em&gt; do you read?”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My God, I thought, another spacecraft.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Quell’s voice touched my thoughts. “Impossible. In all these billions of miles of space. What are the chances of meeting—”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Another spaceship?” I asked aloud.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“This is &lt;em&gt;Lightfall 1,&lt;/em&gt;” came the voice again. “Shall we hang fire, &lt;em&gt;Cetus 7&lt;/em&gt;?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/leviathan_99/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/leviathan_99/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Deep in the false night, our captain walked along the sleeping quarter corridors. Quell scanned his mind and spoke his words to me in whispers: “‘What, pretending at sleep? Do that, and bite your bitter tongues, which hate me for spoiled games. But if Christ Himself walked through space this night—’”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And Quell, speaking in his own voice, added: “Not Christ. But one of His lost shepherds.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The next morning, Redleigh summoned Quell and me to Small’s communication console. There we met crewman Downs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/leviathan_99/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/leviathan_99/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At last Redleigh said, “Well?”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And Downs lifted his head and looked straight at the first mate and said, “That was unlawful, uncommon, criminal eavesdropping. We have no right!”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Upon uncommon &lt;em&gt;dangers&lt;/em&gt;!”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Would you mutiny, sir?” said Small.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Redleigh pulled back, a horrified look on his face. “Mutiny?!”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Quell broke in. “He would … &lt;em&gt;take over.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And we answered mutely, with our own horrified faces.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Redleigh said, “Have you not just heard what is in his heart, what he intends to do?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/leviathan_99/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/leviathan_99/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“Mr. Redleigh, you have come to mutiny.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The captain had granted us entrance to his quarters and he stood within, facing us, his strange white eyes seeming to stare.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Sir,” said Redleigh. “The simple fact is—”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The captain interrupted. “Simple? The sun’s temperature is 20,000 degrees. Yet it will burn Earth. Simple? I distrust people who come with plain facts and then preach calamities. Now, Redleigh, listen. I am giving over command of this spacecraft to you.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/leviathan_99/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/leviathan_99/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The trembling became more convulsive, the light on the screen more erratic. The sound grew loud, but, we knew, it was not the immense sound Leviathan might make when it arrived.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Captain,” said Redleigh. “Permission to turn back. We’ll be destroyed.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Head on, Mr. Redleigh,” said the captain. “It’s merely testing us.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The storm on the screen rose and fell and rose again. And then, a sudden silence.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“What?” said Redleigh.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/leviathan_99/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/leviathan_99/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Quell’s mind moved outside the ship to find the captain, alone.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And though I could not see, I heard, and what the captain finally said was this: “What? Nothing? All quiet, gone, spent? Is this the end? No more the hunt, the journey, and the goal? That terrifies me most: No more the goal! From here on then, what is the captain for? What does he do, if time and circumstance knock all the mountains down to one dull flat and endless plain, one long bleak winter afternoon, not even tea and simple bread to brighten it?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/leviathan_99/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/leviathan_99/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“Sir?”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Quell came to attention as Downs came on deck.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Sir, your suit is finished.” The engineer held out a suit made of some stiff black material.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Much thanks,” said Quell. “It is a fine piece of work.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Downs tapped on the metal carapace. “I am tempted to die and wear the damned thing myself.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Stick around,” said Quell. “You may get your wish.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Quell!” I said.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Quell stiffened, alert, turning toward me.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
