<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Indian army on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/misc/indian-army/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Indian army on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/misc/indian-army/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Ambushed</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/misc/indian-army/ambushed/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/misc/indian-army/ambushed/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mananbhattnavy/status/1779826380810883311&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ambushed&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;During a military training course in Mhow, India, the 1962 war with China broke out.  My course was cancelled, and everyone returned to their units.  However, I received special orders to stay put and await further instructions.  Two days later, my posting to Jammu and Kashmir arrived – with immediate reporting required.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Having driven my car to Mhow, I had no choice but to take it back to Punjab, leave it there, and then travel on to J&amp;amp;K.  Pressed for time, I decided to drive straight from Mhow to Delhi, a risky decision.  One particularly dangerous stretch was between Gwalior and Agra, notorious for bandits and lawlessness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ethos</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/misc/indian-army/ethos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/misc/indian-army/ethos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A story of Army Ethos&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The desert wind whipped around Naya Chor, a lonely outpost in the vast Sindh Desert. Inside the spartan office, Captain Aditya Singh, the Unit Adjutant, chuckled as the phone buzzed for the umpteenth time that day. He recognized the number – it could only be Jag Ram.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Jag Ram wasn&amp;rsquo;t your typical Subedar Major (SM Sahib). A former wrestler, his imposing size and booming voice were legendary within the battalion. Recruited from the famed &amp;ldquo;Pahlwan&amp;rdquo; (Wrestler) Coy of the Grenadiers, a unit known for its burly Jat soldiers, Jag Ram wasn&amp;rsquo;t just strong – he was a leader. He&amp;rsquo;d represented the Services in wrestling competitions, his dedication earning him the respect of his peers and superiors alike.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
