<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;स्थानेश्वरः on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;स्थानेश्वरः on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Cognition</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/cognition/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/cognition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;metacognition-in-animals&#34;&gt;Metacognition in animals&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Do animals and birds have meta-cognition? We can all agree that animals and birds are conscious, are capable of cognizing, but how can you evaluate your own mental states and repeat the acts that you think are causal in producing the mental state of pleasure in absence of metacognition? Playing for fun is not uncommon among animals or birds. But these also demonstrate mimicry, particularly copying human actions. If they are able to copy human actions and are able to evaluate their mental states, are they also able to evaluate the mental states of the humans that they are copying? And if so, they are also inter-subjectively aware. For me, these are not problems, because the way I understand consciousness is it can never be bereft of reflexivity and inter-subjectivity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Customs</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/customs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/customs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ravana-dies-again&#34;&gt;rAvaNa dies again&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ravana Dies Again&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I remember asking my father after watching Ramlila twice: but they already killed Ravana last year and why did they kill him again? And my father said: you, son, have to kill Ravana again and again till the end of time. I simply failed to comprehend his statement and even forgot about this conversation. After five decades, I came to realize its depth and fathom meaning of repeated death of Ravana.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gods</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/Gods/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/Gods/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;all-knowing&#34;&gt;All-knowing&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Today I am having compassion for the being that is said to be all-knowing. and this compassion extends also to my philosopher colleagues who have extensively worked on omniscience. For every fact, there are millions of fabrications. One cannot actually know what love is like without experiencing it first hand. But what about hate? But I am more worried about knowing things like infinity. I do not think that all-knowing entity has not fathomed it, but then that would be finite. i am perfectly fine to remain ignorant than to know the hair count in every single rat ball, past and future.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Life</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/life/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-order&#34;&gt;The Order&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I remember not being able to articulate the ṛ phoneme, and so when the old man said, &amp;ldquo;ṛtaṃ ca satyaṃ ca,&amp;rdquo; I said, &amp;rsquo;litam ca satyaṃ ca.&amp;quot;+++(4)+++ I must have been four or five. I never thought of what they meant. I was supposed to sing these old songs so many times that every cell in my body was supposed to savor the memory. It was not reciting the mantras but reliving the recollections of hundreds of generations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Money</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/money/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/money/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have observed that even after joining the billionaire&amp;rsquo;s club, a pauper still remains a pauper.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-discovery-of-god&#34;&gt;The discovery of God&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When the aliens encountered a lost civilization on the blue planet, they discovered a giant monolith with the writings &amp;ldquo;In God We Trust.&amp;rdquo; They were able to relate to most of the human concepts but the term God did not resemble any of their  concepts. All their historians, anthropologists, archaeologists, philosophers and sociologists vested their energy to comprehend the signature concept that they found alien.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Other people</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/other-people/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/other-people/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;trust&#34;&gt;Trust&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To trust is to make yourself vulnerable.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;And nobody likes that.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;But all our social transactions are based on trust,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;and so we seek that people trust us.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;To trust is therefore to live in a perpetual dilemma of being shattered.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some of us have surplus of trust.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;We make our trust to translate into our faith.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;And we trust on the dead more than the living.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;And we enter the jungle of solipsism&lt;br&gt;&#xA;when we find the dead ones more trustworthy than the living ones.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>paNDits</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/paNDits/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/paNDits/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;revenge-of-a-logician&#34;&gt;Revenge of a Logician&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Two friends grew up together in their gurukula, school. One studied astrology, another logic. They both became quite established in their fields. The logician (Naiyāyika) wrote a good number of commentaries and introduced some new categories. The astrologer made tons of money. Tired of his poverty, the logician embarked to see his successful friend and ask for his help.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is hard to imagine how quickly people change when they become successful. The astrologer could not stop making fun of the poor logician for the choice of his subject. And the villagers laughed at his cost. Heart-broken, the logician said farewell. When his friend tried to give him some money, he asked for just one single hair. The astrologer happily pulled one hair and gave it as a gift.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Places</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/places/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/places/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ecological-concern&#34;&gt;Ecological concern&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ecological concern is not just an environmental concern; it also is not our concern for other species. at the end of the day, it is the search for our own lost soul. we are the only species capable of making a difference and saving species. nature has given us that power. it is about how we embrace our responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;kalis-magic&#34;&gt;Kali&amp;rsquo;s Magic&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I could not resist the temptation to climb up the little mound right next to the town. After the sunset, mountains wake up with their own music of silence and the blanket of darkness only makes them luminous nothing. It was just a hike of ten minutes and I wanted to capture this moment while my brother was still a company.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Politics</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/politics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/politics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;shorts&#34;&gt;Shorts&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Long ago in Nepal, people elected their leader by a marathon. Inspired by this, I believe we can have a similar system. Rather than a race, we should let the best comedian win.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;in-defense-of-her-majesty&#34;&gt;In Defense of Her Majesty&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is ridiculous for me to reconsider monarchy after four decades, as the first time I marched in the streets of Kathmandu against monarchy, I was just a teenager. But then, I had not watched The Truman Show; it was not even made. Hollywood did exist, but I had not read Baudrillard.   I did attend some carnivals but nobody even mentioned Bakhtin. My support is not for power but for grandiose, for extravagance and for the simulacra. With the royals around, we all can appreciate the Lorde within each of us.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shorts</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/shorts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/shorts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;masks&#34;&gt;Masks&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are moments when the mask fails to hide the face behind.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;books&#34;&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Books, I think, are like fruit trees. As long as you take care of them, they keep giving new fruits every new season.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;right-and-left&#34;&gt;right and left&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;there was this guy named empire with massive manhood. he named his two balls right and left.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Teachers</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/teachers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/teachers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;shorts&#34;&gt;Shorts&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When there were teachers, I was not ready to listen.  When I opened my ears, they were gone.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;teachers-never-die&#34;&gt;Teachers Never Die&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Teachers Never Die. I used this exact copy of Bhuṣaṇasāra 35 years ago, when I studied with Bidur Paudyal. My friends evolved and did great many things in their lives. I, on the other hand, am stuck with the same old book, reminiscing the old times. Students are transitory. Teachers are transitory. All these relations are preconditions for the power beyond our being to express itself.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tech</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/tech/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/tech/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;are-you-human&#34;&gt;Are you human?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Every time I log onto something, I am asked serious questions, like right now, I am reviewing a paper for a journal and the system asks me to click, &amp;ldquo;I am a human.&amp;rdquo; Often times, I have been asked to confirm, I am not a robot. Is there any room left for the skeptics like myself in this world?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;liking&#34;&gt;Liking&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Facebook is making our concept of liking very shallow. When I clicked like for one page it said I already liked it. There is no room for me to like the same thing again and again. Well this says all about the Facebook likes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transcendence</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/transcendence/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/transcendence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;shorts&#34;&gt;Shorts&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Every society or civilization is founded on myth. It is not the power of  truth but of myth that keeps the culture alive. The first liberation is to free oneself from these constructions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;freedom&#34;&gt;Freedom&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is the inner drive, a surge of being that overpowers the conditions of us being in whichever states. This is not a judgment upon something, this is not a philosophy or politics. We do not explore freedom, it is the other way around. It is the freedom that has found us and freedom will keep finding all the new forms.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Word</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/word/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/sthAneshvaraH/word/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;poetic-vision&#34;&gt;Poetic vision&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We are woven twice, in two different layers of our being. The first is when the being or sat expressed itself, it being manifest as mantras. We then were the songs articulated by the first poet, Brahmā. But his poetry lacked shades and needed more colors to be infused. His grandson Shukra made it possible, weaving the threads, the chandas, once again. His love for Divyā, a demon princess with a divine name, explains the paradox behind this poetic vision. Sapped with his vigor and lust, poetry came to life, with the lineage of both gods and demons. We can still distill the mantras of the grandfather in the songs of Shukra.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
