<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Ecce homo on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Ecce homo on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>00</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/00/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/00/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;author-intro&#34;&gt;Author intro&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;FRIEDRICH NIETZSCHE was born near Leipzig in 1844, the son of a Lutheran clergyman. He attended the famous Pforta School, then went to university at Bonn and at Leipzig, where he studied philology and read Schopenhauer. When he was only twenty-four he was appointed to the chair of classical philology at Basle University; he stayed there until his health forced him into retirement in 1879. While at Basle he made and broke his friendship with Wagner, participated as an ambulance orderly in the Franco-Prussian War, and published &lt;em&gt;The Birth of Tragedy&lt;/em&gt; (1872), &lt;em&gt;Untimely Meditations&lt;/em&gt; (1873–6) and the first two parts of &lt;em&gt;Human, All Too Human&lt;/em&gt; (1878–9). From 1880 until his final collapse in 1889, except for brief interludes, he divorced himself from everyday life and, supported by his university pension, he lived mainly in France, Italy and Switzerland. The third part of &lt;em&gt;Human, All Too Human&lt;/em&gt; appeared in 1880, followed by &lt;em&gt;The Dawn&lt;/em&gt; in 1881. &lt;em&gt;Thus Spoke Zarathustra&lt;/em&gt; was written between 1883 and 1885, and his last completed books were &lt;em&gt;Ecce Homo&lt;/em&gt;, an autobiography, and &lt;em&gt;Nietzsche contra Wagner&lt;/em&gt;. He became insane in 1889 and remained in a condition of mental and physical paralysis until his death in 1900.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>01 HOW ONE BECOMES WHAT ONE IS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/01_HOW_ONE_BECOMES_WHAT_ONE_IS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/01_HOW_ONE_BECOMES_WHAT_ONE_IS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;foreword&#34;&gt;FOREWORD&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;SEEING that I must shortly approach mankind with the heaviest demand that has ever been made on it, it seems to me indispensable to say &lt;em&gt;who I am&lt;/em&gt;. This ought really to be known already: for I have not neglected to ‘bear witness’ about myself. But the disparity between the greatness of my task and the &lt;em&gt;smallness&lt;/em&gt; of my contemporaries has found expression in the fact that I have been neither heard nor even so much as seen. I live on my own credit, it is perhaps merely a prejudice that I am alive at all?… I need only to talk with any of the ‘cultured people’ who come to the Ober-Engadin in the summer to convince myself that I am &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; alive… Under these circumstances there exists a duty against which my habit, even more the pride of my instincts revolts, namely to say: &lt;em&gt;Listen to me! for I am thus and thus. Do not, above all, confound me with what I am not!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 WHY I AM SO WISE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/02_WHY_I_AM_SO_WISE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/02_WHY_I_AM_SO_WISE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;THE fortunateness of my existence, its uniqueness perhaps, lies in its fatality: to express it in the form of a riddle, as my father I have already died, as my mother I still live and grow old. This twofold origin, as it were from the highest and the lowest rung of the ladder of life, at once &lt;em&gt;décadent&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;beginning&lt;/em&gt; – this if anything explains that neutrality, that freedom from party in relation to the total problem of life which perhaps distinguishes me. I have a subtler sense for signs of ascent and decline than any man has ever had, I am the teacher &lt;em&gt;par excellence&lt;/em&gt; in this matter – I know both, I am both. – My father died at the age of thirty-six: he was delicate, lovable and morbid, like a being destined to pay this world only a passing visit – a gracious reminder of life rather than life itself. In the same year in which his life declined mine too declined: in the thirty-sixth year of my life I arrived at the lowest point of my vitality – I still lived, but without being able to see three paces in front of me. At that time – it was 1879 – I relinquished my Basel professorship, lived through the summer like a shadow in St Moritz and the following winter, the most sunless of my life, &lt;em&gt;as&lt;/em&gt; a shadow in Naumburg. This was my minimum: ‘The Wanderer and his Shadow’ came into existence during the course of it. I undoubtedly knew all about shadows in those days… In the following winter, the first winter I spent in Genoa, that sweetening and spiritualization which is virtually inseparable from an extreme poverty of blood and muscle produced ‘Daybreak’. The perfect brightness and cheerfulness, even exuberance of spirit reflected in the said work is in my case compatible not only with the profoundest physiological weakness, but even with an extremity of pain. In the midst of the torments which attended an uninterrupted three-day headache accompanied by the laborious vomiting of phlegm – I possessed a dialectical clarity &lt;em&gt;par excellence&lt;/em&gt; and thought my way very cold-bloodedly through things for which when I am in better health I am not enough of a climber, not refined, not &lt;em&gt;cold&lt;/em&gt; enough. My readers perhaps know the extent to which I regard dialectics as a symptom of &lt;em&gt;décadence,&lt;/em&gt; for example in the most famous case of all: in the case of Socrates. – All morbid disturbances of the intellect, even that semi-stupefaction consequent on fever, have remained to this day totally unfamiliar things to me, on their nature and frequency I had first to instruct myself by scholarly methods. My blood flows slowly. No one has ever been able to diagnose fever in me. A doctor who treated me for some time as a nervous case said at last: ‘No! there is nothing wrong with your nerves, it is only I who am nervous.’ Any kind of local degeneration absolutely undemonstrable; no organically originating stomach ailment, though there does exist, as a consequence of general exhaustion, a profound weakness of the gastric system. Condition of the eyes, sometimes approaching dangerously close to blindness, also only consequence, not causal: so that with every increase in vitality eyesight has also again improved. – Convalescence means with me a long, all too long succession of years – it also unfortunately means relapse, deterioration, periods of a kind of &lt;em&gt;décadence.&lt;/em&gt; After all this do I need to say that in questions of &lt;em&gt;décadence&lt;/em&gt; I am &lt;em&gt;experienced?&lt;/em&gt; I have spelled it out forwards and backwards. Even that filigree art of grasping and comprehending in general, that finger for nuances, that psychology of ‘looking around the corner’ and whatever else characterizes me was learned only then, is the actual gift of that time in which everything in me became more subtle, observation itself together with all the organs of observation. To look from a morbid perspective towards &lt;em&gt;healthier&lt;/em&gt; concepts and values, and again conversely to look down from the abundance and certainty of &lt;em&gt;rich&lt;/em&gt; life into the secret labour of the instinct of &lt;em&gt;décadence&lt;/em&gt; – that is what I have practised most, it has been my own particular field of experience, in this if in anything I am a master. I now have the skill and knowledge to &lt;em&gt;invert perspectives:&lt;/em&gt; first reason why a ‘revaluation of values’ is perhaps possible at all to me alone. –&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 WHY I AM SO CLEVER</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/03_WHY_I_AM_SO_CLEVER/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/03_WHY_I_AM_SO_CLEVER/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;− WHY do I know a few &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; things? Why am I so clever altogether? I have never reflected on questions that are none − I have not squandered myself. − I have, for example, no experience of actual &lt;em&gt;religious&lt;/em&gt; difficulties. I am entirely at a loss to know to what extent I ought to have felt ‘sinful’. I likewise lack a reliable criterion of a pang of conscience: from what one &lt;em&gt;bears&lt;/em&gt; of it, a pang of conscience does not seem to me anything respectable… I should not like to leave an act in the lurch &lt;em&gt;afterwards,&lt;/em&gt; I would as a matter of principle prefer to leave the evil outcome, the &lt;em&gt;consequences,&lt;/em&gt; out of the question of values. When the outcome is evil one can easily lose the &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; eye for what one has done: a pang of conscience seems to me a kind of ‘&lt;em&gt;evil&lt;/em&gt; eye’. To honour to oneself something that went wrong all the more &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; it went wrong − that rather would accord with my morality. − ‘God’, ‘immortality of the soul’, ‘redemption’, ‘the Beyond’, all of them concepts to which I have given no attention and no time, not even as a child − perhaps I was never childish enough for it? − I have absolutely no knowledge of atheism as an outcome of reasoning, still less as an event: with me it is obvious by instinct. I am too inquisitive, too &lt;em&gt;questionable,&lt;/em&gt; too high spirited to rest content with a crude answer. God is a crude answer, a piece of indelicacy against us thinkers − fundamentally even a crude &lt;em&gt;prohibition&lt;/em&gt; to us: you shall not think!… I am interested in quite a different way in a question upon which the ‘salvation of mankind’ depends far more than it does upon any kind of quaint curiosity of the theologians: the question of &lt;em&gt;nutriment.&lt;/em&gt; One can for convenience’ sake formulate it thus: ‘how to nourish yourself so as to attain your maximum of strength, of &lt;em&gt;virtù&lt;/em&gt; in the Renaissance style, of moraline-free virtue?’ – My experiences here are as bad as they possibly could be; I am astonished that I heard this question so late, that I learned ‘reason’ from these experiences so late. Only the perfect worthlessness of our German education – its ‘idealism’ – can to some extent explain to me why on precisely this point I was backward to the point of holiness. This ‘education’ which from the first teaches one to lose sight of &lt;em&gt;realities&lt;/em&gt; so as to hunt after altogether problematic, so-called ‘ideal’ objectives, ‘classical education’ for example − as if it were not from the first an utterly fruitless undertaking to try to unite ‘classical’ and ‘German’ in &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; concept! It is, moreover, mirth-provoking − just think of a ‘classically educated’ Leipziger! − Until my very maturest years I did in fact eat &lt;em&gt;badly&lt;/em&gt; − in the language of morals ‘impersonally’, ‘selflessly’, ‘altruistically’, for the salvation of cooks and other fellow Christians. With the aid of Leipzig cookery, for example, which accompanied my earliest study of Schopenhauer (1865), I very earnestly denied my ‘will to live’. To ruin one’s stomach so as to receive inadequate nutriment − the aforesaid cookery seems to me to solve this problem wonderfully well. (It is said that 1866 produced a change in this domain −.) But German cookery in general − what does it not have on its conscience! Soup &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; the meal (in Venetian cookery books of the sixteenth century still called &lt;em&gt;alla tedesca&lt;/em&gt;); meat cooked to shreds, greasy and floury vegetables; the degeneration of puddings to paperweights! If one adds to this the downright bestial dinner-drinking habits of the ancient and by no means only the &lt;em&gt;ancient&lt;/em&gt; Germans one will also understand the origin of the &lt;em&gt;German spirit&lt;/em&gt; − disturbed intestines… The German spirit is an indigestion, it can have done with nothing. − But to the &lt;em&gt;English&lt;/em&gt; diet too, which compared with the Germans, even with the French, is a kind of ‘return to nature’, that is to say to cannibalism, my own instinct is profoundly opposed; it seems to me to give the spirit &lt;em&gt;heavy&lt;/em&gt; feet − the feet of Englishwomen… The best cookery is that of &lt;em&gt;Piedmont.&lt;/em&gt; Aleoholic drinks are no good for me; a glass of wine or beer a day is quite enough to make life for me a ‘Vale of Tears’ – Munich is where my antipodes live. Granted I was a little late to grasp this – I &lt;em&gt;experienced&lt;/em&gt; it really from childhood onwards. As a boy I believed wine-drinking to be, like tobacco-smoking, at first only a vanity of young men, later a habit. Perhaps the wine of Naumburg is in part to blame for this &lt;em&gt;austere&lt;/em&gt; judgement. To believe that wine &lt;em&gt;makes cheerful&lt;/em&gt; I would have to be a Christian, that is to say believe what is for precisely me an absurdity. Oddly enough, while I am put extremely out of sorts by &lt;em&gt;small,&lt;/em&gt; much diluted doses of alcohol, I am almost turned into a sailor when it comes to &lt;em&gt;strong&lt;/em&gt; doses. Even as a boy I showed how brave I was in this respect. To write a long Latin essay in a &lt;em&gt;single&lt;/em&gt; night’s sitting and then go on to make a fair copy of it, with the ambition in my pen to imitate in severity and concision my model Sallust, and to pour a quantity of grog of the heaviest calibre over my Latin, was even when I was a pupil of venerable Schulpforta in no way opposed to my physiology, nor perhaps to that of Sallust – however much it might have been to venerable Schulpforta… Later, towards the middle of life, I decided, to be sure, more and more strictly &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; any sort of ‘spirituous’ drink: an opponent of vegetarianism from experience, just like Richard Wagner, who converted me, I cannot advise all &lt;em&gt;more spiritual&lt;/em&gt; natures too seriously to abstain from alcohol absolutely. &lt;em&gt;Water&lt;/em&gt; suffices… I prefer places in which there is everywhere opportunity to drink from flowing fountains (Nice, Turin, Sils); a small glass runs after me like a dog. &lt;em&gt;In vino Veritas:&lt;/em&gt; it seems that here too I am again at odds with all the world over the concept ‘truth’ − with me the spirit moves over the water… A couple more signposts from my morality. A big meal is easier to digest than one too small. That the stomach comes into action as a whole, first precondition of a good digestion. One has to &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; the size of one’s stomach. For the same reason those tedious meals should be avoided which I call interrupted sacrificial feasts, those at the &lt;em&gt;table d’hôte.&lt;/em&gt; − No eating between meals, no coffee: coffee makes gloomy. &lt;em&gt;Tea&lt;/em&gt; beneficial only in the morning. Little, but strong: tea very detrimental and sicklying o’er the whole day if it is the slightest bit too weak. Each has here his own degree, often between the narrowest and most delicate limits. In a very &lt;em&gt;agaçant&lt;/em&gt; climate it is inadvisable to start with tea: one should start an hour earlier with a cup of thick oil-free cocoa. − &lt;em&gt;Sit&lt;/em&gt; as little as possible; credit no thought not born in the open air and while moving freely about − in which the muscles too do not hold a festival. All prejudices come from the intestines. − Assiduity − I have said it once before − the actual &lt;em&gt;sin&lt;/em&gt; against the holy spirit. −&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 WHY I WRITE SUCH GOOD BOOKS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/04_WHY_I_WRITE_SUCH_GOOD_BOOKS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/04_WHY_I_WRITE_SUCH_GOOD_BOOKS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I AM one thing, my writings are another. – Here, before I speak of these writings themselves, I shall touch on the question of their being understood or &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; understood. I shall do so as perfunctorily as is fitting: for the time for this question has certainly not yet come. My time has not yet come, some are born posthumously. – One day or other institutions will be needed in which people live and teach as I understand living and teaching: perhaps even chairs for the interpretation of Zarathustra will be established. But it would be a complete contradiction of myself if I expected ears &lt;em&gt;and hands&lt;/em&gt; for &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; truths already today: that I am not heard today, that no one today knows how to take from me, is not only comprehensible; it even seems to me right. I do not want to be taken for what I am not – and that requires that I do not take myself for what I am not. To say it again, little of ‘ill will’ can be shown in my life; neither would I be able to speak of barely a single case of ‘literary ill will’. On the other hand all too much of &lt;em&gt;pure folly&lt;/em&gt;!… It seems to me that to take a book of mine into his hands is one of the rarest distinctions anyone can confer upon himself – I even assume he removes his shoes when he does so – not to speak of boots… When Doctor Heinrich von Stein once honestly complained that he understood not one word of my Zarathustra, I told him that was quite in order: to have understood, that is to say &lt;em&gt;experienced&lt;/em&gt;, six sentences of that book would raise one to a higher level of mortals than ‘modern’ man could attain to. How &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; I, with &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; feeling of distance, even want the ‘modern men’ I know – to read me! – My triumph is precisely the opposite of Schopenhauer’s – I say ‘non &lt;em&gt;legor&lt;/em&gt;, non &lt;em&gt;legar&lt;/em&gt;’. – Not that I should like to underestimate the pleasure which the &lt;em&gt;innocence&lt;/em&gt; in the rejection of my writings has given me. This very summer just gone, at a time when, with my own weighty, too heavily weighty literature, I was perhaps throwing all the rest of literature off its balance, a professor of Berlin University kindly gave me to understand that I ought really to avail myself of a different form: no one read stuff like mine. – In the end it was not Germany but Switzerland which offered me the two extreme cases. An essay of Dr V. Widmann in the &lt;em&gt;Bund&lt;/em&gt; on ‘Beyond Good and Evil’ under the title ‘Nietzsche’s Dangerous Book’, and a general report on my books as a whole on the part of Herr Karl Spitteler, also in the &lt;em&gt;Bund,&lt;/em&gt; constitute a maximum in my life – of what I take care not to say… The latter, for example, dealt with my Zarathustra as an &lt;em&gt;advanced exercise in style&lt;/em&gt;, with the request that I might later try to provide some content; Dr Widmann expressed his respect for the courage with which I strive to abolish all decent feelings. – Through a little trick of chance every sentence here was, with a consistency I had to admire, a truth stood on its head: remarkably enough, all one had to do was to ‘revalue all values’ in order to hit the nail on the head with regard to me – instead of hitting my head with a nail… All the more reason for me to attempt an explanation. – Ultimately, no one can extract from things, books included, more than he already knows. What one has no access to through experience one has no ear for. Now let us imagine an extreme case: that a book speaks of nothing but events which lie outside the possibility of general or even of rare experience – that it is the &lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt; language for a new range of experiences. In this case simply nothing will be heard, with the acoustical illusion that where nothing is heard there &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; nothing… This is in fact my average experience and, if you like, the &lt;em&gt;originality&lt;/em&gt; of my experience. Whoever believed he had understood something of me had dressed up something out of me after his own image – not uncommonly an antithesis of me, for instance an ‘idealist’; whoever had understood nothing of me denied that I came into consideration at all. – The word ‘superman’ to designate a type that has turned out supremely well, in antithesis to ‘modern’ men, to ‘good’ men, to Christians and other nihilists – a word which, in the mouth of a Zarathustra, the &lt;em&gt;destroyer&lt;/em&gt; of morality, becomes a very thoughtful word – has almost everywhere been understood with perfect innocence in the sense of those values whose antithesis makes its appearance in the figure of Zarathustra: that is to say as an ‘idealistic’ type of higher species of man, half ‘saint’, half ‘genius’… Other learned cattle caused me on its account to be suspected of Darwinism; even the ‘hero cult’ of that great unconscious and involuntary counterfeiter Carlyle which I rejected so maliciously has been recognized in it. He into whose ear I whispered he ought to look around rather for a Cesare Borgia than for a Parsifal did not believe his ears. – That I am utterly incurious about discussions of my books, especially by newspapers, will have to be forgiven me. My friends, my publishers know this and do not speak to me about such things. In a particular instance I once had a sight of all the sins that had been committed against a single book – it was ‘Beyond Good and Evil’; I could tell a pretty story about that. Would you believe it that the ‘Nationalzeitung’ – a Prussian newspaper, for my foreign readers – I myself read, if I may say so, only the Journal des Débats – could in all seriousness understand the book as a ‘sign of the times’, as the real genuine &lt;em&gt;Junker philosophy&lt;/em&gt; for which the ‘Kreuzzeitung’ merely lacked the courage?…&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 THE BIRTH OF TRAGEDY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/05_THE_BIRTH_OF_TRAGEDY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/05_THE_BIRTH_OF_TRAGEDY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;IN order to be just to ‘The Birth of Tragedy’ (1872) one will have to forget a few things. It made its &lt;em&gt;effect&lt;/em&gt; and even exercised fascination through what was wrong with it − through its application to &lt;em&gt;Wagnerism,&lt;/em&gt; as if this were a symptom of a &lt;em&gt;beginning.&lt;/em&gt; That is what made this book an event in Wagner’s life: it was only from then on that great hopes surrounded the name Wagner. Even today people remind me, sometimes in the middle of Parsifal, that it is really I who have it on my conscience that so high an opinion of the &lt;em&gt;cultural value&lt;/em&gt; of this movement has come to predominate. − I have often found the book cited as ‘the Rebirth of Tragedy out of the Spirit of Music’: people have had ears only for a new formula for the art, the intention, the task of &lt;em&gt;Wagner −&lt;/em&gt; what of value was concealed in the book was thereby not listened to. ‘Hellenism and Pessimism’: that would have been a less ambiguous tide: that is to say as a first instruction in how the Greeks got rid of pessimism − with what they &lt;em&gt;overcame&lt;/em&gt; it… Precisely tragedy is the proof that the Greeks were &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; pessimists: Schopenhauer blundered in this as he blundered in everything. − Taken up and viewed impartially, ‘The Birth of Tragedy’ looks very untimely: one would not dream it was &lt;em&gt;begun&lt;/em&gt; amid the thunders of the battle of Wörth. I thought these problems through before the walls of Metz, in cold September nights while serving in the medical corps; one would rather believe the book to be fifty years older. It is politically indifferent − ‘un-German’ one would say today − it smells offensively Hegelian, it is in only a few formulas infected with the cadaverous perfume of Schopenhauer. An ‘idea’ − the antithesis Dionysian and Apollonian − translated into the metaphysical; history itself as the evolution of this ‘idea’; in tragedy this antithesis elevated to a unity; from this perspective things which had never before caught sight of one another suddenly confronted with one another, illuminated by one another and &lt;em&gt;comprehended…&lt;/em&gt; for example opera and revolution… The book’s two decisive &lt;em&gt;novelties&lt;/em&gt; are, firstly the understanding of the &lt;em&gt;dionysian&lt;/em&gt; phenomenon in the case of the Greeks − it offers the first psychology of this phenomenon, it sees in it the sole root of the whole of Hellenic art − The other novelty is the understanding of Socratism: Socrates for the first time recognized as an agent of Hellenic disintegration, as a typical &lt;em&gt;décadent.&lt;/em&gt; ‘Rationality’ &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; instinct. ‘Rationality’ at any price as dangerous, as a force undermining life! − A profound hostile silence with regard to Christianity throughout the book. Christianity is neither Apollonian nor Dionysian, it &lt;em&gt;negates&lt;/em&gt; all &lt;em&gt;aesthetic&lt;/em&gt; values − the only values ‘The Birth of Tragedy’ recognizes: it is in the profoundest sense nihilistic, while in the Dionysian symbol there is attained the extreme limit of &lt;em&gt;affirmation.&lt;/em&gt; In one place the Christian priests are alluded to as a ‘malicious species of dwarfs’, as ‘subterraneans’…&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 THE UNTIMELY ESSAYS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/06_THE_UNTIMELY_ESSAYS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/06_THE_UNTIMELY_ESSAYS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;THE four &lt;em&gt;untimely essays&lt;/em&gt; are altogether warlike. They demonstrate that I was no ‘Jack o’ Dreams’, that I derive pleasure from drawing the sword − also, perhaps, that I have a dangerously supple wrist. The &lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt; attack (1873) was on German culture, which even at that time I already looked down on with remorseless contempt. Without meaning, without substance, without aim: a mere ‘public opinion’. There is no more vicious misunderstanding than to believe that the Germans’ great success in arms could demonstrate anything in favour of this culture − not to speak of &lt;em&gt;its&lt;/em&gt; victory over France… The &lt;em&gt;second&lt;/em&gt; untimely essay (1874) brings to light what is dangerous, what gnaws at and poisons life, in our way of carrying on science −: life &lt;em&gt;sick&lt;/em&gt; with this inhuman clockwork and mechanism, with the ‘&lt;em&gt;im&lt;/em&gt;personality’ of the worker, with the false economy of ‘division of labour’. The &lt;em&gt;goal&lt;/em&gt; gets lost, culture − the means, the modern way of carrying on science, &lt;em&gt;barbarized&lt;/em&gt;… In this essay the ‘historical sense’ of which this century is so proud is recognized for the first time as a sickness, as a typical sign of decay. − In the &lt;em&gt;third&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;fourth&lt;/em&gt; untimely essays two pictures of the sternest &lt;em&gt;selfishness, self-discipline&lt;/em&gt; are erected against this, as signposts to a &lt;em&gt;higher&lt;/em&gt; concept of culture, to the restoration of the concept ‘culture’: untimely types &lt;em&gt;par excellence,&lt;/em&gt; full of sovereign contempt for all that around them which was called ‘Reich’, ‘culture’, ‘Christianity’, ‘Bismarck’, ‘success’ − Schopenhauer and Wagner &lt;em&gt;or,&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; word, Nietzsche…&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 HUMAN, ALL TOO HUMAN</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/07_HUMAN_ALL_TOO_HUMAN/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/07_HUMAN_ALL_TOO_HUMAN/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With Two Supplements&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘HUMAN, All Too Human’ is the memorial of a crisis. It calls itself a book for &lt;em&gt;free&lt;/em&gt; spirits: almost every sentence in it is the expression of a victory − with this book I liberated myself from that in my nature which &lt;em&gt;did not belong to me.&lt;/em&gt; Idealism does not belong to me: the title says: ‘where &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; see ideal things, &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; see − human, alas all too human things!’… I know humanity &lt;em&gt;better…&lt;/em&gt; The expression ‘free spirit’ should here be understood in no other sense: a spirit that has &lt;em&gt;become free,&lt;/em&gt; that has again seized possession of itself. The tone, the sound of the voice has completely changed: one will find the book sagacious, cool, sometimes harsh and mocking. A certain spirituality of &lt;em&gt;noble&lt;/em&gt; taste seems to be in constant struggle to keep itself aloft above a more passionate current running underneath. In this connection there is significance in the fact that it is actually the hundredth anniversary of the death of Voltaire with which the book as it were apologizes for being published in 1878. For Voltaire is, in contrast to all who have written after him, above all a &lt;em&gt;grandseigneur&lt;/em&gt; of the spirit: precisely what I am too. − The name of Voltaire on a writing by me − that really was progress − &lt;em&gt;towards myself&lt;/em&gt;… If one looks more closely, one discovers a merciless spirit who knows every hiding-place in which the ideal is at home − where it has its castle-keep and as it were its last place of security. With a torch in hand which gives no trembling light I illuminate with piercing brightness this &lt;em&gt;underworld&lt;/em&gt; of the ideal. It is a war, but a war without powder and smoke, without warlike attitudes, without pathos and contorted limbs − all this would still have been ‘idealism’. One error after another is calmly laid on ice, the ideal is not refuted − &lt;em&gt;it freezes…&lt;/em&gt; Here for example ‘the genius’ freezes; on the next corner ‘the saint’ freezes; ‘the hero’ freezes into a thick icicle; at last ‘faith’, so-called ‘conviction’, freezes; ‘pity’ also grows considerably cooler − almost everywhere ‘the thing in itself freezes…&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 DAYBREAK</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/08_DAYBREAK/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/08_DAYBREAK/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thoughts about Morality as a Prejudice&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;i&#34;&gt;I&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;WITH this book begins my campaign against &lt;em&gt;morality.&lt;/em&gt; Not that it smells in the slightest of gunpowder – quite other and more pleasant odours will be perceived in it, provided one has some subtlety in one’s nostrils. Neither big nor even small guns: if the effect of the book is negative, its means are all the less so, means from which the effect follows like a conclusion &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; like a cannon-shot. That one takes leave of the book with a cautious reserve in regard to everything that has hitherto been honoured and even worshipped under the name morality does not contradict the fact that in the entire book there is no negative word, no attack, no malice – that it rather lies in the sun, round, happy, like a sea-beast sunning itself among rocks. In the end it was I myself who was this sea-beast: almost every sentence in the book was thought, &lt;em&gt;tracked down&lt;/em&gt; among that confusion of rocks near to Genoa where I was alone and still shared secrets with the sea. Even now, when I chance to light on this book every sentence becomes for me a spike with which I again draw something incomparable out of the depths: its entire skin trembles with tender shudders of recollection. The art in which it is preeminent is no small one in making things which easily slip by without a sound, moments which I call divine lizards, stay still for a little – not with the cruelty of that young Greek god who simply impaled the poor little lizard, but none the less still with something sharp, with the pen… ‘There are so many daybreaks that have not yet dawned’ – this &lt;em&gt;Indian&lt;/em&gt; inscription stands on the gateway to this book. Where does its author &lt;em&gt;seek&lt;/em&gt; that new dawn, that hitherto still undetected tender roseate sky with which another day – ah, a whole series, a whole world of new days! – breaks? In a &lt;em&gt;revaluation of all values,&lt;/em&gt; in an escape from all moral values, in an affirmation of and trust in all that has hitherto been forbidden, despised, accursed. This &lt;em&gt;affirmative&lt;/em&gt; book pours its light, its love, its tenderness upon nothing but evil things, it restores to them their ‘soul’, the good conscience, the exalted right and &lt;em&gt;privilege&lt;/em&gt; to exist. Morality is not attacked, it only no longer comes into consideration… This book ends with an ‘Or?’ – it is the only book which ends with an ‘Or?’…&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 THE GAY SCIENCE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/09_THE_GAY_SCIENCE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/09_THE_GAY_SCIENCE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;‘DAYBREAK’ is an affirmative book, profound but bright and benevolent. The same applies once again and in the highest degree to the &lt;em&gt;gaya scienza:&lt;/em&gt; in practically every sentence of this book profundity and exuberance go hand in hand. A poem which expresses gratitude for the most wonderful month of January I have ever experienced – the entire book is a gift – betrays out of what a depth ‘science’ has here become &lt;em&gt;gay:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 THUS SPOKE ZARATHUSTRA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/10_THUS_SPOKE_ZARATHUSTRA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/10_THUS_SPOKE_ZARATHUSTRA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A Book for Everyone and No One&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I SHALL now tell the story of Zarathustra. The basic conception of the work, the &lt;em&gt;idea of eternal recurrence,&lt;/em&gt; the highest formula of affirmation that can possibly be attained − belongs to the August of the year 1881: it was jotted down on a piece of paper with the inscription: ‘6,000 feet beyond man and time’. I was that day walking through the woods beside the lake of Silva-plana; I stopped beside a mighty pyramidal block of stone which reared itself up not far from Surlei. Then this idea came to me. − If I reckon a couple of months back from this day I find as an omen a sudden and profoundly decisive alteration in my taste, above all in music. The whole of Zarathustra might perhaps be reckoned as music; − certainly a rebirth of the art of &lt;em&gt;hearing&lt;/em&gt; was a precondition of it. In a little mountain resort not far from Vicenza, Recoaro, where I spent the spring of the year 1881, I discovered together with my &lt;em&gt;maestro&lt;/em&gt; and friend Peter Gast, who was likewise ‘reborn’, that the phoenix music flew past us with lighter and more luminous wings than it had ever exhibited before. If on the other hand I reckon from that day forwards to the sudden delivery accomplished under the most improbable circumstances in February 1883 − the closing section, from which I have quoted a couple of sentences in the &lt;em&gt;Foreword,&lt;/em&gt; was completed precisely at that sacred hour when Richard Wagner died in Venice − the pregnancy is seen to have lasted eighteen months. This term of precisely eighteen months might suggest, at least to Buddhists, that I am really a female elephant. − The interval is occupied by the &lt;em&gt;‘gaya scienza’,&lt;/em&gt; which bears a hundred signs of the proximity of something incomparable; finally it gives the opening of Zarathustra itself, it gives in the penultimate piece of the fourth book the fundamental idea of Zarathustra. − Also belonging to this interval is that &lt;em&gt;Hymn to Life&lt;/em&gt; (for mixed chorus and orchestra) the score of which was published two years ago by E. W. Fritzsch of Leipzig: a perhaps not insignificant symptom of the condition of this year, when I was possessed to the highest degree by the &lt;em&gt;affirmative&lt;/em&gt; pathos &lt;em&gt;par excellence,&lt;/em&gt; which I call the tragic pathos. It will one day be sung to my memory. − The text, I may state expressly because a misunderstanding exists about it, is not by me: it is the astonishing inspiration of a young Russian lady with whom I was then friendly, Fräulein Lou von Salomé. He who knows how to extract any meaning at all from the closing words of the poem will divine why I preferred and admired it: they possess greatness. Pain does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; count as an objection to life: ‘Have you no more happiness to give me, well then! &lt;em&gt;still do you have your pain…’ Perhaps my music is also great at this point.&lt;/em&gt; [&lt;em&gt;Last note&lt;/em&gt; of the clarinet in A is &lt;em&gt;C sharp&lt;/em&gt; not &lt;em&gt;C.&lt;/em&gt; Printing error.) − I lived the following winter in the pleasandy quiet bay of Rapallo not far from Genoa which cuts in between Chiavari and the promontory of Porto Fino. My health was not of the best; the winter cold and exceedingly wet; a small &lt;em&gt;albergo&lt;/em&gt; situated right against the sea, so that at night the high tide made sleep impossible, offered all in all the very opposite of what one might desire. In spite of this, and almost as a proof of my proposition that everything decisive comes about ‘in spite of, it was during this winter and under these unfavourable conditions that my Zarathustra came into existence. − In the mornings I climbed in a southerly direction into the heights along the glorious route to Zoagli, past pine-trees and with a vast view of the sea; in the afternoons, whenever my health permitted I walked around the entire bay from Santa Margherita to Porto Fino. This place and this landscape is even closer to my heart through the great love Kaiser Friedrich the Third felt for it; in the autumn of 1886 I happened to be on this coast again when he visited this little forgotten world of happiness for the last time. − It was on these two walks that the whole of the first Zarathustra came to me, above all Zarathustra himself, as a type: more accurately, &lt;em&gt;be stole up on me…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 BEYOND GOOD AND EVIL</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/11_BEYOND_GOOD_AND_EVIL/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/11_BEYOND_GOOD_AND_EVIL/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Prelude to a Philosophy of the Future&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;THE task for the immediately following years was as clear as it could be. Now that the affirmative part of my task was done, it was the turn of the denying, the No-saying and &lt;em&gt;No-doing&lt;/em&gt; part: the revaluation of existing values themselves, the great war – the evocation of a day of decision. Included here is the slow search for those related to me, for such as out of strength would offer me their hand for &lt;em&gt;the work of destruction. –&lt;/em&gt; From now on all my writings are fish-hooks: perhaps I understand fishing as well as anyone?… If nothing got &lt;em&gt;caught&lt;/em&gt; I am not to blame. &lt;em&gt;There were no fish&lt;/em&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 GENEALOGY OF MORALS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/12_GENEALOGY_OF_MORALS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/12_GENEALOGY_OF_MORALS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A Polemic&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;THE three essays of which this Genealogy consists are in regard to expression, intention and art of surprise perhaps the uncanniest things that have ever been written. Dionysos is, as one knows, also the god of darkness. – Each time a beginning which is &lt;em&gt;intended&lt;/em&gt; to mislead, cool, scientific, even ironic, intentionally foreground, intentionally keeping in suspense. Gradually an increasing disquiet; isolated flashes of lightning; very unpleasant truths becoming audible as a dull rumbling in the distance – until at last a &lt;em&gt;tempo feroce&lt;/em&gt; is attained in which everything surges forward with tremendous tension. At the conclusion each time amid perfecdy awful detonations a &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; truth visible between thick clouds. – The truth of the &lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt; essay is the psychology of Christianity: the birth of Christianity out of the spirit of &lt;em&gt;ressentiment&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;, as is no doubt believed, out of the ‘spirit’ – essentially a counter-movement, the great revolt against the domination of &lt;em&gt;noble&lt;/em&gt; values. The &lt;em&gt;second&lt;/em&gt; essay gives the psychology of the &lt;em&gt;conscience&lt;/em&gt;: it is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;, as is no doubt believed, ‘the voice of God in man’ – it is the instinct of cruelty turned backwards after it can no longer discharge itself outwards. Cruelty here brought to light for the first time as one of the oldest substrata of culture and one that can least be thought away. The &lt;em&gt;third&lt;/em&gt; essay gives the answer to the question where the tremendous &lt;em&gt;power&lt;/em&gt; of the ascetic ideal, the priestly ideal, comes from, although it is the &lt;em&gt;harmful&lt;/em&gt; ideal &lt;em&gt;par excellence&lt;/em&gt;, a will to the end, a &lt;em&gt;décadence&lt;/em&gt; ideal. Answer: &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; because God is active behind the priests, which is no doubt believed, but &lt;em&gt;faute de mieux –&lt;/em&gt; because hitherto it has been the only ideal, because it had no competitors. ‘For man will rather will nothingness than &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; will’… What was lacking above all was a &lt;em&gt;counter-ideal – until the advent of Zarathustra. –&lt;/em&gt; I have been understood. Three decisive preliminary studies of a psychologist for a revaluation of all values. – This book contains the first psychology of the priest.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 TWILIGHT OF THE IDOLS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/13_TWILIGHT_OF_THE_IDOLS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/13_TWILIGHT_OF_THE_IDOLS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How to Philosophize with a Hammer&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;THIS writing of fewer than 150 pages, cheerful and fateful in tone, a demon which laughs – the work of so few days I hesitate to reveal their number, is the exception among books: there exists nothing more rich in substance, more independent, more overthrowing – more wicked. If you want to get a quick idea of how everything was upsidedown before me, make a start with this writing. That which is called &lt;em&gt;idol&lt;/em&gt; on the title-page is quite simply that which has hitherto been called truth. &lt;em&gt;Twilight of the Idols&lt;/em&gt; – in plain terms: the old truth is coming to an end…&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 THE WAGNER CASE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/14_THE_WAGNER_CASE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/14_THE_WAGNER_CASE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A Musicians’ Problem&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;IF one is to be fait to this writing one has to suffer from the destiny of music as from an open wound. – &lt;em&gt;What&lt;/em&gt; is it I suffer from when I suffer from the destiny of music? From this: that music has been deprived of its world-transfiguring, affirmative character, that it is &lt;em&gt;décadence&lt;/em&gt; music and no longer the flute of Dionysos… Supposing, however, that one in this way feels the cause of music to be &lt;em&gt;one’s own&lt;/em&gt; cause, to be the history of &lt;em&gt;one’s own&lt;/em&gt; suffering, one will find this writing full of consideration and mild beyond measure. In such cases to be cheerful and good-naturedly to mock at oneself as well – &lt;em&gt;ridendo dicere&lt;/em&gt; severum where &lt;em&gt;verum dicere&lt;/em&gt; would justify every kind of severity – is humaneness itself. Who really doubts that I, old artillerist that I am, have the ability to bring up my &lt;em&gt;heavy&lt;/em&gt; guns against Wagner? – I kept to myself everything decisive in this matter – I have loved Wagner. – Ultimately this is an attack on a subtle ‘unknown’ who could not easily be detected by another, in the sense and direction of my task – oh, I have still got quite other ‘unknowns’ to reveal than a Cagliostro of music – even more, to be sure, an attack on the German nation growing ever more sluggish and poor in instinct in spiritual matters, ever more &lt;em&gt;honourable&lt;/em&gt;, which with an enviable appetite continues to nourish itself with opposites and knows how to gulp down ‘faith’ as well as scientificality, ‘Christian love’ as well as anti-Semitism, will to power (to the ‘Reich’) as well as the &lt;em&gt;évangile des bumbles;&lt;/em&gt; without having any trouble digesting them… This lack of party in choosing between opposites! This ventral neutrality and ‘selflessness’! This fairness of German &lt;em&gt;taste,&lt;/em&gt; which accords everything equal rights – which finds everything tasty… Without any doubt the Germans are idealists… When I last visited Germany I found German taste occupied in trying to accord Wagner and the Trumpeter of Säckingen equal rights; I myself witnessed how in Leipzig, to the honour of one of the most genuine and German musicians in the old sense of the word German, no mere Reich German, &lt;em&gt;Meister Heinrich Schütz,&lt;/em&gt; they founded a Liszt Society for the encouragement and propagation of &lt;em&gt;cunning&lt;/em&gt; church music… Without any doubt the Germans are idealists…&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 WHY I AM A DESTINY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/15_WHY_I_AM_A_DESTINY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/15_WHY_I_AM_A_DESTINY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I KNOW my fate. One day there will be associated with my name the recollection of something frightful – of a crisis like no other before on earth, of the profoundest collision of conscience, of a decision evoked &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; everything that until then had been believed in, demanded, sanctified. I am not a man, I am dynamite. – And with all that there is nothing in me of a founder of a religion – religions are affairs of the rabble, I have need of washing my hands after contact with religious people… I do not &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; ‘believers’, I think I am too malicious to believe in myself, I never speak to masses… I have a terrible fear I shall one day be pronounced &lt;em&gt;holy:&lt;/em&gt; one will guess why I bring out this book &lt;em&gt;beforehand;&lt;/em&gt; it is intended to prevent people from making mischief with me… I do not want to be a saint, rather even a buffoon… Perhaps I am a buffoon… And none the less, or rather &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; none the less – for there has hitherto been nothing more mendacious than saints – the truth speaks out of me. – But my truth is &lt;em&gt;dreadful:&lt;/em&gt; for hitherto the &lt;em&gt;lie&lt;/em&gt; has been called truth. – R&lt;em&gt;evaluation of all values:&lt;/em&gt; this is my formula for an act of supreme coming-to-oneself on the part of mankind which in me has become flesh and genius. It is my fate to have to be the first &lt;em&gt;decent&lt;/em&gt; human being, to know myself in opposition to the mendaciousness of millennia… I was the first to &lt;em&gt;discover&lt;/em&gt; the truth, in that I was the first to sense – &lt;em&gt;smell&lt;/em&gt; – the lie as lie… My genius is in my nostrils… I contradict as has never been contradicted and am none the less the opposite of a negative spirit. I am a &lt;em&gt;bringer of good tidings&lt;/em&gt; such as there has never been, I know tasks from such a height that any conception of themhas hitherto been lacking; only after me is it possible to hope again. With all that I am necessarily a man of fatality. For when truth steps into battle with the lie of millennia we shall have convulsions, an earthquake spasm, a transposition of valley and mountain such as has never been dreamed of. The concept politics has then become completely absorbed into a war of spirits, all the power-structures of the old society have been blown into the air – they one and all reposed on the lie: there will be wars such as there have never yet been on earth. Only after me will there be &lt;em&gt;grand politics&lt;/em&gt; on earth.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 NOTES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/16_NOTES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/ecce_homo/16_NOTES/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;foreword&#34;&gt;FOREWORD&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;heaviest demand&lt;/em&gt;. The forthcoming &lt;em&gt;Revaluation of all Values&lt;/em&gt; – together with the effect it may be expected to produce – is presumably what is meant.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Nitimur in &lt;em&gt;vetitum&lt;/em&gt;. We strive after the forbidden (Ovid).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘&lt;em&gt;It is the stillest… guide the world&lt;/em&gt;’. Quoted from &lt;em&gt;Thus Spoke Zarathustra&lt;/em&gt;, Part Two: ‘The Stillest Hour’.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The figs are falling&lt;/em&gt;… sky and afternoon. Quoted from &lt;em&gt;Zarathustra&lt;/em&gt;, Part Two: ‘On the Blissful Islands’.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;décadent&lt;/em&gt;. Nietzsche employs, here and elsewhere, the French word, since none with precisely this meaning was available to him in German.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
