<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;05 MANTRA on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/05_MANTRA/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;05 MANTRA on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/05_MANTRA/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Mantra Siddhi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/05_MANTRA/01_Mantra_Siddhi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/05_MANTRA/01_Mantra_Siddhi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“Many people talk about Mantra Siddhi (the manifestation of the deity inherent in the mantra), but I am afraid that most of them have missed the boat. Let&amp;rsquo;s say that I want to locate you, and I know your name. But that alone is not enough. I must also know what you look like and where you live, because there may be many people with the same name. Only if I know your likes and dislikes, your temperament, all the facets of your character, do I really know you. Then I can locate you.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Using Mantras</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/05_MANTRA/02_Using_Mantras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/05_MANTRA/02_Using_Mantras/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;How will I know which form I have an affinity for?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“That is the job of your guru, to assign you the proper mantra and the proper form. He will know which mantras are appropriate for you. If you are of a very tender nature and you start to repeat a mantra for some terrifying deity like Smashan Tara you may scare yourself to death. If you are prone to greed and you worship Lakshmi, the goddess of wealth, you may simply enhance your greed, which will not help you progress. This is why a guru is necessary: to teach you what you need to learn. People are amazing nowa days; they tell the guru what they want to learn from him, instead of trying to find out from him what they need to know. Is there anything more ridic ulous?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 The Five S&#39;s</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/05_MANTRA/03_The_Five_Ss/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/05_MANTRA/03_The_Five_Ss/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“Both anusthanas and purashcharanas require you to follow what we call in Sanskrit the path of the Five S&amp;rsquo;s: sthana, samaya, sankhya, samagri, and samyama. The purpose of these rules is to achieve the sa-guna or mr anifested form of the deity. You know Sanskrit; translate these words.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&amp;lsquo;Sthana&amp;rsquo; means location.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;So first you must stay in one location throughout the duration of your penance and not travel about. Moreover, you must sit in the same place each day, face in the same direction, and if possible sit in the same posi tion.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Secrecy</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/05_MANTRA/04_Secrecy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/05_MANTRA/04_Secrecy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some days later when I was in Bombay I accompanied Vimalananda on an uneventful visit to K., one of his old friends. Afterward I noticed that Vim alananda was quieter than usual, so after we reached home and had tea I casually asked him, &amp;ldquo;Have you known that gentleman for very long?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;| 148 1&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;MANTRA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He replied, “There are many restrictions to follow if you really want to perfect a mantra. One of the most important is that you must never tell any one which mantra you repeat. When you tell someone else your mantra you allow them access to the Shakti you are trying to accumulate, which is tan tamount to giving them a blank check and asking them to clean out your bank account. Anyone who needs to know your mantra will be able to find out without asking you; whoever cannot find it out without asking does not need to know&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Pronunciation</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/05_MANTRA/05_Pronunciation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/05_MANTRA/05_Pronunciation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I could see that mantras were really very useful things. “Telling your mantra to someone else is fatal, but there are other mistakes which can also ruin you. Mispronunciation is one of the worst. The way a word is pronounced has a lot to do with its meaning. For instance, when you come in and I say, &amp;lsquo;Hello, Robby, how are you?&amp;rsquo; with a pleasant voice and a smiling face, how do you feel?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 Four Levels of Speech</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/05_MANTRA/06_Four_Levels_of_Speech/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/05_MANTRA/06_Four_Levels_of_Speech/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Of course the Rishis and their disciples knew how to pronounce Sanskrit properly.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Yes they did, and they knew other things as well, including how to best make use of all four levels of speech.&amp;quot; As I racked my brain for any informa tion I might have collected on that subject, he continued. “You know, speech is not a product of the mind; speech is an independent creative fac ulty, a sense which operates through the mind. Kundalini is the power of an individual&amp;rsquo;s self-expression, which means that speech is simply the verbal expression of Kundalini. This is why the lotuses of the chakras have Bija Mantras for petals, and why mantras are so important for awakening Kun dalini.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 The Four Classes</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/05_MANTRA/07_The_Four_Classes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/05_MANTRA/07_The_Four_Classes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“And all this is due to the chemical composition of the speaker&amp;rsquo;s con sciousness,&amp;quot; I volunteered, as I thought I knew which direction Vimalanan da’s discourse was heading&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He nodded his assent. “And this chemical composition determines what sort of sadhana is appropriate for you, what you can succeed at. There is no lack of people today who claim to have located the keys to the Vedas, and who claim that they are living a &amp;lsquo;Vedic&amp;rsquo; life, and teaching their disciples &amp;lsquo;Vedic&amp;rsquo; sadhanas. Most of them are gasbagging; they are talking out of their wits. Think, for a moment, about the caste system. India has been plagued by casteism for centuries, but the caste system started out as something quite different from what it has become.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
