<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;02 KUNDALINI on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/02_KUNDALINI/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;02 KUNDALINI on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/02_KUNDALINI/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Self-Identification</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/02_KUNDALINI/01_Self-Identification/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/02_KUNDALINI/01_Self-Identification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“Actually there is no difference betwen the Kundalini Shakti and Adya, the original Shakti of the universe, except that the Kundalini Shakti has become individualized.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Vimalananda was not one to repeat himself; as soon as he began to speak about something of interest to me I was expected to drop whatever I was doing and listen. Usually he picked moments when I was engrossed in some mundane matter like reading the newspaper, since drawing my atten tion to his words would disengage my mind at least temporarily from its attachment to the mundane.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Coverings</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/02_KUNDALINI/02_Coverings/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/02_KUNDALINI/02_Coverings/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“While Kundalini sleeps in the Muladhara Chakra at the base of the spine you are awake to the world and asleep to reality. When She awakes to unite with Her Shiva in your brain then you wake up to reality; you &amp;lsquo;fall asleep&amp;rsquo; to the world. An ignorant person believes that he is in the world; his Kundalini self-identifies with the poison of Maya. A jnani, one who knows, says rather, ‘The world is in me,&amp;rsquo; because his Kundalini self-identifies with Shiva.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Nadis and Chakras</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/02_KUNDALINI/03_Nadis_and_Chakras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/02_KUNDALINI/03_Nadis_and_Chakras/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“The ego or ahamkara does not actually reside in the physical body, because the ego is not at all physical. It resides in the subtle body, and moves in the nadis, the ethereal nerves. The body&amp;rsquo;s 72,000 nadis act as con duits for prana, which is closely related to the ego. Numerologically, 72,000 means 7 + 2 = 9: the Nine Doors through which prana can enter or leave the body. Most of the nadis begin or terminate at these Doors, which are the sense organs: the two eyes, the two nostrils, the two ears, the mouth, the anus, and the genital organ. Prana, moving with the breaths, enkindles the body&amp;rsquo;s fire, just as a bellows is used to ignite and inflame the fire in a forge, and the mind is carried out through these Doors by prana so that it can experience the world. Control of the nadis enables you to control the ego, the mind and the senses.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 The Nine Chakras</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/02_KUNDALINI/04_The_Nine_Chakras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/02_KUNDALINI/04_The_Nine_Chakras/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“Most people will tell you there are six chakras. An Aghori will tell you there are nine. To understand this statement you must at least know the dif ference between a nara (man) and a khara (donkey). If you think this is a joking matter, it is because you are a khara yourself.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I had grinned at the comparison, and now I grinned at his affront. He snorted and went on.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Raising Kundalini</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/02_KUNDALINI/05_Raising_Kundalini/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/02_KUNDALINI/05_Raising_Kundalini/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had to shake my head in appreciation and agreement, it was so true.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“To make Kundalini rise from the tip of the spine you must create enough pressure to force Her out of the Muladhara Chakra. The upward motion will continue only so long as the pressure remains; without it Kundalini drops back down to the bottom, due to gravity. Because humans stand erect, grav ity acts only on the tip of the spinal cord, not on the whole thing as it does in other animals, whose spines are horizontal or nearly so. This is one rea son why it is easier to awaken Kundalini in a human than in an animal.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 Samadhi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/02_KUNDALINI/06_Samadhi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/02_KUNDALINI/06_Samadhi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I have always said that life is a memory. There are actually two types of memory: conscious and unconscious. The conscious memory is very fickle and inconstant; it is directed outwards towards mundane objects, which are temporary and transitory but seem eternal to the ignorant mind. The unconscious memory is permanent; it has been collecting all your karmas from tens of millions of births without any lapse or distortion. So the uncon scious memory is actually conscious, since it perfectly records everything that happens to you, and the conscious memory is actually unconscious. People say, &amp;lsquo;I did it because of the force of circumstance,&amp;rsquo; when what they mean is that they were not conscious enough to remember not to yield to&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 Kula Kundalini</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/02_KUNDALINI/07_Kula_Kundalini/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/02_KUNDALINI/07_Kula_Kundalini/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;If you hope to continue to exist after Kundalini is awakened completely you must be able to make Her go from the Muladhara to the Sahasrara, and then in the reverse direction, downwards from the Sahasrara to the&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;( 771&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;AGHORA II: Kundalini&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Muladhara, under perfect control. Prana and Apana are then perfectly united. Apana is represented as a downward-pointing triangle, and Prana as an upward-pointing one. Their union forms a six-pointed star.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 The Snake</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/02_KUNDALINI/08_The_Snake/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/02_KUNDALINI/08_The_Snake/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As Joseph Campbell documents in his book The Inner Reaches of Outer Space, the force that the Tantras call Kundalini has been represented as a ser pent in many world cultures, including the Sumerian, Chinese, ancient Irish, Aztec and Greek (the caduceus). Images of Kundalini as the Serpent Power predominantly reflect Her power of possessiveness, of Maya. Indian cosmology describes seven netherworlds beneath the surface of the earth in which dwell asuras (the &amp;ldquo;selfish&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;jealous” gods) and nagas (semi-divine snake beings). In the microcosm the &amp;lsquo;surface of the earth&amp;rsquo; is the Muladhara Chakra; &amp;lsquo;dwelling beneath the earth&amp;rsquo;s surface&amp;rsquo; means living wholly in objec tive reality, within the realm of Maya, which is the skin of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 The Chakras</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/02_KUNDALINI/09_The_Chakras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/02_KUNDALINI/09_The_Chakras/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Even though the chakras of the subtle body have been identified by other cultures, such as the ancient Egyptian and the Navajo, they have never been directly introduced into popular religion, for good reason. Having our Kun dalinis unawakened and our chakras closed is a form of protection; exist ence is possible for embodied beings solely because their chakras are&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1831&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;AGHORA II: Kundalini&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;normally blocked. In fact, many Kundalini-generated disorders are due not to the blockage of a chakra but to the lack of blockage thereof. The delusion that the chakras are the cause of physiological imbalances stems from the confusion that exists between the chakras themselves and the other struc tures that exist in association with them. The chakras mentioned above, the Muladhara and the rest, function only when Kundalini moves within them; at all other times what functions are their corresponding but more superfi cial structures. Arthur Avalon comments that:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 Kula Kundalini</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/02_KUNDALINI/10_Kula_Kundalini/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/svoboda/aghora/2_kuNDalinI/02_KUNDALINI/10_Kula_Kundalini/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The fourth, fifth and sixth chapters of the book of I Samuel describe the capture by the Philistines and the eventual return to Israel of the Ark of the&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[84]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;KUNDALINI&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Covenant. While it is difficult to draw direct correlations between otherwise unrelated ancient cultures, it is striking to note that during the period that the Philistines possessed the Ark the idol of their god Dagon was mysteri ously toppled and disfigured, and the entire population was struck low with hemorrhoids. It would certainly seem that neither the Philistines nor their god could digest the Ark&amp;rsquo;s shakti. When they consulted their diviners they were told to return the Ark to Israel with a trespass offering consisting of five golden hemorrhoids and five mice, also made of gold. Is it a coincidence that hemorrhoids appear in the physical body near the location of the Muladhara Chakra, or that the mouse is the vehicle of Ganesha, the Lord of the Muladhara? Or does this imagery reflect similar subtle realities?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
