<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;3 Book Three on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;3 Book Three on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>108</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/108/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/108/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;New battles.&lt;/em&gt; – After Buddha was dead, they still showed his shadow in a cave for centuries – a tremendous, gruesome shadow. God is dead; but given the way people are, there may still for millennia be caves in which they show his shadow. – And we – we must still defeat his shadow as well!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>109</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/109/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/109/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Let us beware.&lt;/em&gt; – Let us beware of thinking that the world is a living being. Where would it stretch? What would it feed on? How could it grow and procreate? After all, we know roughly what the organic is; are we then supposed to reinterpret what is inexpressibly derivative, late, rare, accidental, which we perceive only on the crust of the earth, as something essential, common, and eternal, as those people do who call the universe an organism? This nauseates me. Let us beware even of believing that the universe is a machine; it is certainly not constructed to one end, and the word ‘machine’ pays it far too high an honour. Let us beware of assuming in general and everywhere anything as elegant as the cyclical movements of our neighbouring stars; even a glance at the Milky Way raises doubts whether there are not much coarser and more contradictory movements there, as well as stars with eternally linear paths, etc. The astral order in which we live is an exception; this order and the considerable duration that is conditioned by it have again made possible the exception of exceptions: the development of the organic. The total character of the world, by contrast, is for all eternity chaos, not in the sense of a lack of necessity but of a lack of order, organization, form, beauty, wisdom, and whatever else our aesthetic anthropomorphisms are called. Judged from the vantage point of our reason, the unsuccessful attempts are by far the rule; the exceptions are not the secret aim, and the whole musical mechanism repeats eternally its tune, which must never be called a melody – and ultimately even the phrase ‘unsuccessful attempt’ is already an anthropomorphism bearing a reproach. But how could we reproach or praise the universe! Let us beware of attributing to it heartlessness or unreason or their opposites: it is neither perfect, nor beautiful, nor noble, nor does it want to become any of these things; in no way does it strive to imitate man! In no way do our aesthetic and moral judgements apply to it! It also has no drive to self-preservation or any other drives; nor does it observe any laws. Let us beware of saying that there are laws in nature. There are only necessities: there is no one who commands, no one who obeys, no one who transgresses. Once you know that there are no purposes, you also know that there is no accident; for only against a world of purposes does the word ‘accident’ have a meaning. Let us beware of saying that death is opposed to life. The living is only a form of what is dead, and a very rare form. Let us beware of thinking that the world eternally creates new things. There are no eternally enduring substances; matter is as much of an error as the god of the Eleatics.1 But when will we be done with our caution and care? When will all these shadows of god no longer darken us? When will we have completely de-deified nature? When may we begin to &lt;em&gt;naturalize&lt;/em&gt; humanity with a pure, newly discovered, newly redeemed nature?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>110</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/110/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/110/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Origin of knowledge.&lt;/em&gt; – Through immense periods of time, the intellect produced nothing but errors; some of them turned out to be useful and species-preserving; those who hit upon or inherited them fought their fight for themselves and their progeny with greater luck. Such erroneous articles of faith, which were passed on by inheritance further and further, and finally almost became part of the basic endowment of the species, are for example: that there are enduring things; that there are identical things; that there are things, kinds of material, bodies; that a thing is what it appears to be; that our will is free; that what is good for me is also good in and for itself. Only very late did the deniers and doubters of such propositions emerge; only very late did truth emerge as the weakest form of knowledge. It seemed that one was unable to live with it; that our organism was geared for its opposite: all its higher functions, the perceptions of sense and generally every kind of sensation, worked with those basic errors that had been incorporated since time immemorial. Further, even in the realm of knowledge those propositions became the norms according to which one determined ‘true’ and ‘untrue’ – down to the most remote areas of pure logic. Thus the &lt;em&gt;strength&lt;/em&gt; of knowledge lies not in its degree of truth, but in its age, its embeddedness, its character as a condition of life. Where life and knowledge seem to contradict each other, there was never any serious fight to begin with; denial and doubt were simply considered madness. Those exceptional thinkers, like the Eleatics, who still posited and clung to the opposites of the natural errors, believed in the possibility of also &lt;em&gt;living&lt;/em&gt; this opposite: they invented the sage as the man of unchangeability, impersonality, universality of intuition, as one and all at the same time, with a special capacity for that inverted knowledge; they had the faith that their knowledge was at the same time the principle of &lt;em&gt;life.&lt;/em&gt; But in order to be able to claim all this, they had to &lt;em&gt;deceive&lt;/em&gt; themselves about their own state: they had fictitiously to attribute to themselves impersonality and duration without change; they had to misconstrue the nature of the knower, deny the force of impulses in knowledge, and generally conceive reason as a completely free, self-originated activity. They closed their eyes to the fact that they, too, had arrived at their propositions in opposition to what was considered valid or from a desire for tranquillity or sole possession or sovereignty. The subtler development of honesty and scepticism finally made also these people impossible; even their life and judgements proved dependent on the ancient drives and fundamental errors of all sentient existence. This subtler honesty and scepticism arose wherever two conflicting propositions seemed to be &lt;em&gt;applicable&lt;/em&gt; to life because both were compatible with the basic errors, and thus where it was possible to argue about the greater or lesser degree of &lt;em&gt;usefulness&lt;/em&gt; for life; also wherever new propositions showed themselves to be not directly useful, but at least also not harmful, as expressions of an intellectual play impulse, and innocent and happy like all play. Gradually the human brain filled itself with such judgements and convictions; and ferment, struggle, and lust for power developed in this tangle. Not only utility and delight, but also every kind of drive took part in the fight about the ‘truths’; the intellectual fight became an occupation, attraction, profession, duty, dignity – knowledge and the striving for the true finally took their place as a need among the other needs. Henceforth, not only faith and conviction, but also scrutiny, denial, suspicion, and contradiction were a &lt;em&gt;power;&lt;/em&gt; all ‘evil’ instincts were subordinated to knowledge and put in its service and took on the lustre of the permitted, honoured, useful and finally the eye and the innocence of the &lt;em&gt;good.&lt;/em&gt; Thus knowledge became a part of life and, as life, a continually growing power, until finally knowledge and the ancient basic errors struck against each other, both as life, both as power, both in the same person. The thinker – that is now the being in whom the drive to truth and those life-preserving errors are fighting their first battle, after the drive to truth has &lt;em&gt;proven&lt;/em&gt; itself to be a life-preserving power, too. In relation to the significance of this battle, everything else is a matter of indifference: the ultimate question about the condition of life is posed here, and the first attempt is made here to answer the question through experiment. To what extent can truth stand to be incorporated? – that is the question; that is the experiment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>111</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/111/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/111/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The origin of the logical.&lt;/em&gt; – What is the origin of logic in man’s head? Surely it arose out of the illogical, the realm of which must originally have been immense. But innumerable beings drew inferences in a way different from that in which we do now perished; nonetheless, they might have been closer to the truth! He, for instance, who did not know how to find ‘identity’ often enough, both with regard to nourishment and to hostile animals – that is, he who subsumed too slowly and was too cautious in subsumption – had a slighter probability of survival than he who in all cases of similarity immediately guessed that they were identical. The predominant disposition, however, to treat the similar as identical – an illogical disposition, for there is nothing identical as such – is what first supplied all the foundations for logic. Similarly, in order for the concept of substance to originate, which is indispensable to logic though nothing real corresponds to it in the strictest sense, it was necessary that for a long time changes in things not be seen, not be perceived; the beings who did not see things exactly had a head start over those who saw everything ‘in a flux’. As such, every great degree of caution in inferring, every sceptical disposition, is a great danger to life. No living being would be preserved had not the opposite disposition – to affirm rather than suspend judgement, to err and make things up rather than wait, to agree rather than deny, to pass judgement rather than be just – been bred to become extraordinarily strong. The course of logical thoughts and inferences in our brains today corresponds to a process and battle of drives that taken separately are all very illogical and unjust; we usually experience only the outcome of the battle: that is how quickly and covertly this ancient mechanism runs its course in us.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>112</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/112/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/112/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cause and effect.&lt;/em&gt; – We call it ‘explanation’, but ‘description’ is what distinguishes us from older stages of knowledge and science. We are better at describing – we explain just as little as all our predecessors. We have uncovered a diverse succession where the naive man and investigator of older cultures saw only two different things, ‘cause’ and ‘effect’, as they said; we have perfected the picture of becoming but haven’t got over, got behind the picture. The series of ‘causes’ faces us much more completely in each case; we reason, ‘this and that must precede for that to follow’ – but we haven’t thereby &lt;em&gt;understood&lt;/em&gt; anything. The specifically qualitative aspect for example of every chemical process, still appears to be a ‘miracle’, as does every locomotion; no one has ‘explained’ the push. And how could we explain! We are operating only with things that do not exist – with lines, surfaces, bodies, atoms, divisible times, divisible spaces. How is explanation to be at all possible when we first turn everything into a &lt;em&gt;picture&lt;/em&gt; – our picture! It is enough to view science as an attempt to humanize things as faithfully as possible; we learn to describe ourselves more and more precisely as we describe things and their succession. Cause and effect: there is probably never such a duality; in truth a continuum faces us, from which we isolate a few pieces, just as we always perceive a movement only as isolated points, i.e. do not really see, but infer. The suddenness with which many effects stand out misleads us; it is a suddenness only for us. There is an infinite number of processes that elude us in this second of suddenness. An intellect that saw cause and effect as a continuum, not, as we do, as arbitrary division and dismemberment – that saw the stream of the event – would reject the concept of cause and effect and deny all determinedness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>113</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/113/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/113/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On the doctrine of poisons.&lt;/em&gt; – So much has to come together in order for scientific thought to originate, and all these necessary forces have had to be separately invented, practised, cultivated! In their separateness they have, however, very often had a totally different effect from that which they have today when in the realm of scientific thought they mutually limit and keep each other in check: they have worked as poisons, e.g. the doubting drive, the denying drive, the waiting drive, the collecting drive, the dissolving drive. Many hecatombs of human beings had to be sacrificed before these drives learned to grasp their coexistence and feel like functions of one organizing force in one human being! And how far we still are from the time when artistic energies and the practical wisdom of life join with scientific thought so that a higher organic system will develop in relation to which the scholar, the physician, the artist, and the lawmaker, as we now know them, would have to appear as paltry antiquities!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>114</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/114/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/114/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The scope of the moral.&lt;/em&gt; – As soon as we see a new picture, we immediately construct it with the help of all the old experiences we have had &lt;em&gt;depending on the degree&lt;/em&gt; of our honesty and justice. There are no experiences other than moral ones, not even in the realm of sense perception.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>115</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/115/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/115/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The four errors.&lt;/em&gt; – Man has been educated by his errors: first, he saw himself only incompletely; secondly, he endowed himself with fictitious attributes; thirdly, he placed himself in a false rank order in relation to animals and nature; fourthly, he invented ever new tables of goods and for a time took them to be eternal and unconditioned – so that now this, now that human drive and condition occupied first place and was ennobled as a result of this valuation. If one discounts the effect of these four errors, one has also discounted humanity, humaneness, and ‘human dignity’.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>116</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/116/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/116/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Herd instinct.&lt;/em&gt; – Wherever we encounter a morality, we find an evaluation and ranking of human drives and actions. These evaluations and rankings are always the expression of the needs of a community and herd: that which benefits &lt;em&gt;it&lt;/em&gt; the most – and second most, and third most – is also the highest standard of value for all individuals. With morality the individual is instructed to be a function of the herd and to ascribe value to himself only as a function. Since the conditions for preserving one community have been very different from those of another community, there have been very different moralities; and in view of essential changes in herds and communities, states and societies that are yet to come, one can prophesy that there will yet be very divergent moralities. Morality is herd-instinct in the individual.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>117</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/117/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/117/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Herd pangs of conscience.&lt;/em&gt; – During the longest and most remote periods of time there was a kind of pang of conscience completely different from that which exists now. Today one feels responsible only for what one wants and does, and finds one’s pride in oneself: all our teachers of justice start from this feeling of self and pleasure in the individual (des &lt;em&gt;Einzelnen),&lt;/em&gt; as if the spring of justice (&lt;em&gt;des Rechts&lt;/em&gt;)2 had always arisen here. But for the longest period of humanity’s existence there was nothing more frightful than feeling alone (&lt;em&gt;einzeln).&lt;/em&gt; To be alone (&lt;em&gt;allein),&lt;/em&gt; to experience things by oneself (&lt;em&gt;einzeln),&lt;/em&gt; to neither obey nor rule, to represent an individual (&lt;em&gt;ein Individuum bedeuten&lt;/em&gt;) – that was no pleasure back then, but a punishment; one was sentenced ‘to be an individual (&lt;em&gt;Individuum)’.&lt;/em&gt; Freedom of thought was considered discomfort itself. While we experience law and conformity as compulsion and loss, one formerly experienced egoism as a painful thing, as an actual affliction. To be a self, to estimate oneself according to one’s own measure and weight – that was contrary to taste in those days. The inclination to this would have been considered madness, for every misery and every fear were associated with being alone (&lt;em&gt;Alleinsein).&lt;/em&gt; Back then, ‘free will’ had bad conscience as its closest neighbour. The more unfreely one acted, the more the herd instinct and not the sense of self spoke through the action, the more moral one considered oneself. In those days, everything that hurt the herd, whether the individual had willed it or not, gave the individual pangs of conscience – and his neighbour as well; indeed, the whole herd! On this point we have relearned most of all.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>118</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/118/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/118/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Benevolence.&lt;/em&gt; – Is it virtuous when a cell transforms itself into a function of a stronger cell? It has to. And is it evil when the stronger cell assimilates the weaker? It also has to; this is necessary for it, since it strives for superabundant replenishment and wants to regenerate itself. Accordingly one should make a distinction in benevolence between the drive to appropriate and the drive to submit, depending on whether it is the stronger or the weaker who experiences it. Joy and desire go together in the stronger, who wants to transform something into a function of himself; joy and the wish to be desired go together in the weaker, who wants to become a function. Compassion is essentially the former, a pleasant stirring of the drive to appropriate at the sight of the weaker; however, we must still keep in mind that ‘strong’ and ‘weak’ are relative concepts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>119</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/119/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/119/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;No altruism!&lt;/em&gt; – In many people I see a surplus strength and pleasure in wanting to become a function; they press towards and have the most delicate sense for all places where precisely &lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; can be a function. Here belong those women who turn themselves into some function of a man that is especially weakly developed in him, and to that extent become his purse or his politics or his sociability. Such beings preserve themselves best when they insert themselves into another organism; if they do not succeed at this, they become cranky, irritated, and devour themselves.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>120</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/120/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/120/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Health of the soul.&lt;/em&gt; – The popular medical formulation of morality (the originator of which is Ariston of Chios), ‘virtue is the health of the soul’,3 would, in order to be useful, have to be changed at least to read, ‘your virtue is the health of your soul’. For there is no health as such, and all attempts to define such a thing have failed miserably. Deciding what is health even for your &lt;em&gt;body&lt;/em&gt; depends on your goal, your horizon, your powers, your impulses, your mistakes and above all on the ideals and phantasms of your soul. Thus there are innumerable healths of the body; and the more one allows the particular and incomparable to rear its head again, the more one unlearns the dogma of the ‘equality of men’, the more the concept of a normal health, along with those of a normal diet and normal course of an illness, must be abandoned by our medical men. Only then would it be timely to reflect on the health and illness of the &lt;em&gt;soul&lt;/em&gt; and to locate the virtue peculiar to each man in its health – which of course could look in one person like the opposite of health in another. Finally, the great question would still remain whether we can &lt;em&gt;do without&lt;/em&gt; illness, even for the development of our virtue; and whether especially our thirst for knowledge and self-knowledge do not need the sick soul as much as the healthy; in brief, whether the will to health alone is not a prejudice, a cowardice and a piece of most refined barbarism and backwardness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>121</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/121/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/121/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Life not an argument.&lt;/em&gt; – We have arranged for ourselves a world in which we are able to live – by positing bodies, lines, planes, causes and effects, motion and rest, form and content; without these articles of faith no one could endure living! But that does not prove them. Life is not an argument; the conditions of life might include error.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>122</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/122/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/122/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Moral scepticism in Christianity.&lt;/em&gt; – Christianity, too, has made a great contribution to enlightenment: it taught moral scepticism in an extremely trenchant and effective way – accusing, embittering, but with untiring patience and refinement; it annihilated in every single man the faith in his ‘virtues’. It caused those great virtuous men, of whom there was no dearth in antiquity, to disappear forever from the face of the earth – those popular men who with a faith in their own perfection went about with the dignity of a toreador. When we now, educated in this Christian school of scepticism, read the moral books of antiquity, e.g. those of Seneca or Epictetus,4 we feel an amusing superiority and are full of secret insights and overviews, as if a child were speaking before an old man or an overenthusiastic young beauty were speaking before La Rochefoucauld:5 we know better what virtue is! In the end, however, we have applied this same scepticism also to all &lt;em&gt;religious&lt;/em&gt; states and procedures, such as sin, repentance, grace, sanctification; and we have all allowed the worm to dig so deeply that even when reading Christian books we now have the same feeling of refined superiority and insight: we also know the religious feelings better! And it is time to know them well and to describe them well, for even the pious of the old faith are dying out: let us save their image and their type at least for knowledge!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>123</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/123/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/123/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Knowledge more than a means.&lt;/em&gt; – Even &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; this new passion – I mean the passion for knowledge – science would be promoted: up to now science has grown and matured without it. The good faith in science, the prejudice in its favour that rules our modern states (and formerly even the Church), is essentially based on the fact that this unconditional tendency and urge has manifested itself in science so rarely and that science is specifically regarded &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; as a passion but as a condition and ‘ethos’. Indeed, often mere &lt;em&gt;amour-plaisir&lt;/em&gt;6 of knowledge (curiosity) is sufficient, or &lt;em&gt;amour-vanité,7&lt;/em&gt; being accustomed to it with the ulterior motive of honour and bread; it is even enough for many that they have a surplus of leisure and do not know what to do with it except read, collect, arrange, observe, recount – their ‘scientific drive’ is their boredom. Pope Leo X8 once (in his brief to Beroaldus)9 sang the praise of science: he designated it the most beautiful ornament and the greatest pride of our life, a noble occupation in happiness and unhappiness; ‘without it’, he says finally, ‘all human undertakings would lack a firm hold – indeed, even with it they are changeable and unstable enough!’ But this fairly sceptical pope keeps silent, like all other churchly eulogists of science, his final judgement on science. Although one might infer from his words that he places science above art – strange as this may be for such a friend of the arts – in the end it is nothing but politeness when he does not speak of what he, too, places high above all science: ‘revealed truth’ and the ‘eternal salvation of the soul’. Compared to that, what are ornaments, pride, entertainment, and the security of life to him! ‘Science is something second-class; nothing ultimate, unconditional; not an object of passion’ – this judgement was held back in Leo’s soul: the truly Christian judgement about science! In antiquity the dignity and recognition of science were diminished by the fact that even among her most zealous disciples the striving for &lt;em&gt;virtue&lt;/em&gt; took first place, and that one thought one had given knowledge one’s highest praise when one celebrated it as the best means to virtue. It is something new in history that knowledge wants to be more than a means.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>124</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/124/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/124/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the horizon of the infinite.&lt;/em&gt; – We have forsaken the land and gone to sea! We have destroyed the bridge behind us – more so, we have demolished the land behind us! Now, little ship, look out! Beside you is the ocean; it is true, it does not always roar, and at times it lies there like silk and gold and dreams of goodness. But there will be hours when you realize that it is infinite and that there is nothing more awesome than infinity. Oh, the poor bird that has felt free and now strikes against the walls of this cage! Woe, when homesickness for the land overcomes you, as if there had been more &lt;em&gt;freedom&lt;/em&gt; there – and there is no more ‘land’!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>125</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/125/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/125/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The madman.&lt;/em&gt; – Haven’t you heard of that madman who in the bright morning lit a lantern and ran around the marketplace crying incessantly, ‘I’m looking for God! I’m looking for God!’ Since many of those who did not believe in God were standing around together just then, he caused great laughter. Has he been lost, then? asked one. Did he lose his way like a child? asked another. Or is he hiding? Is he afraid of us? Has he gone to sea? Emigrated? – Thus they shouted and laughed, one interrupting the other. The madman jumped into their midst and pierced them with his eyes. ‘Where is God?’ he cried; ‘I’ll tell you! &lt;em&gt;We have killed him&lt;/em&gt; – you and I! We are all his murderers. But how did we do this? How were we able to drink up the sea? Who gave us the sponge to wipe away the entire horizon? What were we doing when we unchained this earth from its sun? Where is it moving to now? Where are we moving to? Away from all suns? Are we not continually falling? And backwards, sidewards, forwards, in all directions? Is there still an up and a down? Aren’t we straying as though through an infinite nothing? Isn’t empty space breathing at us? Hasn’t it got colder? Isn’t night and more night coming again and again? Don’t lanterns have to be lit in the morning? Do we still hear nothing of the noise of the grave-diggers who are burying God? Do we still smell nothing of the divine decomposition? – Gods, too, decompose! God is dead! God remains dead! And we have killed him! How can we console ourselves, the murderers of all murderers! The holiest and the mightiest thing the world has ever possessed has bled to death under our knives: who will wipe this blood from us? With what water could we clean ourselves? What festivals of atonement, what holy games will we have to invent for ourselves? Is the magnitude of this deed not too great for us? Do we not ourselves have to become gods merely to appear worthy of it? There was never a greater deed – and whoever is born after us will on account of this deed belong to a higher history than all history up to now!’ Here the madman fell silent and looked again at his listeners; they too were silent and looked at him disconcertedly. Finally he threw his lantern on the ground so that it broke into pieces and went out. ‘I come too early’, he then said; ‘my time is not yet. This tremendous event is still on its way, wandering; it has not yet reached the ears of men. Lightning and thunder need time; the light of the stars needs time; deeds need time, even after they are done, in order to be seen and heard. This deed is still more remote to them than the remotest stars – &lt;em&gt;and yet they have done it themselves!&lt;/em&gt;’ It is still recounted how on the same day the madman forced his way into several churches and there started singing his *requiem aeternam deo.*10Led out and called to account, he is said always to have replied nothing but, ‘What then are these churches now if not the tombs and sepulchres of God?’&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>126</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/126/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/126/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mystical explanations&lt;/em&gt; – Mystical explanations are considered deep; the truth is, they are not even shallow.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>127</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/127/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/127/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aftereffects of the oldest religiosity.&lt;/em&gt; – Every thoughtless person believes that the will alone is effective; that willing is something simple, absolutely given, underivable, and intelligible in itself. When he does something, e.g. strikes something, he is convinced that it is &lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt; who is striking, and that he did the striking because he &lt;em&gt;wanted&lt;/em&gt; to strike. He does not even notice a problem here; the feeling of &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; suffices for him to assume cause and effect, but also to believe that he &lt;em&gt;understands&lt;/em&gt; their relation. He knows nothing of the mechanism of what happened and the hundredfold delicate work that has to be done to bring about the strike, or of the incapacity of the will as such to do even the slightest part of this work. The will is to him a force that works by magic: the belief in the will as the cause of effects is the belief in forces that work by magic. Now, originally man believed, wherever he saw something happen, that a will had to be the cause and that beings with a personal will had to be operating in the background – the concept of mechanics was quite foreign to him. But since man believed for immense periods of time only in persons (and not in substances, forces, things, etc.), the faith in cause and effect has become for him the fundamental faith that he uses everywhere something happens – still today instinctively and as an atavism of the oldest origin. The propositions, ‘no effect without a cause’, ‘every effect again a cause’, appear as generalizations of much narrower propositions: ‘no effecting without willing’; ‘it is possible to have an effect only on willing beings’; ‘no suffering of an effect is ever pure and without consequences, but all suffering is an agitation of the will’ (towards action, defence, revenge, retribution) – but in the prehistory of humanity the former and latter propositions were identical: the former were not generalizations of the latter, but the latter were elucidations of the former.11 With his assumption that only that which wills exists, Schopenhauer enthroned a primordial mythology; he seems never to have attempted an analysis of the will because like everyone else he &lt;em&gt;believed&lt;/em&gt; in the simplicity and immediacy of all willing – whereas willing is actually such a well-practised mechanism that it almost escapes the observing eye. Against him I offer these propositions: first, in order for willing to come about, a representation of pleasure or displeasure is needed. Secondly, that a violent stimulus is experienced as pleasure or pain is a matter of the &lt;em&gt;interpreting&lt;/em&gt; intellect, which, to be sure, generally works without our being conscious of it (&lt;em&gt;uns unbewufit);&lt;/em&gt; and one and the same stimulus &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be interpreted as pleasure or pain. Thirdly, only in intellectual beings do pleasure, pain, and will exist; the vast majority of organisms has nothing like it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>128</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/128/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/128/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The value of prayer.&lt;/em&gt; – Prayer has been invented for people who never really have thoughts of their own and who know no elevation of the soul or do not notice it if it occurs: what are such people to do in sacred places or in all important situations in life that demand calm and a kind of dignity? In order that they at least do not &lt;em&gt;disturb,&lt;/em&gt; the wisdom of all founders of religions, small as well as great, has prescribed to them the formulas of prayer as a long mechanical work of the lips, combined with exertion of the memory and a same fixed posture of hands and feet and eyes! So they may, like the Tibetans, go ahead regurgitating their ‘om mane padme hum’12 countless times or, as in Benares, count the name of the god off their fingers, Ram-Ram-Ram13 (and so on, with or without charm), or honour Vishnu with his thousand names,14 or Allah with his ninety-nine; or they may use prayer-mills and rosaries – the main point is that this work keeps them still for a time and makes them a tolerable sight: their type of prayer has been invented for the benefit of the pious who know thoughts and elevations of their own. And even they have their tired hours, when a string of venerable words and sounds and a mechanical piety do them good. But supposing these rare human beings – in every religion the religious person is an exception – can figure out what to do; those who are poor in spirit cannot figure out what to do, and to forbid them their prayer-rattling is to deprive them of their religion – as Protestantism increasingly shows us more and more. From such people religion wants only that they &lt;em&gt;keep still&lt;/em&gt; with their eyes, hands, legs, and other organs; thus they are made beautiful for a time and – more like human beings!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>129</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/129/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/129/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The conditions for God.&lt;/em&gt; – ‘God himself cannot exist without wise people’, said Luther,15 and with good reason; but ‘God can exist even less without unwise people’ – that our good Luther did not say!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>130</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/130/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/130/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A dangerous decision.&lt;/em&gt; – The Christian decision to find the world ugly and bad has made the world ugly and bad.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>131</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/131/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/131/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Christianity and suicide.&lt;/em&gt; – When Christianity came into existence the inclination to suicide was very strong – Christianity turned it into a lever of its power: it allowed only two kinds of suicide, dressed them up with the highest dignity and the highest hopes and forbade all others in a terrible manner. But martyrdom and the ascetic’s slow suicide were permitted.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>132</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/132/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/132/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Against Christianity.&lt;/em&gt; – What decides against Christianity now is our taste, not our reasons.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>133</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/133/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/133/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Principle.&lt;/em&gt; – An inescapable hypothesis to which humanity must have recourse again and again is still &lt;em&gt;more powerful&lt;/em&gt; in the long run than the best believed faith in something untrue (such as the Christian faith). In the long run: that means here a hundred thousand years.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>134</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/134/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/134/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pessimists as victims.&lt;/em&gt; – Wherever a deep dissatisfaction with existence comes to prevail, it is the aftereffects of some great dietary mistake made by a people over a long time that are coming to light. Thus the spread of Buddhism (&lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; its origin) depended greatly on the Indians’ excessive and almost exclusive diet of rice and the general enervation resulting from it. Perhaps the modern European discontent is due to the fact that our prehistory, the entire middle ages, was given to drinking thanks to the influence of Germanic tastes on Europe: the middle ages means the alcohol poisoning of Europe. – The German dissatisfaction with life is essentially a winter sickness exacerbated by the effects of cellar air and the noxious stove fumes in German living rooms.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>135</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/135/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/135/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Origin of sin.&lt;/em&gt; – Sin, as it is now experienced wherever Christianity reigns or once reigned: sin is a Jewish feeling and a Jewish invention; and given that this is the background of all Christian morality, Christianity can be said to have aimed at ‘Judaizing’ the whole world. The extent to which this has succeeded in Europe is best brought out by how alien Greek antiquity – a world without feelings of sin – strikes our sensibility as being, despite all the good will expended by entire generations and many excellent individuals to approach and incorporate this world. ‘Only when you &lt;em&gt;repent&lt;/em&gt; does God have mercy on you’ – to a Greek, that is an object of ridicule and an annoyance; he would say, ‘Maybe slaves feel that way.’ What is here being presupposed is a being who is powerful, supremely powerful and yet enjoys revenge: his power is so great that no harm whatsoever can be done unto him except in matters of honour. Every sin is an injury of respect, a &lt;em&gt;crimen laesae majestatis divinae&lt;/em&gt;16 – and nothing further! Feeling spiritually crushed, degraded, wallowing in the dust – that is the first and last condition of his grace; in sum, restoration of his divine honour! Whether the sin has done any other harm; whether it has planted some deep, growing calamity that seizes and strangles one person after another like a disease; this honour-craving Oriental couldn’t care less: sin is an assault on him, not on humanity! He gives those to whom he grants his grace also this same nonchalance about the natural consequences of sin. God and humanity are here conceived as so separate and opposite that there can basically be no sin against humanity – every deed is supposed to be considered &lt;em&gt;only with respect to its supernatural consequences,&lt;/em&gt; not with respect to its natural consequences; that is what Jewish feeling, to which everything natural is indignity itself, demands. The Greeks, by contrast, were closer to the thought that even sacrilege can have dignity – even theft, as in the case of Prometheus;17 even the slaughter of cattle as the expression of an insane envy, as in the case of Ajax:18 in their need to incorporate into and devise some dignity for sacrilege, they invented &lt;em&gt;tragedy&lt;/em&gt; – an art form and a pleasure that has remained utterly and profoundly foreign to the Jew, despite all his poetic talent and inclination towards the sublime.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>136</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/136/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/136/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The chosen people.&lt;/em&gt; – The Jews, who feel they are the chosen people of all peoples precisely because they are the moral genius of all peoples (owing to their ability &lt;em&gt;more profoundly to despise&lt;/em&gt; the human being in themselves than any other people) – the Jews take a pleasure in their divine monarch and the holy which is similar to that which the French nobility took in Louis XIV. This nobility had surrendered all its power and sovereignty and had become contemptible: in order not to feel this, in order to be able to forget this, there was a need for a royal splendour, a royal authority and plenitude of power &lt;em&gt;without equal&lt;/em&gt; to which only the nobility had access. In rising to the height of the court by virtue of this privilege and seeing from there everything as beneath oneself, as contemptible, one got over an irritable conscience. Thus one deliberately built the tower of royal power ever higher into the clouds and staked on it the ultimate building stones of one’s own power.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>137</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/137/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/137/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Speaking in a parable.&lt;/em&gt; – A Jesus Christ was possible only in a Jewish landscape – I mean one over which the gloomy and sublime thunder clouds of the wrathful Jehovah hovered continually. Here alone was the rare and sudden piercing of a single sunbeam through the gruesome general and perpetual day-night experienced as a miracle of ‘love’, as the ray of the most undeserved ‘grace’. Only here could Christ dream of his rainbow and his heavenly ladder on which God descended to man; everywhere else good weather and sunshine were too much of a rule and everyday occurrence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>138</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/138/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/138/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Christ’s error.&lt;/em&gt; – The founder of Christianity thought that there was nothing from which men suffered more than their sins. That was his error – the error of one who felt himself free of sin and who lacked experience of it! Thus his soul filled itself with that wonderful fantastic compassion for a torment that was rarely a very great torment even among his people, who invented sin! But the Christians have found a way of retroactively vindicating their master and of sanctifying his error into ‘truth’.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>139</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/139/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/139/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The colour of the passions.&lt;/em&gt; – People like St Paul have an ‘evil eye’ for the passions: they come to know only what is dirty, disfiguring, and heartbreaking about them; hence their ideal impulse seeks the annihilation of the passions, which they see totally purified in the divine. Quite unlike St Paul and the Jews, the Greeks turned their ideal impulse precisely towards the passions and loved, elevated, gilded and deified them; evidently passion made them feel not only happier but also purer and more divine than usual. And the Christians? Did they want to become Jews in this respect? Did they perhaps succeed?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>140</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/140/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/140/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Too Jewish.&lt;/em&gt; – If God wanted to become an object of love, he should first of all have had to give up judging and justice: a judge, even a merciful one, is no object of love. The founder of Christianity lacked delicacy of feeling in this regard, being a Jew.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>141</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/141/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/141/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Too oriental.&lt;/em&gt; – What? A god who loves men provided that they believe in him and who casts evil gazes and threats at anyone who does not believe in this love? What? A love hemmed in by conditions as the feeling of an almighty god? A love that has not even mastered the feeling of honour and roused vengefulness? How oriental this all is! ‘If I love you, what does that concern you?’19 is surely a sufficient critique of all of Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>142</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/142/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/142/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Incense.&lt;/em&gt; – Buddha says: ‘Don’t flatter your benefactors!’ Repeat this saying in a Christian church and it will instantly clear the air of everything Christian.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>143</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/143/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/143/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The greatest advantage of polytheism.&lt;/em&gt; – For an individual to posit his &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt; ideal and to derive from it his own law, joys and rights – that may well have been considered hitherto to be the most outrageous of human aberrations and idolatry itself; indeed, the few who dared it always felt the need to apologize to themselves, usually as follows: ‘Not I! Not I! But a &lt;em&gt;god&lt;/em&gt; through me!’ The wonderful art and power of creating gods – polytheism – was that through which this drive could discharge itself, purify, perfect and ennoble itself; for originally it was a base and undistinguished drive, related to stubbornness, disobedience, and envy. To be &lt;em&gt;hostile&lt;/em&gt; to this drive to have one’s own ideal: that was formerly the law of every morality. There was only one norm: &lt;em&gt;‘the&lt;/em&gt; human being’ – and every people believed itself to &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; this one and ultimate norm. But above and outside oneself, in a distant overworld, one got to see a &lt;em&gt;plurality of norms:&lt;/em&gt; one god was not the denial of or anathema to another god! Here for the first time one allowed oneself individuals; here one first honoured the rights of individuals. The invention of gods, heroes, and overmen (&lt;em&gt;Übermenschen&lt;/em&gt;) of all kinds, as well as deviant or inferior forms of humanoid life (&lt;em&gt;Neben- und Untermenschen),&lt;/em&gt; dwarfs, fairies, centaurs, satyrs, demons, and devils, was the invaluable preliminary exercise for the justification of the egoism and sovereignty of the individual: the freedom that one conceded to a god in his relation to other gods one finally gave to oneself in relation to laws, customs, and neighbours. Monotheism, in contrast, this rigid consequence of the teachings of a normal human type – that is, the belief in a normal god next to whom there are only false pseudo-gods – was perhaps the greatest danger to humanity so far: it threatened us with that premature stagnation which, as far as we can tell, most other species have long reached; for all of them believe in one normal type and ideal for their species and have translated the morality of custom (&lt;em&gt;Sittlichkeit der Sitte&lt;/em&gt;) definitively into flesh and blood. In polytheism the free-spiritedness and many-spiritedness of humanity received preliminary form – the power to create for ourselves our own new eyes and ever again new eyes that are ever more our own – so that for humans alone among the animals there are no eternal horizons and perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>144</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/144/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/144/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Religious wars.&lt;/em&gt; – The greatest progress of the masses up till now has been the religious war, for it proves that the mass has begun to treat concepts with respect. Religious wars start only when the finer quarrels among sects have refined common reason so that even the mob becomes subtle and takes trifles seriously, and actually considers it possible that the ‘eternal salvation of the soul’ might hinge on slight differences between concepts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>145</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/145/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/145/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Danger for vegetarians.&lt;/em&gt; – A diet consisting primarily of rice leads to the use of opium and narcotics, just as a diet consisting primarily of potatoes leads to the use of liquor. But its subtler effects also include ways of thinking and feeling that work narcotically. This harmonizes with the fact that the promoters of narcotic ways of thinking and feeling, like those Indian gurus, praise precisely a diet that is purely vegetarian and would like to make that a law of the masses: thus they want to call forth and increase a need that &lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; are able to satisfy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>146</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/146/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/146/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;German hopes.&lt;/em&gt; – Let us not forget that names of peoples are usually terms of abuse. The Tartars, for example, are literally ‘the dogs’; that is what the Chinese called them. The ‘Germans’: this originally meant ‘heathen’; that is what the Goths after their conversion named the great mass of their unbaptized kindred tribes, in accordance with their translation of the Septuagint20 in which the heathens were designated with a word that in Greek means ‘the nations’; see Ulfilas.21 It would still be possible for the Germans to turn the term of abuse for them into a name of honour by becoming the first &lt;em&gt;un-Christian&lt;/em&gt; nation in Europe: for which Schopenhauer honoured them as having a very strong predisposition. That would be a way of fulfilling the words of &lt;em&gt;Luther,&lt;/em&gt; who taught them to be un-Roman and to say: ‘Here &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; stand! &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; can do no other!’22&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>147</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/147/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/147/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Question and answer.&lt;/em&gt; – What do savage tribes today take over first of all from the Europeans? Liquor and Christianity, the narcotics of Europe. And from what do they perish most quickly? From European narcotics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>148</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/148/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/148/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Where reformations arise.&lt;/em&gt; – At the time of the great corruption of the Church, the Church in Germany was the least corrupt; that is why the Reformation occurred &lt;em&gt;here,&lt;/em&gt; as a sign that even the beginnings of corruption were felt to be intolerable. For relatively speaking, no people has ever been more Christian than the Germans at the time of Luther; their Christian culture was ready to burst into a hundredfold splendour of blossoms – only one more night was needed, but this brought the storm that put an end to everything.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>149</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/149/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/149/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The failure of reformations.&lt;/em&gt; – That several attempts to found new Greek religions have failed testifies to the higher culture of the Greeks even in rather early times; it indicates that even early in Greece, there must have been many diverse individuals whose diverse plights could not be disposed of with a single prescription of faith and hope. Pythagoras23 and Plato, perhaps Empedocles24 as well, and the Orphic enthusiasts25 much earlier yet, were out to found new religions; and the former two had souls and talents which were so much those of founders of religions that one cannot wonder enough at their failure; yet all they managed to found were sects. Every time the reformation of an entire people fails and only sects raise their heads, one may conclude that the people is already very heterogeneous and is starting to break away from crude herd instincts and the morality of custom (&lt;em&gt;Sittlichkeit der Sitte):&lt;/em&gt; a notable hovering condition which one usually disparages as decay in morals and corruption, when in fact it announces the maturation of the egg and the impending breaking of the eggshell. That Luther’s reformation succeeded in the North is a sign of the fact that the North was backward in comparison to the South and still had rather uniform and monochrome needs; Europe would not have been christianized at all had not the culture of the old world of the South gradually been barbarized through an excessive admixture of Germanic barbarian blood and its cultural superiority lost. The more general and unconditional the influence of an individual or an individual’s thought can be, the more homogeneous and the lower must the mass be that is influenced, while counter-movements betray inner counter-needs that also want satisfaction and recognition. Conversely, one may always infer a high level of culture when powerful and domineering natures only manage to have a slight and sectarian influence: this is also true of the individual arts and the areas of knowledge. Where there is ruling, there are masses; where there are masses, there is a need for slavery. Where there is slavery, there are few individuals, and these have herd instincts and conscience against them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>150</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/150/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/150/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Towards a critique of saints.&lt;/em&gt; – Must one then, in order to have a virtue, want to have it in its most brutal form – the way the Christian saints wanted and needed it, as those who endured life only with the thought that the mere sight of their virtue would destroy the self-esteem of anyone who viewed it? But a virtue with such an effect I call brutal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>151</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/151/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/151/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On the origin of religion.&lt;/em&gt; – The metaphysical need is not the origin of religion, as Schopenhauer26 has it, but only a &lt;em&gt;late offshoot&lt;/em&gt; of it. Under the rule of religious ideas, one has got used to the idea of ‘another world (behind, below, above)’ and feels an unpleasant emptiness and deprivation at the annihilation of religious delusions – and from this feeling grows now ‘another world’, but this time only a metaphysical and not a religious one. But what led to the belief in ‘another world’ in primordial times was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a drive or need, but an &lt;em&gt;error&lt;/em&gt; in the interpretation of certain natural events, an embarrassing lapse of the intellect.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>152</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/152/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/152/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The greatest change.&lt;/em&gt; – The lighting and colours of everything have changed! We no longer fully understand how the ancients experienced what was most familiar and frequent – for example the day and waking. Because the ancients believed in dreams, waking life had a different light. The same goes for the whole of life, illuminated by a light radiated back on it from death and its significance: our ‘death’ is a completely different death. All experiences shone differently because a god glowed from them; all decisions and prospects concerning the distant future as well, for one had oracles and secret signs and believed in prophecy. ‘Truth’ was formerly experienced differently because the lunatic could be considered its mouthpiece – which makes &lt;em&gt;us&lt;/em&gt; shudder and laugh. Every injustice affected feelings differently, for one feared divine retribution and not just a civil punishment and dishonour. What was joy in an age when one believed in devils and tempters! What was passion when one saw the demons lurking nearby! What was philosophy when doubt was felt as a sin of the most dangerous kind, as a sacrilege against eternal love, as mistrust of everything that is good, lofty, pure, and merciful! We have given things a new colour; we keep on painting them – but what can we nowadays accomplish in comparison to the &lt;em&gt;splendour of colour&lt;/em&gt; of that old master! I mean ancient humanity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>153</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/153/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/153/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;*Homo poeta.*27 – ‘I myself, who most single-handedly made this tragedy of tragedies, insofar as it is finished; I, having first tied the knot of morality into existence and drawn it so tight that only a god can loosen it – which is what Horace demands!28 – I myself have now in the fourth act slain all gods, out of morality! What is now to become of the fifth act? From where shall I take the tragic solution? Should I start considering a comic solution?’&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>154</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/154/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/154/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Different types of danger in life.&lt;/em&gt; – You have no idea what you are experiencing; you run through life as if you were drunk and once in a while fall down a staircase. But thanks to your drunkenness, you don’t break your limbs in the process; your muscles are too slack and your head too dull for you to find the stones of these stairs as hard as the rest of us do! For us, life is a greater danger: we are made of glass – woe unto us if we &lt;em&gt;bump&lt;/em&gt; against something! And everything is lost if we &lt;em&gt;fall&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>155</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/155/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/155/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What we lack.&lt;/em&gt; – We love what is &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt; in nature and have discovered it – because in our heads, great human beings are lacking. It was the other way around for the Greeks; their feeling for nature is different from ours.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>156</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/156/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/156/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The most influential.&lt;/em&gt; – That a human being resists his whole age, stops it at the gate and demands an accounting – that &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; exercise an influence! Whether he wants to is irrelevant; that he &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; is what matters.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>157</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/157/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/157/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mentiri.29&lt;/em&gt; – Watch out! He’s thinking; in a moment he will have a lie ready. This is a stage of culture at which entire peoples have stood. Just consider what the Romans meant by the word &lt;em&gt;mentiri!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>158</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/158/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/158/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;An uncomfortable trait.&lt;/em&gt; – To find all things deep – that is an uncomfortable trait: it makes one constantly strain one’s eyes and in the end always find more than one had wished.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>159</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/159/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/159/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Every virtue has its age.&lt;/em&gt; – Whoever is unyielding these days will often have pangs of conscience because of his candour; for unyieldingness and candour are virtues that belongs to different ages.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>160</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/160/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/160/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dealing with virtues.&lt;/em&gt; – To a virtue, too, one can be undignified and fawning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>161</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/161/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/161/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To the lovers of the age.&lt;/em&gt; – The ex-priest and the ex-convict constantly make faces: what they want is a face without a past. – But have you ever seen people who know that the future is mirrored in their faces and are so polite to you, you lovers of ‘the age’, that they make a face without a future?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>162</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/162/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/162/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Egoism.&lt;/em&gt; – Egoism is the &lt;em&gt;perspectival&lt;/em&gt; law of feeling according to which what is closest appears large and heavy, while in the distance everything decreases in size and weight.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>163</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/163/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/163/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;After a great victory.&lt;/em&gt; – The best thing about a great victory is that it takes the fear of defeat out of the victor. ‘Why not also be defeated once?’ he says to himself; ‘I’m rich enough for that now.’&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>164</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/164/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/164/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The seekers of rest.&lt;/em&gt; – I recognize the spirits who seek rest by the many &lt;em&gt;dark&lt;/em&gt; objects with which they surround themselves: he who wants to sleep makes his room dark or crawls into a cave. – A hint to those who don’t know, but would like to know, what they actually seek most!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>165</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/165/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/165/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On the happiness of those who renounce something.&lt;/em&gt; – He who thoroughly forgoes something for a long time will, upon accidentally re-encountering it, almost think he has discovered it – and what happiness every discoverer has! Let us be wiser than the snakes who lie too long in the same sunlight.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>166</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/166/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/166/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Always in our company.&lt;/em&gt; – Everything that is of my kind, in nature and history, speaks to me, praises me, spurs me on, comforts me – everything else I don’t hear or forget right away. We are always only in our own company.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>167</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/167/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/167/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Misanthropy and love.&lt;/em&gt; – One speaks of being sick of people only when one can no longer digest them and yet still has one’s stomach full of them. Misanthropy is the result of an all-too-greedy love of man and ‘cannibalism’ – but who told you to swallow men like oysters, my Prince Hamlet?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>168</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/168/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/168/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;About a sick man.&lt;/em&gt; – ‘He is doing badly!’ – ‘What’s wrong?’ – ‘He is suffering from the desire to be praised and finds no nourishment for it.’ ‘Unbelievable! The whole world is celebrating him, and pampering him; he is on everyone’s lips.’ – ‘Yes, but he has a bad ear for praise. If a friend praises him, it sounds to him as if the friend is praising himself. If an enemy praises him, it sounds to him as if the enemy wants be praised for that. And when finally he is praised by any of the rest – and they are not many at all; that is how famous he is! – it offends him that they don’t want him as a friend or enemy; he likes to say: What do I care about people who are capable of trying to play “the just man” even towards me?’&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>169</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/169/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/169/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Open enemies.&lt;/em&gt; – Courage before the enemy is one thing; it does not prevent one from being a coward and indecisive scatterbrain. That is how Napoleon judged ‘the most courageous person’ he knew: Murat.30 Which shows that open enemies are indispensable to some people if they are to rise to &lt;em&gt;their own&lt;/em&gt; kind of virtue, manliness, and cheerfulness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>170</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/170/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/170/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;With the crowd.&lt;/em&gt; – So far he is still running with the crowd and singing its praises, but one day he will become its opponent! For he is following it thinking that this will give his laziness full play, and he has not yet discovered that the crowd is not lazy enough for him! That it always pushes ahead! That it allows no one to stand still! – And he so much likes to stand still!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>171</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/171/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/171/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fame.&lt;/em&gt; – When the gratitude of many towards one throws away all shame, fame arises.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>172</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/172/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/172/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The spoiler of taste.&lt;/em&gt; – A: ‘You are a spoiler of taste – that is what everyone says!’ B: ‘Of course! I spoil for everyone the taste for his own party – and no party forgives that.’&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>173</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/173/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/173/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Being deep and seeming deep.&lt;/em&gt; – Those who know they are deep strive for clarity. Those who would like to seem deep to the crowd strive for obscurity. For the crowd takes everything whose ground it cannot see to be deep: it is so timid and so reluctant to go into the water.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>174</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/174/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/174/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aside.&lt;/em&gt; – Parliamentarianism, i.e. the public permission to choose between five basic political opinions, flatters and wins the favour of all those who like to &lt;em&gt;appear&lt;/em&gt; independent and individualistic and would like to fight for their opinions. In the end, however, it is irrelevant whether the herd is commanded to have one opinion or permitted to have five. Whoever deviates from the five public opinions and steps aside will always have the whole herd against him.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>175</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/175/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/175/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On eloquence.&lt;/em&gt; – Who has had the most convincing eloquence so far? The drum roll; and as long as kings and commanders have control over that, they will remain the best orators and rabble rousers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>176</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/176/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/176/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Compassion.&lt;/em&gt; – Those poor reigning princes! All their rights are now suddenly turning into claims, and all these claims soon begin to sound like presumptions! The moment they merely say ‘We’ or ‘my people’, wicked old Europe starts to smile. Verily, a chief master of ceremonies in the modern world would waste little ceremony on them and might perhaps decree: ‘les souverains rangent aux parvenus.’31&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>177</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/177/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/177/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On ‘the educational establishment’.&lt;/em&gt; – In Germany, higher men lack one great means of education: the laughter of higher men; for in Germany, these do not laugh.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>178</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/178/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/178/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On moral enlightenment.&lt;/em&gt; – One must talk the Germans out of their Mephistopheles, and their Faust, too. They are two moral prejudices against the value of knowledge.32&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>179</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/179/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/179/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thoughts.&lt;/em&gt; – Thoughts are the shadows of our sensations – always darker, emptier, simpler.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>180</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/180/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/180/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The good age for free spirits.&lt;/em&gt; – Free spirits take liberties even with science – and for the time being, one also allows them to – as long as the Church is still standing! To that extent they now have their good age.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>181</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/181/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/181/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Following and leading.&lt;/em&gt; – A: ‘Of these two, one will always follow and the other will always lead, wherever fate may take them. And &lt;em&gt;yet&lt;/em&gt; the former is superior to the other in virtue and spirit!’ B: ‘And yet? And yet? That was said for the others, not for me, not for us! – &lt;em&gt;Fit secundum regulam.’33&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>182</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/182/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/182/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In solitude.&lt;/em&gt; – When one lives alone, one neither speaks too loud nor writes too loud, for one fears the hollow echo – the criticism of the nymph Echo. And all voices sound different in solitude!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>183</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/183/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/183/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The music of the best future.&lt;/em&gt; – I would consider the foremost musician to be the one who knew only the sadness of the deepest happiness, and no other sadness at all; there has never been such a musician.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>184</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/184/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/184/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Justice.&lt;/em&gt; – I’d rather let myself be robbed than be surrounded by scarecrows – that is my taste. And in any case it is a matter of taste – nothing more!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>185</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/185/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/185/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Poor.&lt;/em&gt; – Today he is poor, not because they have taken everything away from him but because he has thrown everything away. What is that to him? He is used to &lt;em&gt;finding&lt;/em&gt; things. It is the poor who misunderstand his voluntary poverty.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>186</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/186/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/186/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bad conscience.&lt;/em&gt; – Everything he does now is upright and orderly – and still he has a bad conscience. For the extraordinary is his task.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>187</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/187/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/187/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What is offensive in the presentation.&lt;/em&gt; – This artist offends me in the way he presents his ideas, his very good ideas: so broad and emphatic, and with such crude artifices of persuasion, as if he were speaking to a mob. Whenever we devote some time to his art, it is soon as if we were ‘in bad company’.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>188</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/188/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/188/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Work.&lt;/em&gt; – How close work and the worker are now even to the most leisurely among us! The royal courtesy of the words ‘We are all workers!’ would still have been a cynicism and an indecency under the reign of Louis XIV.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>189</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/189/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/189/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The thinker.&lt;/em&gt; – He is a thinker: that means he knows how to make things simpler than they are.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>190</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/190/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/190/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Against those who praise.&lt;/em&gt; – A: ‘One is praised only by one’s peers.’ B: ‘Yes! And whoever praises you tells you: you are my peer!’&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>191</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/191/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/191/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Against many a defence.&lt;/em&gt; – The most perfidious way of damaging a cause is deliberately to defend it with faulty arguments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>192</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/192/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/192/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The good-natured.&lt;/em&gt; – What distinguishes those good-natured people whose faces radiate good will from the rest? They feel well in the presence of another person and quickly fall in love with him; consequently they wish him well, and their first judgement is: ‘I like him.’ In such people there is the following succession: the wish to appropriate (they do not scruple much over the worth of the other person), quick appropriation, delight in possession, and action for the benefit of the person possessed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>193</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/193/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/193/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kant’s joke.&lt;/em&gt; – Kant wanted to prove, in a way that would dumbfound the whole world, that the whole world was right: that was the secret joke of this soul. He wrote against the scholars in favour of popular prejudice, but for scholars and not for the people.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>194</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/194/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/194/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The ‘openhearted’ one.&lt;/em&gt; – That person probably always acts according to secret reasons, for he always has communicable reasons on his tongue and virtually in his open hand.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>195</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/195/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/195/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Laughable.&lt;/em&gt; – Look! Look! He is running away from people, but they follow him because he is running &lt;em&gt;ahead&lt;/em&gt; of them – that is how much they are a herd!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>196</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/196/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/196/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Limits of our sense of hearing.&lt;/em&gt; – One hears only those questions to which one is able to find an answer.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>197</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/197/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/197/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Better be careful!&lt;/em&gt; – There is nothing we like so much to impart to others as the seal of secrecy – along with what is under it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>198</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/198/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/198/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chagrin of the proud one.&lt;/em&gt; – The proud man feels chagrined even by those who bring him forward: he gives the horse of his carriage the evil eye.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>199</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/199/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/199/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Generosity.&lt;/em&gt; – With the rich, generosity is often just a type of shyness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>200</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/200/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/200/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Laughter.&lt;/em&gt; – Laughter means: to gloat, but with a good conscience.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>201</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/201/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/201/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Applause.&lt;/em&gt; – In applause there is always a kind of noise – even in the applause we give ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>202</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/202/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/202/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A squanderer.&lt;/em&gt; – As yet he does not have that poverty of the rich man who has already counted his entire treasure once – he squanders his spirit with the unreason of a squandering nature.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>203</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/203/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/203/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hic niger est.34&lt;/em&gt; – Usually he has no thought – but on rare occasions bad thoughts come to him.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>204</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/204/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/204/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Beggars and courtesy.&lt;/em&gt; – ‘One isn’t being impolite if one uses a stone to knock on a door which lacks a doorbell’: that is how beggars think, and everyone who is suffering some kind of distress, but no one thinks they are right.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>205</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/205/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/205/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Need.&lt;/em&gt; – Need is taken to be the cause why something came to be; in reality, it is often merely an effect of what has come to be.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>206</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/206/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/206/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When it rains.&lt;/em&gt; – It is raining, and I think of the poor who now huddle together with their many troubles and without any practice at concealing them: each is ready to hurt the other and to make for himself a pitiful kind of pleasure even when the weather is bad. That and that alone is the poverty of the poor!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>207</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/207/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/207/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The envious one.&lt;/em&gt; – He is envious – let’s hope he won’t have any children; he would envy them because he can no longer be a child.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>208</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/208/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/208/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Great man!&lt;/em&gt; – From the fact that someone is a ‘great man’ one cannot infer that he is a man; he may be just a boy, or a chameleon of all stages of life, or a bewitched little woman.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>209</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/209/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/209/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A way of asking for reasons.&lt;/em&gt; – There is a way of asking us for our reasons that not only makes us forget our best reasons but also awakens in us a defiance and resistance towards reasons in general – a very stultifying mode of asking and a trick used by tyrannical people!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>210</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/210/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/210/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Moderation in diligence.&lt;/em&gt; – One should not try to surpass one’s father in diligence; that makes one sick.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>211</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/211/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/211/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Secret enemies.&lt;/em&gt; – To be able to afford a secret enemy – that is a luxury for which the morality even of elevated spirits is usually not rich enough.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>212</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/212/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/212/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Not to let oneself be deceived.&lt;/em&gt; – His spirit has bad manners, is hasty and always stutters out of impatience; hence one hardly recognizes how much stamina and robustness the soul possesses in which this spirit dwells.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>213</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/213/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/213/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The road to happiness.&lt;/em&gt; – A wise man asked a fool what the road to happiness is. The latter replied without delay, like someone being asked the way to the nearest town: ‘Admire yourself and live on the street!’ ‘Stop,’ replied the sage, ‘you are asking too much; it is quite enough to admire oneself!’ The fool countered: ‘But how can one constantly admire without constantly feeling contempt?’&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>214</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/214/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/214/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Faith makes blessed.&lt;/em&gt; – Virtue gives happiness and a type of blessedness only to those who have not lost faith in their virtue – not to those subtler souls whose virtue consists of a deep mistrust of themselves and of all virtue. So in the end, here, too, ‘faith makes blessed’35 – and, mind you, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; virtue!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>215</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/215/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/215/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ideal and material.&lt;/em&gt; – You envisage a noble ideal, but are &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; such a noble stone that such a divine image could be fashioned out of you? And anyway – isn’t all your work a barbarous sculpting? A blasphemy against your ideal?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>216</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/216/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/216/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Danger in the voice.&lt;/em&gt; – With a very loud voice in one’s throat one is almost incapable of thinking subtle things.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>217</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/217/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/217/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cause and effect.&lt;/em&gt; – Before the effect one believes in causes different from those one believes in after the effect.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>218</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/218/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/218/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My antipathy.&lt;/em&gt; – I do not love people who have to explode like bombs in order to have any effect whatsoever and in whose presence one is always in danger of suddenly losing one’s hearing – or more.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>219</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/219/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/219/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The purpose of punishment.&lt;/em&gt; – The purpose of punishment is to improve the one &lt;em&gt;who punishes;&lt;/em&gt; that is the last resort of the apologists for punishment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>220</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/220/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/220/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sacrifice.&lt;/em&gt; – The sacrificial animal thinks differently about sacrifice than the spectator, but one has never let it have its say.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>221</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/221/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/221/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Forbearance.&lt;/em&gt; – Fathers and sons have much more forbearance for each other than mothers and daughters.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>222</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/222/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/222/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Poet and liar.&lt;/em&gt; – The poet sees in the liar a foster brother (&lt;em&gt;Milchbruder&lt;/em&gt;) whose milk he has drunk up; that is why the latter has remained stunted and miserable and has not even got as far as having a good conscience.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>223</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/223/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/223/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vicariousness of the senses.&lt;/em&gt; – ‘Our eyes are also intended for hearing’, said the old father confessor who had gone deaf, ‘and among the blind he is king who has the longest ears.’&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>224</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/224/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/224/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Animals’ criticism.&lt;/em&gt; – I fear that the animals see man as a being like them who in a most dangerous manner has lost his animal common sense – as the insane animal, the laughing animal, the weeping animal, the miserable animal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>225</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/225/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/225/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The natural.&lt;/em&gt; – ‘Evil has always had great effects in its favour! And nature is evil! Let us therefore be natural!’ That is the secret reasoning of the great effect-artists of humanity, who have all too often been considered great human beings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>226</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/226/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/226/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The distrustful and style.&lt;/em&gt; – We say the strongest things simply, provided that we are among people who believe in our strength – such an environment breeds ‘simplicity of style’. The distrustful speak emphatically; the distrustful make emphatic.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>227</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/227/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/227/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bad inference; bad shot.&lt;/em&gt; – He cannot control himself; from that, a woman infers that it would be easy to control him and casts her net for him – the poor woman who will shortly be his slave.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>228</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/228/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/228/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Against mediators.&lt;/em&gt; – He who wants to mediate between two resolute thinkers shows that he is mediocre: he has no eye for what is unique; seeing things as similar and making things the same is the sign of weak eyes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>229</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/229/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/229/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Obstinacy and faithfulness.&lt;/em&gt; – From defiance he clings to something he has come to see through, but he calls it ‘faithfulness’.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>230</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/230/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/230/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lack of silence.&lt;/em&gt; – His whole being fails to &lt;em&gt;persuade&lt;/em&gt; – that is because he has never remained silent about any of his good deeds.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>231</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/231/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/231/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The ‘thorough’.&lt;/em&gt; – Those who are slow to know think that slowness is an aspect of knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>232</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/232/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/232/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dreaming.&lt;/em&gt; – Either one does not dream, or does so interestingly. One should learn to spend one’s waking life in the same way: not at all, or interestingly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>233</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/233/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/233/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The most dangerous point of view.&lt;/em&gt; – What I now do or omit is as important for &lt;em&gt;everything that is to come&lt;/em&gt; as the greatest event of the past: seen from this tremendous perspective, from that of their effects, all actions appear equally great and small.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>234</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/234/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/234/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Words of comfort for a musician.&lt;/em&gt; – ‘Your life does not reach men’s ears; to them you live a mute life, and all the subtlety of melody, all tender resolution about following or leading, remain hidden from them. It is true: you are not coming down a main street with regimental music, but that does not give these good people the right to say your way of life lacks music. He who has ears to hear, let him hear!’&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>235</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/235/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/235/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spirit and character.&lt;/em&gt; – Some reach their peak as characters, but their spirit is not adequate for this height, while with others it is the other way around.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>236</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/236/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/236/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In order to move the crowd.&lt;/em&gt; – Must not he who wants to move the crowd be an actor playing the role of himself? Must he not first translate himself into the grotesquely obvious and &lt;em&gt;present&lt;/em&gt; his entire person and cause in this coarsened and simplified version?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>237</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/237/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/237/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The polite one.&lt;/em&gt; – ‘He is so polite!’ – Yes, he always carries a cake for Cerberus36 and is so timid that he takes everyone for Cerberus, even you and me; that is his ‘politeness’.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>238</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/238/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/238/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Without envy.&lt;/em&gt; – He is quite without envy, but that has no merit because he wants to conquer a country that no one has yet possessed and hardly anyone has ever seen.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>239</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/239/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/239/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The joyless one.&lt;/em&gt; – One single joyless person is enough to create constant sullenness and dark skies for a an entire household, and only a miracle can cause that one person to be lacking! Happiness is not nearly as contagious a disease – why is that?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>240</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/240/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/240/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;At the sea.&lt;/em&gt; – I wouldn’t build a house for myself (and it is part of my good fortune not to be a home-owner!). But if I had to, I would, like some Romans, build it right into the sea – I certainly would like to share a few secrets with this beautiful monster.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>241</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/241/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/241/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Work and artist.&lt;/em&gt; – This artist is ambitious, nothing more: ultimately his work is just a magnifying glass that he offers everyone who looks his way.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>242</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/242/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/242/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Suum cuique?37&lt;/em&gt; – However great my greed for knowledge may be, I cannot take anything else out of things than what already belongs to me – what belongs to others remains behind. How is it possible for a human being to be a thief or a robber!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>243</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/243/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/243/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Origin of ‘good’ and ‘bad’.&lt;/em&gt; – An improvement is invented only by someone who is able to feel ‘this is not good’.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>244</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/244/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/244/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thoughts and words.&lt;/em&gt; – Even one’s thoughts one cannot entirely reproduce in words.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>245</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/245/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/245/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Praise by choice.&lt;/em&gt; – The artist chooses his subjects; that is his way of praising.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>246</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/246/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/246/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mathematics.&lt;/em&gt; – Let us introduce the subtlety and rigour of mathematics into all sciences to the extent to which that is at all possible; not in the belief that we will come to know things this way, but in order to &lt;em&gt;ascertain&lt;/em&gt; our human relation to things. Mathematics is only the means to general and final knowledge of humanity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>247</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/247/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/247/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Habit.&lt;/em&gt; – Every habit makes our hand more witty and our wit less handy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>248</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/248/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/248/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Books.&lt;/em&gt; – What good is a book that does not even carry us beyond all books?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>249</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/249/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/249/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sigh of the one who comes to know.&lt;/em&gt; – ‘Oh, my greed! In this soul there dwells no selflessness but rather an all-desiring self that would like, as it were, to see with the eyes and seize with the hands of many individuals – a self that would like to bring back the entire past, that wants to lose nothing it could possibly possess! Oh, this flame of my greed! Oh, that I might be reborn into a hundred beings!’ – Whoever does not know this sigh from experience does not know the passion of coming to know.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>250</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/250/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/250/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Guilt.&lt;/em&gt; – Although the shrewdest judges of the witches and even the witches themselves were convinced of the guilt of witchcraft, this guilt still did not exist. This is true of all guilt.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>251</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/251/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/251/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Misunderstood sufferers.&lt;/em&gt; – Great natures suffer differently from what their admirers imagine: they suffer most severely from the ignoble, petty agitations of some evil moments – in short, from their doubts about their own greatness – and not from the sacrifices and martyrdoms that their task demands from them. As long as Prometheus has pity for men and sacrifices himself for them, he is happy and great; but when he is envious of Zeus and the homage paid to him by mortals, then he suffers!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>252</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/252/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/252/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Better in debt.&lt;/em&gt; – ‘Better to remain in debt than to pay with a coin that does not bear our image!’ says our sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>253</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/253/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/253/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Always at home.&lt;/em&gt; – One day we reach our goal – and now we point with pride to the long journeys we took to reach it. In truth we did not notice we were travelling. But we got so far because at each point we believed we were &lt;em&gt;at home.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>254</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/254/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/254/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Against embarrassment.&lt;/em&gt; – Whoever is always deeply occupied is beyond all embarrassment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>255</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/255/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/255/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Imitators.&lt;/em&gt; – A: ‘What? You want no imitators?’ B: ‘I don’t want people to imitate me; I want everyone to set his own example, which is what &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; do.’ A: ‘So –?’&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>256</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/256/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/256/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Skinnedness.&lt;/em&gt; – All people of depth find happiness in being for once like flying fish, playing on the outermost crests of waves; what they consider best in things is that they have a surface: their skinnedness – &lt;em&gt;sit venia verbo&lt;/em&gt;.38&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>257</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/257/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/257/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;From experience.&lt;/em&gt; – Some do not know how rich they are until they experience what kinds of rich people will steal from them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>258</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/258/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/258/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Those who deny chance.&lt;/em&gt; – No victor believes in chance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>259</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/259/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/259/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;From paradise.&lt;/em&gt; – ‘Good and evil are the prejudices of God’ – said the snake.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>260</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/260/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/260/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;One times one.&lt;/em&gt; – One is always wrong; but with two, truth begins. – One cannot prove his case, but two are already irrefutable.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>261</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/261/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/261/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originality.&lt;/em&gt; – What is originality? To &lt;em&gt;see&lt;/em&gt; something that still has no name; that still cannot be named even though it is lying right before everyone’s eyes. The way people usually are, it takes a name to make something visible at all. – Those with originality have usually been the name-givers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>262</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/262/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/262/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sub specie aeterni.39&lt;/em&gt; – A: ‘You are moving ever faster from the living: soon they will strike you out of their lists!’ – B: ‘That is the only way to participate in the privilege of the dead.’ – A: ‘What privilege?’ – B: ‘No longer to die.’&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>263</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/263/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/263/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Without vanity.&lt;/em&gt; – When we are in love we want our defects to remain hidden – not from vanity but so the loved one won’t suffer. Yes, the lover would like to be godlike – also not from vanity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>264</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/264/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/264/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What we do.&lt;/em&gt; – What we do is never understood but always merely praised and reproached.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>265</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/265/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/265/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ultimate doubt.&lt;/em&gt; – What, then, are man’s truths ultimately? – They are the &lt;em&gt;irrefutable&lt;/em&gt; errors of man.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>266</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/266/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/266/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Where cruelty is needed.&lt;/em&gt; – He who has greatness is cruel to his virtues and secondary considerations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>267</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/267/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/267/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;With a great goal.&lt;/em&gt; – With a great goal one is superior even to justice, not only to one’s deeds and judges.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>268</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/268/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/268/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What makes one heroic?&lt;/em&gt; – To approach at the same time one’s highest suffering and one’s highest hope.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>269</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/269/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/269/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What do you believe in?&lt;/em&gt; – In this: that the weight of all things must be determined anew.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>270</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/270/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/270/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What does your conscience say?&lt;/em&gt; – ‘You should become who you are.’40&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>271</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/271/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/271/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Where lie your greatest dangers? – &lt;em&gt;In compassion.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>272</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/272/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/272/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What do you love in others? – &lt;em&gt;My hopes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>273</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/273/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/273/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Whom do you call bad?&lt;/em&gt; – He who always wants to put people to shame.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>274</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/274/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/274/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What is most human to you? – &lt;em&gt;To spare someone shame.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>275</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/275/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/3_Book_Three/275/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What is the seal of having become free’? – &lt;em&gt;No longer to be ashamed before oneself.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1 Group of philosophers in the early fifth century BC who argued that the world of change was a mere appearance of an underlying unchanging being&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2 The German word ‘Recht’ is usually ambiguous, meaning both ‘right’ and ‘law’. In this case it seems best to render it as ‘justice’.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3 Ariston lived in the third century BC. This is fragment number 359 in &lt;em&gt;Stoicorum veterum fragmenta,&lt;/em&gt; ed. von Arnim.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
