<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;अतीन्द्रियः on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/atIndriyaH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;अतीन्द्रियः on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/atIndriyaH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Doctor and Dakini</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/atIndriyaH/doctor_and_dAkinI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/atIndriyaH/doctor_and_dAkinI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: Ateendriyo on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The new doctor woke up with a start and looked outside his window to see the fog covered mountains. Arun had not even spent a few months sitting back in Dehradun when he had been posted to Joshimath district. He had recently joined the state medical services, and despite his parent&amp;rsquo;s remonstrations, he had wanted to serve in the state far flung, rural areas. The state health services had only just launched a small scheme, where doctors could serve for short periods in difficult to reach areas, adn then return to their private practices.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Doctor in the crevass</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/atIndriyaH/doctor_in_crevass/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/atIndriyaH/doctor_in_crevass/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://threads-web.vercel.app/threads/1374375474638430209&#34;&gt;https://threads-web.vercel.app/threads/1374375474638430209&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Want to hear a ghost story? Let me tell you one! I feel safe telling these only on a Tuesday. Story has been received from a friend, who heard it from a medical officer in some military or Paramilitary battalion or refinement.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There was this Medical Officer, who was posted to glacier region. It was one of those snowy, dark, cold nights, and the Doctor Saab (as army and Paramilitary forces call their medical officers), was sitting in his tent. This Doctor saab was the son of some big shot bureaucrat, and arrogant to boot. Competent, compassionate towards patients, and all. But, arrogant, and with a hair trigger temper. That night, doctor Saab was angry. Really, truly angry. He had called up his commander who had slightly berated him. Mind you, this chap wasn&amp;rsquo;t used to listening to any crap from anyone. Listening to some khaalis 100% &amp;ldquo;daant&amp;rdquo; from someone, that too Some non medico! Huh!! Our doctor Saab was pissed, and his anger was about as high as the altitude where he was at. Why was he getting this daant? Well, the commander had wanted to know why doctor Saab was still at the post where he was.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
