<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Cricket on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/MT/cricket/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Cricket on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2005 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/MT/cricket/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The sub-continental stirrings</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/MT/cricket/2005-12-18_the-sub-continental-stirrings/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/MT/cricket/2005-12-18_the-sub-continental-stirrings/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/12/18/the-sub-continental-stirrings/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We had earlier commented how the Trojan horse, whom we used to call Chappal (slipper) in our days of youth was working his wonders with the Indian army. We had speculated that he was specifically an agent of the roguish pirate chief Ponting to do away with his main dangers before the invasion of the subcontinent. We have now got some intelligence as to how the Indian ants invited the parasitoid wasp Greg “Chappal” into their nest. The lazy king of Vanga, seeing his Kiwi mercenary returning to his own country, decided to get Chappal thinking he was an ally of his. A little did he know of the mission Ponting had primed Chappal for. In the mean time with the actual battle performance of the Vanga champion being less than desirable, and the veteran Prince of Bombay being side-lined due to the blows he had received from cannon shards in the thick of battle, the prince of the Karnata country decided to stage a coup de tat with his supporters. Pulling around him a bunch of adventurers such as the Bundela, the Mohammedan Kaif, the viShama Gambhira and others he got over the Trojan plant Chappal to his side. Then he used Chappal to seize the throne by ousting the Vanga warrior and also trying to threaten the Vanga’s supporters like the Sikh turbanator and the Andhra chieftain from Vangipura. As result the whole Indian army has been stirred and the atmosphere of fear has been reinstated to possibly trigger a decline in performance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Trojan horse?</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/MT/cricket/2005-11-12_the-trojan-horse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/MT/cricket/2005-11-12_the-trojan-horse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/11/12/the-trojan-horse/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;With the fall of general Wright, the Hindu armies employed a new trainer in the form of the roguish chief from Southern Saxony, Chappell. we have long known Chappell to be an abrasive character, who has always had his own quirks. He quickly got into a conflict with the prince of Vanga and the brave Andhra grenadier from Vangipura. We believe that the Anglo-Saxon is a Trojan horse sent by the king of the Southern Whites to ruin the Hindu armies. We suspect that he might be a plant to spoil the Hindu performance by his policies of targeted disruption and deletion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The clash of Saxons</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/MT/cricket/2005-08-28_the-clash-of-saxons/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Aug 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/MT/cricket/2005-08-28_the-clash-of-saxons/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/08/28/the-clash-of-saxons/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The great leader of the Southern Saxon, Pirate king Slit-Eyes had died in the battle with the Hindus during their invasion of the southern continent. Slit-Eyes was succeeded by pirate Ponting, who was ably supported by the old guard of the Slit-Eyes empire, such as Gen. Hayden, bombardier McGrath, raider-in-chief Warnie, captains Langer and Gilchrist, Bishop Martyn and other saboteurs, Clarke, Gillespie and Lee. The Southern Saxons in the heydays of Slit-Eyes and Pirate Emperor Border, had engaged in many raiding operations on the Saxon mainland, and had fought many epic battle even as the pirates of the Caribbeans. Warnie in particular had enriched himself on most of these raids with rich harvests of women and jewels and in the process led the pirates to many victories against the Mainland Saxons. The great pirates now embarked on a new expedition to mainland Saxony with a large force of fusiliers and bombardiers on their well made vessels. The Mainland Saxons recalling their own pirate Francis Drake decided to launch themselves into a spirited defence of their land. In the recent past, in a move to restore the pristine Leukospheric composition of their army, they did away with their earstwhile leader, the wily but unsuccessful Sultan Nasser Husseyn. He was replaced by the phelgmatic King Vaughan, master of all Saxony. He was ably aided by pirate Flintoff, who was believed to be a successor of bootlegger Botham in the heydays of Mainland Saxony.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The mother of all battles</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/MT/cricket/2003-12-16_the-mother-of-all-battles/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/MT/cricket/2003-12-16_the-mother-of-all-battles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2003/12/16/the-mother-of-all-battles/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The ruffians of Southern Saxony had always held the Indian armies in contempt. In one of the greatest battles of all times the princes of the Andhra and the Karnata country had destroyed the Saxon pride that had swelled in the great invasion of India in the year of 2001 under Emperor of all Saxony, Slit-Eyes+++(=nAsser Hussain?)+++. In the battle of Chennai the prince of Mumbai had put to sword the Southern Saxon army. Then there had been the African raids where the power of Saxony had demolished the Hindus in the final skirmish. That was followed by skirmishes in India where the Saxons had prevailed again.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
