<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Somewhere a band on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Somewhere a band on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was a desert prairie filled with wind and sun and sagebrush and a silence that grew sweetly up in wildflowers. There was a rail track laid across this silence and now the rail track shuddered.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Soon a dark train charged out of the east with fire and steam and thundered through the station. On its way it slowed at a platform littered with confetti, the tatters of ancient tickets punched by transient conductors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Because.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In his half-sleep last night he had felt something writing on the insides of his eyelids.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Without opening his eyes he read the words as they scrolled:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Somewhere a band is playing,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Playing the strangest tunes,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Of sunflower seeds and sailors&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Somewhere a drummer simmers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;And trembles with times forlorn,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Remembering days of summer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In futures yet unborn.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Hold on,” he heard himself say.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He opened his eyes and the writing stopped.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Because.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Well, now, he thought, as he peered down the tracks. This place isn’t on the map. But when the train slowed, I jumped, because …&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He turned and saw a wind-battered sign over the flimsy station that seemed about to sink under tides of sand: SUMMERTON, ARIZONA.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Yes, sir,” said a voice.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The traveler dropped his gaze to find a man of some middle years with fair hair and clear eyes seated on the porch of the ramshackle station, leaning back in shadow. An assortment of hats hung above him, which read: TICKET SELLER, BAGGAGE MASTER, SWITCHMAN, NIGHT WATCHMAN, TAXI. Upon his head was a cap with the word STATIONMASTER stitched on its bill in bright red thread.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The air was hot as the bakery wagon moved and then, as they reached the shadows of trees, the air began to cool.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The young man leaned forward.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“How did you guess?”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“What?” said the driver.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“That I’m a writer,” said the young man.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The taxi driver glanced at the passing trees and nodded.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Your tongue improves your words on their way out. Keep talking.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“I’ve heard rumors about Summerton.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At which moment an old-fashioned ice wagon with a full dark cavern mouth of frost entered the yard, led by a horse in dire need of his Antarctic cargo. Cardiff could taste the ice, from thirty summers long gone.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Just in time,” said the iceman. “Hot day. Go grab.” He nodded toward the rear of his wagon.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Cardiff, on pure instinct, jumped down from the bread wagon and went straight to the back of the ice wagon, and felt his ten-year-old hand reach in and grab a sharp icicle. He stepped back and rubbed it on his brow. His other hand instinctively took a handkerchief from his pocket to wrap the ice. Sucking it, he moved away.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;James Cardiff stood in quiet amazement.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The front porch of the Egyptian View Arms was the longest he had ever seen. It had so many white wicker rockers he stopped counting. Occupying some of the rockers was an assortment of youngish not quite middle-aged gentlemen, nattily dressed, with slicked-back hair, fresh out of the shower. And interspersed among the men were late-thirties-not-yet-forty women in summer dresses looking as if they had all been cut from the same rose or orchid or gardenia wallpaper. The men had haircuts each sheared by the same barber. The women wore their tresses like bright helmets designed by some Parisian, ironed and curlicued long before Cardiff had been born. And the assembly of rockers all tilted forward and then back, in unison, in a quiet surf, as if the same ocean breeze moved them all, soundless and serene.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Inside the dim hall, Cardiff felt as if he had moved into a summer-cool milk shed that smelled of large canisters of cream hidden away from the sun, and iceboxes dripping their secret liquors, and bread laid out fresh on kitchen tables, and pies cooling on windowsills.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Cardiff took another step and knew he would sleep nine hours a night here and wake like a boy at dawn, excited that he was alive, and all the world beginning, morn after morn, glad for his heart in his body, and his pulse in his wrists.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The dining room, like the porch, was the longest one he’d ever seen.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All of the summer porch people were lined up on either side of an incredible table, staring at Cardiff and Nef as they came through the door.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At the far end were two chairs waiting for them and as soon as Cardiff and Nef sat, there was a flurry of activity as utensils were raised and platters passed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When he looked up, Nef’s chair was empty. The other diners, too, had all left the table, gone back to their rocking chairs or, perhaps, to summer afternoon naps.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Lord,” he murmured. “That woman, young, but how young? Old, but how old?”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Suddenly Elias Culpepper touched his elbow.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“You want a real tour of our town? Claude needs to deliver some more fresh-baked bread. On your feet!”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The wagon was loaded with a redolent harvest. The warm loaves had been neatly stacked row on row within the oven-smelling wagon, thirty or forty loaves in all, with names lettered on the wax-paper wrappings. Beside these were waxed boxes of muffins and cakes, carefully tied with string.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Claude jogged at a goodly pace for two blocks and turned sweetly to the right.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;His eyes twitched toward a front yard mailbox: &lt;em&gt;Abercrombie.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Cardiff checked his list.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abercrombie!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Damn!”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He jumped from the wagon, loaf in hand, when a woman’s voice called, “Thank you, Claude.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A woman of some forty years stood at the gate to take the bread. “You, too, of course,” she said. “Mister … ?”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Cardiff, ma’m.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mr. Culpepper did not immediately respond.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For dead ahead there was afternoon high tea, with apricot and peach tarts and strawberry delight and coffee instead of tea and then port instead of coffee and then there was dinner, a real humdinger, that lasted until well after nine and then the inhabitants of the Egyptian View Arms headed up, one by one, to their most welcome cool summer night beds, and Cardiff sat out on the croquetless and hoopless lawn, watching Mr. Culpepper on the porch, smoking several small bonfire pipes, waiting.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“I … ,” said Cardiff.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Enough,” Culpepper interrupted. “For tonight.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He held out another glass of bright amber wine. Cardiff drank. When he looked up, the front screen door of the Egyptian View Arms tapped shut. Someone went upstairs. His ambiance stayed.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Cardiff refilled his glass.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Never coming home. Never ever,” he whispered.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And went up to bed.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sleep well, someone said somewhere in the house. But he could not sleep. He lay, fully dressed, doing philosophical sums on the ceiling, erasing, adding, erasing again until he sat up abruptly and looked out across the meadow town of thousands of flowers in the midst of which houses rose and sank only to rise again, ships on a summer sea.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;He awoke to the sun pouring in through the high attic window. Questions gathered behind his tongue.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Beside him, the bed was empty.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Gone.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Afraid of the truth?&lt;/em&gt; he wondered.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;No,&lt;/em&gt; he thought, &lt;em&gt;she will have left a note on the icebox door.&lt;/em&gt; Somehow he knew. &lt;em&gt;Go look.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The note was there.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mr. Cardiff:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Many tourists arriving. I must welcome them. Questions at breakfast.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nef.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Far off, wasn’t there the merest wail of a locomotive whistle, the softest churn of some great engine?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Nef was not at breakfast, or lunch, or dinner.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He went to bed hungry.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At midnight the wind blew softly in the window, whispering the curtains, shadowing the moonlight.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There, far across town, lay the cemetery, immense white teeth scattered on a meadow of fresh moon-silvered grass.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Four dozen stones dead, but not dead.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All lies,&lt;/em&gt; he thought.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And found himself halfway down the boarding house stairs, surrounded by the exhalations of sleeping people. There was no sound save the drip of the ice pan under the icebox in the moonlit kitchen. The house brimmed with lemon and lilac illumination from the candied windows over the front entrance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;They were smoking fine cigars and drinking nameless wine in the middle of the night. Cardiff leaned back in his wicker chair, eyes tight shut.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“You been noticing things?” inquired Elias Culpepper.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“A baker’s dozen. When Claude took me on the bread and muffin tour I couldn’t help but notice there are no signs—anywhere—for doctors. Not one funeral parlor that I could see.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Must be somewhere,” said Culpepper.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“How come not in the phone book yellow pages? No doctors, no surgeons, no mortuary offices.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Elias Culpepper leaned forward to scan Cardiff’s notepad.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“You got any more doubts, indecisions, or opinions?”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Cardiff mused over his notes. “There don’t seem to be any roaring businesses in Summerton.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“A few mice but no buffalo.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“No travel agencies, just a train station about to sink in the dust. Main road is mostly potholes. No one seems to leave, and very few arrive. How in Hades do you all survive?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Again, the large bed was a bank of snow on a warm summer night. She lay on one side, looking up at the ceiling, and did not move. He sat on the far edge, saying nothing, and at last tilted over and lay his head on the pillow, and waited.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Finally Nef said, “It seems to me you’ve spent a lot of time in the town graveyard since you arrived. Looking for what?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>19</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sometime during the night, he sensed that he was once more alone.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He woke in a panic, at dawn, thinking, &lt;em&gt;I’ve missed the train. It’s come and gone. But, no—&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He heard the locomotive whistle shrieking across the sky, moaning like a funeral train as the sun rose over desert sands.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Did he or did he not hear a bag, similar to his own, catapult from a not-stopping train to bang the station platform?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>20</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/20/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/20/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;They stood on the platform of the empty station, Cardiff at one end, the tall man at the other.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“James Edward McCoy?” Cardiff said.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Cardiff,” said McCoy, “is that you?”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Both smiled false smiles.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“What are you doing here?” said Cardiff.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“You might have known I would follow,” said James Edward McCoy. “When you left town, I knew someone had died, and you’d gone to give him a proper burial. So I packed my bag.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/21/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“This is gonna be great,” said James Edward McCoy. “I can see it now: my byline on stories about how Summerton, Arizona, hit the rocks and sank. Johnstown flood stand aside. San Francisco earthquake, forget it. I’ll expose how the government destroyed the innocents and plowed their front lawns with salt. First the &lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt;, then papers in London, Paris, Moscow, even Canada. News junkies love to read about others’ misery—here’s an entire town being strangled to death by government greed. And I’m going to tell the world.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>22</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/22/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cardiff led McCoy into the vast yard of motionless stones and flightless angels. McCoy peered at the markers.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Damn. There’s plenty of names, but no dates. When did they die?”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“They didn’t,” Cardiff said softly.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Good God, lemme look closer.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;McCoy took six steps west, four steps east, and came to …&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The open grave with a coffin gaping wide, and a spade tossed to one side.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“What’s this? Funeral today?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>23</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/23/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/23/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I have committed murder,&lt;/em&gt; Cardiff thought.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;No, no. McCoy buried himself. Slipped, fell, and shut the lid.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Cardiff walked almost backward down the middle of the street, unable to tear his gaze from the graveyard, as if expecting McCoy to appear, risen like Lazarus.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When he came to the Egyptian View Arms, he staggered up the walk and into the house, took a deep breath, and found his way to the kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>24</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/24/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;They were passing the graveyard.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I have committed murder,&lt;/em&gt; Cardiff thought.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And, impulsively, he cried, “Claude!”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Claude froze and Cardiff jumped out of the wagon and rushed into the graveyard.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Swaying over the grave, he reached down in a terrible panic to lift the lid.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;McCoy was there, not dead but sleeping, having given up, and was now taking a snooze.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Exhaling, Cardiff spoke down at his terrible enemy, glad that he was alive.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>25</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/25/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The picnic was spread waiting on the back lawn of the EGYPTIAN VIEW ARMS.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Speech!” someone called.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“I don’t know how to begin,” Cardiff said.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“At the beginning!” There was a gentle laughter.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Cardiff took a deep breath and plunged in.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“As you may know, the State Department of Highways has been measuring string from Phoenix east and north and from Gallup north and west. The exact measurements of a new freeway will touch latitude 89 eighty miles west of longitude 40.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>26</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/26/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/26/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My God,&lt;/em&gt; Cardiff thought, &lt;em&gt;even the sunflowers have turned away.&lt;/em&gt; He could not see their faces, but he was certain they fixed him with a fiery stare.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“I’m empty,” he said at last. “I’ve told all my secrets. Now, Nef, you must give me yours.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Well,” she said, and began to take sandwiches out of a hamper, to cut bread and butter it and offer it to him as she spoke.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>27</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/27/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/27/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“And now,” said Nef.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Now?” said Cardiff.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“I must prove that I do not wish to kill the bearer of bad news. Come.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And she led him across the lawn where the picnic blankets still lay as after a storm, tossed and half-furled, and some few dogs had arrived with the army ants while several cats waited for the beasts to leave, and Nef walked among them and opened the front door of the Egyptian View Arms and, ducking his head, blushing, Cardiff stepped in swiftly, but she was already at the stairs and halfway up before he touched the first riser, and then they were in her tower room and he looked and saw that her vast bed had been stripped and the windows thrown open wide with their wind-tossed curtains and the town clock was striking four in the afternoon as Nef lifted her arms and a great soft bloom of sheet rose in a summer cloud over the bed and he seized his half and with her gentled it down in a field of white over the bed to cover its face. And they stood back and watched the late afternoon exhale and fill the lace and blow the curtains inward toward the bed, like a fall of never-arriving snow, and there was a glass of lemonade on either bedside table, and his questioning look caused her to laugh and shake her head. Only lemonade, nothing more.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>28</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/28/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/28/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;He slept and he dreamed.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He was on the train, going east, and then suddenly he was in Chicago, and even more suddenly, he was in front of the Art Institute and was going up the stairs and through the corridors to stand before the great &lt;em&gt;Sunday in the Park&lt;/em&gt; painting.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A woman was standing by the painting and she turned and it was his fiancée.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As he watched, she grew older, aging before his eyes, and she said to him, “You’ve changed.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>29</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/29/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/29/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;He sat for a long while listening to the wind howl in the chimney and the rain funnels outside.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The old house creaked down into a deep swell of night then backed up and over, out of sight of land and light.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Rats practiced graffiti on the walls and spiders played harps so high that only the hairs inside his ears heard and quivered.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How much loss, how much gain?&lt;/em&gt; he wondered. &lt;em&gt;How much leave, and how much remain?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>30</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/30/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/30/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At the train station, there were sunflowers out on the track. Someone had been there ahead of him and if it was Elias Culpepper, he never knew.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The train stopped this time, and he got on and as he bought a ticket from the conductor he asked, “Do you remember me?”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The man looked at his face intently, scowled, and looked again and said, “Can’t say I do.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And the train gathered steam and chugged away from the station and Summerton, Arizona, was left behind.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>31</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/31/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/31/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The train flew across flat corn lands, over the horizon, by the lake and to the great turbulent city next to the lake, and he was running up the steps of the museum and walking among paintings to sit before the endlessly intriguing Seurat, where the Sunday strollers stood still in an eternal park.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now beside him sat Laura, glancing back and forth from the green park to him, stunned and questioning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>32</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/32/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/32/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The train came out of the east and without thinking of time or place, glided slowly past a spot that was marked only by dust, wind, cacti, a scatter of leaves, and a profusion of ticket-punch confetti that celebrated on the air and settled when the train was gone.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, a familiar suitcase skidded to a halt on the remains of a ramshackle station platform, a few surfboards on a tide of sand, followed by a man in a wrinkled summer suit who tumbled out like an acrobat, shouting with pride when he landed, swaying but intact.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>33</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/33/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/bradbury-ray/somewhere_a_band/33/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It was twilight when he reached the first row of orange trees.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It was deepening twilight when he saw the familiar crowds of sunflowers in each yard and the sign, EGYPTIAN VIEW ARMS, swaying above the verandah.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The sun was almost gone as he walked up the last sidewalk, mounted the porch steps, stood before the screen door, and pressed the doorbell. It chimed quietly. A slender shadow appeared on the hall stair.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
