<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Misc on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/misc/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Misc on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/misc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Ashish_to_Adil</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/misc/Ashish_to_Adil/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/misc/Ashish_to_Adil/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/GoldDusters/status/1656377780202864641&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Men are targets of Love J_had as much as women are! A colleague’s younger brother worked in fashion industry. Let’s call him Ashish. He worked with a European brand making denim. There he met a young woman- let’s call her Shaheen.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Shaheen came across as liberal Mz. Loved Gujarati food which Ashish’s baa sent for him. Slowly she found place in his circle. They were seen together. The family was not conservative &amp;amp; thought this was merely a casual liking, they were sure Ashish would not go beyond friendship.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On rAmakRShNa&#39;s &#39;tantra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/misc/on_rAmakRShNa-tantra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/misc/on_rAmakRShNa-tantra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;http://srisaradamath.org/publication/samvit/202103.pdf&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Understanding Sadhana through the Life of Sri Ramakrishna: The Experience of God Realization through Tantric Sadhana — IV&lt;br&gt;&#xA;PRAVRAJIKA VIVEKAPRANA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sri Ramakrishna had moved on to the level of Vishishtha Advaita, where he got a little bit of help from gurus. The first guru was Bhairavi Brahmani.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sri Ramakrishna, by his own desire to realize the various forms of God, practised the well-known ways of reaching out to the realization of God. But because of the physical and mental symptoms that he developed everyone around him thought that he had gone mad. And therefore there was great anguish in the hearts of those who knew him and loved him, to cure him. They were trying to find out remedies to get him out of his “God madness”. This phenomenon also was not unknown in India. &amp;hellip; Bhairavi Brahmani tried to convince him that he was not suffering from any disease. But because others would not believe this, he would cry and keep running to the Mother and ask her why she was putting him through this.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RamaNa quotes</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/misc/ramaNa-quotes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/misc/ramaNa-quotes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Quotes by a neighbor venkaTarAman ramaNan&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;31/05/16, 9:48 pm : It&amp;rsquo;s an interesting fact that the lightest element air has the potential to lift a 500&#xA;tonne aircraft when propelled, in life too our true potential is revealed maybe when our drive propels us.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;31/05/16, 9:49 pm : The word success doesn&amp;rsquo;t having a precise definition but a classic example of&#xA;&amp;ldquo;relative&amp;rdquo; it&amp;rsquo;s just a case of comparative judgement .&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;01/06/16, 7:30 am : Conviction and commitment defines the personality and character and judgement&#xA;defines one&amp;rsquo;s individuality .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RNAnubandha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/misc/RNAnubandha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/misc/RNAnubandha/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AlokJagawat/status/1787720576208957850&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Consequences of bad karma, real life example of account balance, the reasons for accepting the kārmika backfire. Ṛṇānubandhana in jyotiśa, how it works&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;abduction&#34;&gt;Abduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In 2009, my cousin who was a senior gynaecologist was attending my wife. My wife delivered a healthy girl over 4 kg. However, the paediatrician over there just told us that my child is suffering from acute pneumonia and she needs to be operated immediately (There was no symptoms and my sister countered him but she cannot to do anything as he was the paediatrician). Before I could do anything, he called an ambulance from a five-star “hotel” and before we could say anything my daughter was literally abducted. My sister and me followed the ambulance to the hotel.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sikh hindu muslim marriage</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/misc/sikh-hindu-muslim-marriage/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/misc/sikh-hindu-muslim-marriage/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;I think I am the most appropriate women to answer this as I am a Sikh women married to a Muslim man for last 28 yrs in the state of Madhya Pradesh. We got married in year 1990. For understandable reasons you can excuse me for not coming up with my real name as being a mother of one daughter and son at this age I would like to keep my identity intact. But I have to tell my story and I think this is the most appropriate forum to make my views public.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We are two sisters only and younger one is married to a Hindu man, it all started from me as I did my thing of marrying my ‘love’ hence it became difficult for parents to say no to my younger sister for another inter-faith marriage as she too went ahead with marrying her love.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>svembu-child-autism</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/misc/svembu-child-autism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/misc/svembu-child-autism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/svembu/status/1635538115854041091&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;autism-fight&#34;&gt;Autism fight&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;With vicious personal attacks and slander on my character, it is time for me to respond. This is a deeply painful personal thread. My personal life, in contrast to my business life, has been a long tragedy. Autism destroyed our lives and left me suicidally depressed.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My wife Pramila and I were in this fight against autism for over 15 years. She is a super mom and her passionate cause is curing our son of autism. I worked hard along with her. To ensure his safety, I also took some of his treatments so I could know what they did to him.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>To be indian</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/misc/to_be_indian/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/misc/to_be_indian/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://ritambhara.org.in/paper/what-is-indian/&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**Exploring what is Indian? **&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A parable and a discussion&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;By Raghu Ananthanarayanan and K.S. Narendran *&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-parable&#34;&gt;The parable&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;विस्तारः (द्रष्टुं नोद्यम्)&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(At the outset I must seek the indulgence of the reader. I have quoted the Indian words in brackets at important points since they have a nuance that is lost in translation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;May be some readers who are familiar with the language will appreciate the nuances)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A young woman had committed suicide. She was the daughter of a respected village elder. It was an open secret that this girl was in love with a boy who belonged to a lower caste, but who was educated and lived in the ‘city’. He held a good job.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vinay community consciousness</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/misc/vinay-community-consciousness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/hindu/misc/vinay-community-consciousness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A story&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;on&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Community&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Consciousness&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A f i c t i o n s t o r y b a s e d on f a c t s Version-1.0 (alpha)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Paripoornam 🌕🪷☀- A Self Sustainable Community in India based on Natural Living, Natural Farming, Mud homes &amp;amp; Natural Learning. Authentic Alternative School with academics mapped to real world life skills and activities, and health giving education because teachers inner work is such that healing and therapy is part of the curriculum. *Inspired by Waldorf, Gurukulam, J Krishnamurthy and Open Learning. We are 10 families now.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
