<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;01 Book One on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;01 Book One on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The teachers of the purpose of existence.&lt;/em&gt; – Whether I regard human beings with a good or with an evil eye, I always find them engaged in a single task, each and every one of them: to do what benefits the preservation of the human race. Not from a feeling of love for the race, but simply because within them nothing is older, stronger, more inexorable and invincible than this instinct – because this instinct constitutes &lt;em&gt;the essence&lt;/em&gt; of our species and herd. One might quickly enough, with the usual myopia from five steps away, divide one’s neighbours into useful and harmful, good and evil; but on a large-scale assessment, upon further reflection on the whole, one grows suspicious of this tidying and separating and finally abandons it. Even the most harmful person may actually be the most useful when it comes to the preservation of the species; for he nurtures in himself or through his effects on others drives without which humanity would long since have become feeble or rotten. Hatred, delight in the misfortunes of others, the lust to rob and rule, and whatever else is called evil: all belong to the amazing economy of the preservation of the species, an economy which is certainly costly, wasteful, and on the whole most foolish – but still &lt;em&gt;proven&lt;/em&gt; to have preserved our race so far. I no longer know whether you, my dear fellow man and neighbour, are even &lt;em&gt;capable&lt;/em&gt; of living in a way which is damaging to the species, i.e. ‘unreasonably’ and ‘badly’. What &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; have harmed the species may have become extinct many thousands of years ago and may by now belong to the things that are no longer possible even for God. Pursue your best or your worst desires, and above all, perish! In both cases you are probably still in some way a promoter and benefactor of humanity and are thus entitled to your eulogists – as well as to your mockers! But you will never find someone who could completely mock you, the individual, even in your best qualities, someone who could bring home to you as far as truth allows your boundless, fly- and frog-like wretchedness! To laugh at oneself as one would have to laugh in order to laugh &lt;em&gt;from the whole truth&lt;/em&gt; – for that, not even the best have had enough sense of truth, and the most gifted have had far too little genius! Perhaps even laughter still has a future – when the proposition ‘The species is everything, an individual is always nothing’ has become part of humanity and this ultimate liberation and irresponsibility is accessible to everyone at all times. Perhaps laughter will then have formed an alliance with wisdom; perhaps only ‘gay science’ will remain. At present, things are still quite different; at present, the comedy of existence has not yet ‘become conscious’ of itself; at present, we still live in the age of tragedy, in the age of moralities and religions. What is the meaning of the ever-new appearance of these founders of moralities and religions, of these instigators of fights about moral valuations, these teachers of pangs of conscience and religious wars? What is the meaning of these heroes on this stage? For these have been the heroes thus far; and everything else, even if at times it was all that we could see and was far too near, has always served only to set the stage for these heroes, whether as machinery and backdrop or in the role of confidant and servant. (The poets, for example, were always the servants of some kind of morality.) It is obvious that these tragedies, too, work in the interest of the &lt;em&gt;species,&lt;/em&gt; even if they should believe that they are working in the interest of God, as God’s emissaries. They, too, promote the life of the species &lt;em&gt;by promoting the faith in life.&lt;/em&gt; ‘Life is worth living’, each of them shouts, ‘there is something to life, there is something behind life, beneath it; beware!’ This drive, which rules the highest as well as the basest of human beings – the drive for the preservation of the species – erupts from time to time as reason and passion of mind; it is then surrounded by a resplendent retinue of reasons and tries with all its might to make us forget that fundamentally it is drive, instinct, stupidity, lack of reasons. Life &lt;em&gt;ought to&lt;/em&gt; be loved, &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; –! Man &lt;em&gt;ought to&lt;/em&gt; advance himself and his neighbour, &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; –! What names all these Oughts and Becauses have been given and may yet be given in the future! The ethical teacher makes his appearance as the teacher of the purpose of existence in order that what happens necessarily and always, by itself and without a purpose, shall henceforth seem to be done for a purpose and strike man as reason and an ultimate commandment; to this end he invents a second, different existence and takes by means of his new mechanics the old, ordinary existence off its old, ordinary hinges. To be sure, in no way does he want us to &lt;em&gt;laugh&lt;/em&gt; at existence, or at ourselves – or at him; for him, an individual is always an individual, something first and last and tremendous; for him there are no species, sums, or zeroes. Foolish and fanciful as his inventions and valuations may be, badly as he may misjudge the course of nature and deny its conditions – and all ethical systems hitherto have been so foolish and contrary to nature that humanity would have perished from every one had it gained power over humanity – all the same! Every time ‘the hero’ appeared on stage, something new was attained: the gruesome counterpart of laughter, that profound shock that many individuals feel at the thought: ‘Yes, living is worth it! Yes, I am worthy of living!’ Life and I and you and all of us became &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt; to ourselves once again for a while. There is no denying that &lt;em&gt;in the long run&lt;/em&gt; each of these great teachers of a purpose was vanquished by laughter, reason and nature: the brief tragedy always changed and returned into the eternal comedy of existence, and the ‘waves of uncountable laughter’ – to cite Aeschylus1 – must in the end also come crashing down on the greatest of these tragedians. Despite all this corrective laughter, human nature on the whole has surely been altered by the recurring emergence of such teachers of the purpose of existence – &lt;em&gt;it has acquired one additional need,&lt;/em&gt; the need for the repeated appearance of such teachers and such teachings of a ‘purpose’. Man has gradually become a fantastic animal that must fulfil one condition of existence more than any other animal: man &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; from time to time believe he knows &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; he exists; his race cannot thrive without a periodic trust in life – without faith in the &lt;em&gt;reason in life!&lt;/em&gt; And ever again the human race will from time to time decree: ‘There is something one is absolutely forbidden henceforth to laugh at.’ And the most cautious friend of man will add: ‘Not only laughter and gay wisdom but also the tragic, with all its sublime unreason, belongs to the means and necessities of the preservation of the species.’ And therefore! Therefore! Therefore! Oh, do you understand me, my brothers? Do you understand this new law of ebb and flood? We, too, have our time!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Intellectual conscience.&lt;/em&gt; – I keep having the same experience and keep resisting it anew each time; I do not want to believe it although I can grasp it as with my hands: &lt;em&gt;the great majority lacks an intellectual conscience&lt;/em&gt; – indeed, it has often seemed to me as if someone requiring such a conscience would be as lonely in the most densely populated cities as he would be in the desert. Everyone looks at you with strange eyes and goes on handling their scales, calling this good and that evil; nobody as much as blushes when you notice that their weights are underweight – nor do they become indignant with you; perhaps they laugh at your doubts. I mean: &lt;em&gt;to the great majority&lt;/em&gt; it is not contemptible to believe this or that and to live accordingly &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; first becoming aware of the final and most certain reasons pro and con, and without even troubling themselves about such reasons afterwards: the most gifted men and the noblest women still belong to this ‘great majority’. But what are goodheartedness, refinement, and genius to me when the person possessing these virtues tolerates slack feelings in his believing and judging and when he does not consider &lt;em&gt;the desire for certainty&lt;/em&gt; to be his inmost craving and deepest need – as that which separates the higher human beings from the lower! I discovered in certain pious people a hatred of reason and I was well disposed towards them for that: at least this betrayed their bad intellectual conscience! But to stand in the midst of this &lt;em&gt;rerum concordia discors&lt;/em&gt;2 and the whole marvellous uncertainty and ambiguity of existence &lt;em&gt;without questioning,&lt;/em&gt; without trembling with the craving and rapture of questioning, without at least hating the person who questions, perhaps even being faintly amused by him – that is what I feel to be &lt;em&gt;contemptible,&lt;/em&gt; and this is the feeling I look for first in anyone. Some folly keeps persuading me that every person has this feeling, simply as human. That is my type of injustice.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Noble and common.&lt;/em&gt; – For common natures all noble, magnanimous feelings appear to be inexpedient and therefore initially incredible: they give a wink when they hear of such things and seem to want to say, ‘Surely there must be some advantage involved; one cannot see through every wall’ – they are suspicious of the noble person, as if he were furtively seeking his advantage. If they become all too clearly convinced of the absence of selfish intentions and gains, they view the noble person as a kind of fool: they despise him in his pleasure and laugh at the sparkle in his eye. ‘How could one enjoy being at a disadvantage? How could one want with open eyes to be disadvantaged? Some disease of reason must be linked to the noble affection’ – thus they think and look disparagingly, the way they disparage the pleasure that a madman derives from his fixed idea. What distinguishes the common nature is that it unflinchingly keeps sight of its advantage, and that this thought of purpose and advantage is even stronger than its strongest drives; not to allow these drives to lead it astray to perform inexpeditious acts – that is its wisdom and self-esteem. In comparison, the higher nature is more &lt;em&gt;unreasonable&lt;/em&gt; – for the noble, magnanimous, and self-sacrificing person does in fact succumb to his drives; and in his best moments, his reason &lt;em&gt;pauses.&lt;/em&gt; An animal that protects its young at the risk of its own life or during the mating period follows the female unto death does not think of danger and death; its reason likewise pauses because the pleasure in its brood or in the female and the fear of being deprived of this pleasure dominate it totally; the animal becomes stupider than it usually is – just like the person who is noble and magnanimous. Such persons have several feelings of pleasure and displeasure so strong that they reduce the intellect to silence or to servitude: at that point their heart displaces their head, and one speaks thenceforth of ‘passion’. (Occasionally we also encounter the opposite, the ‘reversal of passion’, as it were; for example, somebody once laid his hand on Fontenelle’s heart and said, ‘What you have here, my dear sir, is also brains.’3) The unreason or odd reason (&lt;em&gt;Unvernunft oder Quervernunft&lt;/em&gt;) of passion is what the common type despises in the noble, especially when this passion is directed at objects whose value seems quite fantastic and arbitrary. He is annoyed by the person who succumbs to the passion of the belly, but at least he comprehends the appeal that plays the tyrant in this case; but he cannot comprehend how anyone could, for example, risk health and honour for the sake of a passion for knowledge. The higher nature’s taste is for exceptions, for things that leave most people cold and seem to lack sweetness; the higher nature has a singular value standard. Moreover, it usually believes that the idiosyncrasy of its taste is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a singular value standard; rather, it posits its values and disvalues as generally valid and so becomes incomprehensible and impractical. It is very rare that a higher nature has enough reason left over to understand and treat commonplace people as what they are; above all, it believes in its own passion as something that is present in everyone but concealed, and in this belief it is full of ardour and eloquence. Now when such exceptional people do not themselves feel like exceptions, how can they ever understand the common natures and arrive at a proper estimate of the rule! – and so they, too, speak of the stupidity, inexpedience, and fancifulness of humanity, stunned that the world is taking such an insane course and that it will not commit itself to that which ‘is needful’. – This is the eternal injustice of the noble.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What preserves the species.&lt;/em&gt; – The strongest and most evil spirits have so far done the most to advance humanity: time and again they rekindled the dozing passions – every ordered society puts the passions to sleep –, time and again they reawakened the sense of comparison, of contradiction, of delight in what is new, daring, unattempted; they forced men to pit opinion against opinion, ideal model against ideal model. Mostly by force of arms, by toppling boundary stones, by violating pieties – but also by means of new religions and moralities! In every teacher and preacher of what is new we find the same ‘mischief’ that makes conquerors infamous, even if its expression is subtler and does not instantly set the muscles in motion and for just that reason does not make one as infamous! What is new, however, is under all circumstances &lt;em&gt;evil,&lt;/em&gt; being that which wants to conquer, to overthrow the old boundary stones and pieties; and only what is old is good! In every age the good men are those who bury the old thoughts deeply and make them bear fruit – the farmers of the spirit. But that land is eventually exhausted, and the ploughshare of evil must come time and again. Nowadays there is a thoroughly erroneous moral theory which is celebrated especially in England: it claims that judgements of ‘good’ and ‘evil’ sum up experiences of what is ‘expedient’ and ‘inexpedient’; that what is called good preserves the species while what is called evil harms it. In truth, however, the evil drives are just as expedient, species-preserving, and indispensable as the good ones – they just have a different function.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unconditional duties.&lt;/em&gt; – All persons who feel that they need the strongest words and sounds, the most eloquent gestures and postures, in order to be effective &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt; – revolutionary politicians, socialists, preachers of repentance with or without Christianity, all of whom refuse to accept semi-successes: they all speak of ‘duties’, and indeed always of duties with an unconditional character – without such duties they would have no right to their great pathos; they know that quite well! So they reach for moral philosophies that preach some categorical imperative, or they ingest a goodly piece of religion, as Mazzini4 did, for example. Because they want the unconditional confidence of others, they first need unconditional confidence in themselves on the basis of some ultimate, indisputable and inherently sublime commandment, and they want to feel like and pass themselves off as its servants and instruments. Here we have the most natural and usually very influential opponents of moral enlightenment and scepticism; but they are rare. On the other hand, a very comprehensive class of these opponents can be found wherever self-interest teaches submission while reputation and honour seem to prohibit it. Whoever feels his dignity violated by the thought of being the &lt;em&gt;instrument&lt;/em&gt; of a prince or party or sect or even a financial power – say, as the descendant of an old, proud family – but still wants to or must be this instrument before himself and before the public, needs poignant principles that can be mouthed any time, principles of an unconditional ‘ought’ to which one may openly submit and be seen to have submitted without shame. All refined servility clings to the categorical imperative and is the mortal enemy of those who want to deprive duty of its unconditional character: that is what decency demands of them, and not only decency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Loss of dignity.&lt;/em&gt; – Reflection has lost all its dignity of form: we have made a laughing-stock of the ceremony and solemn gestures of reflection, and couldn’t stand an old-style wise man. We think too fast, while on our way somewhere, while walking or in the midst of all sorts of business, even when thinking of the most serious things; we need little preparation, not even much silence: it is as if we carried around in our heads an unstoppable machine that keeps working even under the most unfavourable circumstances. Formerly, one could tell just by looking at a person that he wanted to think – it was probably a rare occurrence! –, that he now wanted to become wiser and was preparing himself for a thought: one would set one’s face as for prayer and stop walking; yes, one stood still for hours on the street once the thought ‘arrived’ – on one or two legs. The dignity of the matter required it!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Something for the industrious.&lt;/em&gt; – Anyone who now wishes to make a study of moral matters opens up for himself an immense field of work. All kinds of passions have to be thought through separately, pursued separately through ages, peoples, great and small individuals; their entire reason and all their evaluations and modes of illuminating things must be revealed! So far, all that has given colour to existence still lacks a history: where could you find a history of love, of avarice, of envy, of conscience, of piety, of cruelty? Even a comparative history of law or even of punishment is so far lacking entirely. Has anyone done research on the different ways of dividing up the day or of the consequences of a regular schedule of work, festivals, and the rest? Do we know the moral effects of foods? Is there a philosophy of nutrition? (The incessantly erupting clamour for and against vegetarianism proves that there is still no such philosophy!) Has anyone collected people’s experiences of living together – in monasteries, for example? Has anyone depicted the dialectic of marriage and friendship? The customs of scholars, businessmen, artists, artisans – have they found their thinkers? There is so much in them to think about! Everything that humans have viewed until now as the ‘conditions of their existence’ and all the reason, passion, and superstition that such a view involves – has this been researched exhaustively? To observe how differently the human drives have grown and still could grow depending on the moral climate – that alone involves too much work for even the most industrious; it would require whole generations, and generations of scholars who would collaborate systematically, to exhaust the points of view and the material. The same applies to the demonstration of the reasons for the variety of moral climates (&lt;em&gt;‘why&lt;/em&gt; does the sun of one fundamental moral judgement and primary value-standard shine here – and another one there?’). Yet another new project would be to determine the erroneousness of all these reasons and the whole essence of moral judgements to date. If all these jobs were done, the most delicate question of all would emerge in the foreground: whether science is able to &lt;em&gt;furnish&lt;/em&gt; goals of action after having proved that it can take such goals away and annihilate them; and then an experimenting would be in order, in which every kind of heroism could find satisfaction – an experimenting that might last for centuries and eclipse all the great projects and sacrifices of history to date. So far, science has not yet built its cyclops-buildings;5 but the time for that will come, too.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unconscious virtues.&lt;/em&gt; – All qualities of a person of which he is conscious – and especially those he supposes to be visible and plain to others also – are subject to laws of development entirely different from those qualities which are unknown or badly known to him, which conceal themselves by means of their subtlety even from the eye of a rather subtle observer and which know how to hide as if behind nothing at all. This might be compared to the subtle sculptures on the scales of reptiles: it would be a mistake to take them for ornaments or weapons, since one sees them only with a microscope, i.e. with an artificially sharpened eye, which similar animals for whom they might signify something like ornaments or weapons simply lack. Our visible moral qualities, and especially those that we &lt;em&gt;believe&lt;/em&gt; to be visible, take their course; and the invisible ones, which have the same names but are neither ornaments nor weapons with regard to others, &lt;em&gt;also take their course:&lt;/em&gt; probably a totally different one, with lines and subtleties and sculptures that might amuse a god with a divine microscope. For example, we have our diligence, our ambition, our acuteness – all the world knows about them – and in addition, we probably also have &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; industry, &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; ambition, &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; acuteness; but for these reptile scales, no microscope has yet been invented! At this point the friends of instinctive morality will say: ‘Bravo! At least he considers unconscious virtues to be possible – and that’s enough for us.’ Oh, how little you are satisfied with!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our eruptions.&lt;/em&gt; – Countless things that humanity acquired in earlier stages, but so feebly and embryonically that no one could tell that they had been acquired, suddenly emerge into the light much later, perhaps after centuries; meanwhile they have become strong and ripe. Some ages seem to lack completely some talent or virtue, just as some people do: but just wait for their children and grandchildren, if you have time to wait – they bring to light the inner qualities of their grandfathers, the qualities that their grandfathers themselves did not know about. Often it is already the son that betrays his father: the father understands himself better once he has a son. All of us harbour in ourselves hidden gardens and plantations; and, to use another metaphor, we are all growing volcanoes approaching their hour of eruption; how near or distant that is, of course, nobody knows, not even the good Lord.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A kind of atavism.&lt;/em&gt; – I prefer to understand the rare human beings of an age as suddenly appearing, late ghosts of past cultures and their powers: as atavisms of a people and its mores – that way one can really &lt;em&gt;understand&lt;/em&gt; something about them! They now seem strange, rare, extraordinary; and whoever feels these powers in himself must nurse, defend, honor, and cultivate them against another world that resists them: and so he becomes either a great human being or a mad and eccentric one, unless he perishes too soon. Formerly, these same qualities were common and therefore considered ordinary: they weren’t distinguishing. They were perhaps demanded, presupposed; it was impossible to become great through them, if only because there was also no danger of becoming mad and lonely through them. It is principally in the generations and castes that &lt;em&gt;conserve&lt;/em&gt; a people that we find such recrudescences of old instincts, while such atavism is highly improbable where races, habits, and valuations change too rapidly. For tempo is as significant a power in the development of peoples as in music: in our case, what is absolutely necessary is an &lt;em&gt;andante&lt;/em&gt; of development, as the tempo of a passionate and slow spirit – and that is after all what the spirit of conservative generations is like.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Consciousness (Bewußtsein&lt;/em&gt;)6 – Consciousness (&lt;em&gt;Bewußtheit&lt;/em&gt;) is the latest development of the organic, and hence also its most unfinished and unrobust feature. Consciousness gives rise to countless mistakes that lead an animal or human being to perish sooner than necessary, ‘beyond destiny’, as Homer puts it.7 If the preserving alliance of the instincts were not so much more powerful, if it did not serve on the whole as a regulator, humanity would have to perish with open eyes of its misjudging and its fantasizing, of its lack of thoroughness and its incredulity – in short, of its consciousness; or rather, without the instincts, humanity would long have ceased to exist! Before a function is fully developed and mature, it constitutes a danger to the organism; it is a good thing for it to be properly tyrannized in the meantime! Thus, consciousness is properly tyrannized – and not least by one’s pride in it! One thinks it constitutes the &lt;em&gt;kernel&lt;/em&gt; of man, what is abiding, eternal, ultimate, most original in him! One takes consciousness to be a given determinate magnitude! One denies its growth and intermittences! Sees it as ‘the unity of the organism’! This ridiculous overestimation and misapprehension of consciousness has the very useful consequence that an all-too-rapid development of consciousness was &lt;em&gt;prevented.&lt;/em&gt; Since they thought they already possessed it, human beings did not take much trouble to acquire it – and things are no different today! The &lt;em&gt;task&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;assimilating knowledge&lt;/em&gt; and making it instinctive is still quite new; it is only beginning to dawn on the human eye and is yet barely discernible – it is a task seen only by those who have understood that so far we have incorporated only our &lt;em&gt;errors&lt;/em&gt; and that all of our consciousness refers to errors!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On the aim of science.&lt;/em&gt; – What? The final aim of science should be to give man as much pleasure and as little displeasure as possible? But what if pleasure and displeasure are so intertwined that whoever &lt;em&gt;wants&lt;/em&gt; as much as possible of one &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; also have as much as possible of the other – that whoever wants to learn to ‘jubilate up to the heavens’ must also be prepared for ‘grief unto death’?8 And that may well be the way things are! At least the Stoics believed that this is how things are, and they were consistent when they also desired as little pleasure as possible in order to derive as little pain as possible from life (by using the saying ‘The virtuous man is the happiest man’,9 they had both a school slogan for the masses and a fine casuistic delicacy for the refined). Even today you still have the choice: either &lt;em&gt;as little displeasure as possible,&lt;/em&gt; in short, lack of pain – and socialists and politicians of all parties fundamentally have no right to promise their people any more than that – or &lt;em&gt;as much displeasure as possible&lt;/em&gt; as the price for the growth of a bounty of refined pleasures and joys that hitherto have seldom been tasted. Should you decide on the former, i.e. if you want to decrease and diminish people’s susceptibility to pain, you also have to decrease and diminish their &lt;em&gt;capacity for joy.&lt;/em&gt; With &lt;em&gt;science&lt;/em&gt; one can actually promote either of these goals! So far it may still be better known for its power to deprive man of his joys and make him colder, more statue-like, more stoic. But it might yet be found to be the &lt;em&gt;great giver of pain!&lt;/em&gt; – And then its counterforce might at the same time be found: its immense capacity for letting new galaxies of joy flare up!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On the doctrine of the feeling of power.&lt;/em&gt; – Benefiting and hurting others are ways of exercising one’s power over them – that is all one wants in such cases! We &lt;em&gt;hurt&lt;/em&gt; those to whom we need to make our power perceptible, for pain is a much more sensitive means to that end than pleasure: pain always asks for the cause, while pleasure is inclined to stop with itself and not look back. We &lt;em&gt;benefit&lt;/em&gt; and show benevolence toward those who already depend on us in some way (that is, who are used to thinking of us as their causes); we want to increase their power because we thus increase our own, or we want to show them the advantage of being in our power – that way, they will be more satisfied with their situation and more hostile towards and willing to fight against the enemies of &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; power. Whether in benefiting or hurting others we make sacrifices does not affect the ultimate value of our actions; even if we stake our lives, as martyrs do for their church, it is a sacrifice made for &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; desire for power or for the preservation of our feeling of power. He who feels ‘I am in possession of the truth’ – how many possessions does he not renounce in order to save this feeling! What would he not throw overboard in order to stay ‘on top’ – that is, &lt;em&gt;above&lt;/em&gt; the others who lack ‘the truth’! The state in which we hurt others is certainly seldom as agreeable, in an unadulterated way, as that in which we benefit others; it is a sign that we are still lacking power, or it betrays a frustration in the face of this poverty; it brings new dangers and uncertainties to the power we do possess and clouds our horizon with the prospect of revenge, scorn, punishment, failure. Only to the most irritable and covetous adherents of the feeling of power – to those for whom the sight of those who are already subjected (the objects of benevolence) is a burden and boredom – might it be more pleasurable to imprint the seal of power on the reluctant. It depends on how one is accustomed to &lt;em&gt;spice&lt;/em&gt; one’s life; it is a matter of taste whether one prefers the slow or the sudden, the safe or the dangerous and daring increase in power – one always seeks this or that spice according to one’s temperament. An easy prey is something contemptible for proud natures; they take delight only at the sight of unbroken persons who could become their enemies and at the sight of all possessions that are hard to come by; they are often hard towards someone who is suffering, for he is not worthy of their contention and pride – but they are the more obliging toward their &lt;em&gt;equals,&lt;/em&gt; against whom it would be honourable to fight and struggle &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; the occasion should arise. Spurred by the good feeling of &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; perspective, the members of the knightly caste became accustomed to treating each others with exquisite courtesy. Compassion is the most agreeable feeling for those who have little pride and no prospect of great conquests; for them, easy prey – and that is what those who suffer are – is something enchanting. Compassion is praised as the virtue of prostitutes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The things people call love.&lt;/em&gt; – Greed and love: such different feelings these terms evoke! And yet it could be the same instinct, named twice: once disparaged by those who already &lt;em&gt;have,&lt;/em&gt; in whom the instinct has somewhat calmed down and who now fear for what they ‘have’; the other time seen from the standpoint of the unsatisfied, the thirsty, and therefore glorified as ‘good’. Our love of our neighbours – is it not a craving for new &lt;em&gt;property?&lt;/em&gt; And likewise our love of knowledge, of truth, and altogether any craving for what is new? We slowly grow tired of the old, of what we safely possess, and we stretch out our hands again; even the most beautiful landscape is no longer sure of our love after we have lived in it for three months, and some more distant coast excites our greed: possession usually diminishes the possession. The pleasure we take in ourselves tries to preserve itself by time and again changing something new &lt;em&gt;into ourselves&lt;/em&gt; – that is simply what possession means. To grow tired of a possession is to grow tired of ourselves. (One can also suffer from an excess – even the desire to throw away, to dole out, can take on the honorary name ‘love’.) When we see someone suffering, we like to use this opportunity to take possession of him; that is for example what those who become his benefactors and those who have compassion for him do, and they call the lust for new possessions that is awakened in them ‘love’; and their delight is like that aroused by the prospect of a new conquest. Sexual love, however, is what most clearly reveals itself as a craving for new property: the lover wants unconditional and sole possession of the longed-for person; he wants a power over her soul as unconditional as his power over her body; he wants to be the only beloved, to live and to rule in the other soul as that which is supreme and most desirable. If one considers that this means &lt;em&gt;excluding&lt;/em&gt; the whole world from a precious good, from joy and enjoyment; if one considers that the lover aims at the impoverishment and deprivation of all the competitors and would like to become the dragon guarding his golden hoard as the most inconsiderate and selfish of all ‘conquerors’ and exploiters; if one considers, finally, that to the lover himself the rest of the world appears indifferent, pale, and worthless and that he is prepared to make any sacrifice, upset any order, subordinate any other interest; then one is indeed amazed that this wild greed and injustice of sexual love has been as glorified and deified as it has in all ages – yes, that this love has furnished the concept of love as the opposite of egoism when it may in fact be the most candid expression of egoism. Here is it evidently the have-nots and the yearning ones who have formed linguistic usage – there have probably always been too many of them. Those who were granted much possession and satiety in this area must occasionally have made some casual remark about ‘the raging demon’, as did that most charming and beloved of all Athenians, Sophocles:10 but Eros always laughed at such blasphemers; they were always precisely his greatest darlings. Here and there on earth there is probably a kind of continuation of love in which this greedy desire of two people for each other gives way to a new desire and greed, a &lt;em&gt;shared&lt;/em&gt; higher thirst for an ideal above them. But who knows such love? Who has experienced it? Its true name is &lt;em&gt;friendship.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;From a distance.&lt;/em&gt; – This mountain makes the entire region it dominates attractive and significant in every way; having said this to ourselves for the hundredth time, we are so unreasonably and thankfully disposed toward it that we suppose that it, the bestower of such delight, must itself be the most delightful thing in the region – and so we climb it and are disappointed. Suddenly the mountain itself and the entire landscape around us, beneath us, seem to have lost their magic; we had forgotten that certain types of greatness, like certain types of goodness, want to be beheld only from a distance and always from below, not from above – only thus do they &lt;em&gt;have an effect.&lt;/em&gt; Perhaps you know people near you who ought to view themselves only from a distance in order to find themselves at all tolerable or attractive and invigorating; self-knowledge is something they should be advised against.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Over the footbridge.&lt;/em&gt; – When dealing with people who are bashful about their feelings, one has to be able to dissimulate; they feel a sudden hatred towards anyone who catches them in a tender or enthusiastic or elevated feeling, as if he had seen their secrets. If one wants to do them good in such moments, one should make them laugh or utter some cold, jocular sarcasm: then their feeling freezes and they regain power over themselves. But I am giving the moral before the story. There was a time in our lives when we were so close that nothing seemed to obstruct our friendship and brotherhood, and only a small footbridge separated us. Just as you were about to step on it, I asked you: ‘Do you want to cross the footbridge to me?’ – But then you didn’t want to any more; and when I asked again, you were silent. Since then, mountains and torrential rivers, and everything which separates and alienates, have been cast between us, and even if we wanted to reach each other, we couldn’t anymore! But when you think of that little footbridge now, you have no words anymore – only sobs and bewilderment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Finding a motive for one’s poverty.&lt;/em&gt; – There is clearly no trick that enables us to turn a poor virtue into a rich and overflowing one, but we can surely reinterpret its poverty nicely into a necessity, so that its sight no longer offends us and we no longer make reproachful faces at fate on its account. That is what the wise gardener does when he places the poor little stream in his garden in the arms of a nymph and thus finds a motive for its poverty: and who wouldn’t need nymphs as he does?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ancient pride&lt;/em&gt;. – The specific hue which nobility had in the ancient world is absent in ours because the ancient slave is absent from our sensibility. A Greek of noble descent found such immense intermediate stages and such a distance between his own height and that ultimate baseness that he could barely see the slave clearly any more: not even Plato could really see him. It is different with us, accustomed as we are to the &lt;em&gt;doctrine&lt;/em&gt; of human equality, if not also to equality itself. A creature who is not at its own disposal and who lacks leisure is by no means something despicable to us on that account; perhaps each of us possesses too much of such slavishness in accordance with the conditions of our social order and activity, which are utterly different from those of the ancients. The Greek philosopher went through life feeling secretly that there were far more slaves than one might think – namely, that everyone who was not a philosopher was a slave;11 his pride overflowed when he considered that even the mightiest men on earth might be his slaves. This pride, too, is foreign and impossible for us; not even metaphorically does the word ‘slave’ possess for us its full force.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>19</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Evil.&lt;/em&gt; – Examine the lives of the best and the most fruitful people and peoples and ask yourselves whether a tree which is supposed to grow to a proud height could do without bad weather and storms: whether misfortune and exernal resistance, whether any kinds of hatred, jealousy, stubbornness, mistrust, hardness, greed, and violence do not belong to the &lt;em&gt;favourable&lt;/em&gt; conditions without which any great growth even of virtue is scarcely possible? The poison from which the weaker nature perishes strengthens the strong man – and he does not call it poison.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>20</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/20/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/20/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The dignity of foolishness.&lt;/em&gt; – A few millennia further along the course set by the last century – and everything men do will display the highest prudence: but just that way prudence will lose all its dignity. Then it will, to be sure, be necessary to be prudent, but it will also be so commonplace and vulgar that even a moderately aristocratic taste will experience this necessity as a &lt;em&gt;vulgarity.&lt;/em&gt; And just as a tyranny of truth and science could increase esteem for the lie, a tyranny of prudence could spur a new kind of nobility. To be noble might then come to mean: to entertain follies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/21/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To the teachers of selflessness.&lt;/em&gt; – A person’s virtues are called &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; with respect to their presumed effects not on him but on us and society – the praise of virtues has always been far from ‘selfless’, far from ‘unegoistic’! For otherwise one would have had to recognize that the virtues (such as diligence, obedience, chastity, piety, justice) are mostly &lt;em&gt;harmful&lt;/em&gt; to their possessors, being drives which dominate them all too violently and covetously and in no way let reason keep them in balance with the other drives. When you have a virtue – a real, complete virtue (and not just a small drive towards some virtue) – you are its &lt;em&gt;victim!&lt;/em&gt; But the neighbour praises your virtue precisely on that account! One praises the diligent even if he should harm his vision or the originality and freshness of his spirit; one honours and feels sorry for the youth who has ‘worked himself to death’ because one thinks: ‘For society as a whole the loss of even the best individual is merely a small sacrifice! Too bad that the sacrifice is necessary! It would surely be much worse though if the individual had thought otherwise and considered his own preservation and development more important than his work in the service of society!’ And so one feels sorry for this youth, not for his own sake but because a devoted &lt;em&gt;tool,&lt;/em&gt; ruthless towards itself – a so-called ‘good man’ – has been lost to society through his death. Perhaps one also asks whether it would not have been more useful to society if he had worked in a way that was less negligent towards himself and had preserved himself longer – yes, one admits that there would have been some advantage in that, but considers this other advantage to be greater and more last; that a &lt;em&gt;sacrifice&lt;/em&gt; was made and the ethos of the sacrificial animal once again vindicated &lt;em&gt;for all to see.&lt;/em&gt; What is, therefore, first really praised when virtues are praised is their instrumental nature and then the blind drive in every virtue that refuses to be held in check by the overall advantage of the individual – in short, the unreason in virtue that leads the individual to allow himself to be transformed into a mere function of the whole. The praise of virtues is the praise of something privately harmful – the praise of drives which deprive a human being of his noblest selfishness and of the strength for the highest form of self-protection. For the sake of inculcating and incorporating virtuous habits into people, to be sure, one emphasizes various effects of virtue that make virtue and private advantage appear as sisters – and there is in fact such a relationship! Blindly raging industriousness, for example – this typical virtue of an instrument – is represented as the road to riches and honour and as the best poison for curing boredom and the passions; but one keeps silent about its danger, its extreme dangerousness. That is how education always proceeds: it tries to condition the individual through various attractions and advantages to adopt a way of thinking and behaving that, when it has become habit, drive and passion, will rule in him and over him &lt;em&gt;against his ultimate advantage&lt;/em&gt; but ‘for the common good’. How often I see it: that blindly raging industriousness brings riches and honour but at the same time deprives the organs of refinement that make it possible to enjoy the riches and honour; also, that this chief antidote to boredom and to the passions at the same time dulls the senses and makes the spirit resistant to new attractions. (The most industrious age – our own – doesn’t know how to make anything of all its industriousness and money except still more money and still more industriousness; for more genius is required to spend than to acquire! – Well, we’ll still have our ‘grandchildren’!) If education is successful, each virtue of the individual is a public utility and a private disadvantage with respect to the highest private end – probably involving some deterioration of the spirit and the senses or even a premature demise: consider from this standpoint the virtues of obedience, chastity, piety, and justice. The praise of the selfless, the self-sacrificing, the virtuous – that is, of the person who does not apply his entire strength and reason to &lt;em&gt;his own&lt;/em&gt; preservation, development, elevation, promotion, and expansion of power, but rather lives, as regards himself, modestly and throughtlessly, maybe even with indifference and irony – this praise is certainly not born out of the spirit of selflessness! The ‘neighbour’ praises selflessness because &lt;em&gt;it brings him advantages!&lt;/em&gt; If the neighbour himself thought ‘selflessly’, he would reject this decrease in strength, this harm for &lt;em&gt;his&lt;/em&gt; benefit; he would work against the development of such inclinations, and above all he would affirm his selflessness by &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; calling it &lt;em&gt;good!&lt;/em&gt; Hereby we hint at the fundamental contradiction in the morality that is very much honoured just now: the &lt;em&gt;motives&lt;/em&gt; to this morality stand in opposition to its &lt;em&gt;principle!&lt;/em&gt; What this morality wants to use as its proof, it refutes with its criterion of what is moral! In order not to contradict itself, the command ‘You shall renounce yourself and sacrifice yourself’ could be proclaimed only by a being which thereby renounced its own advantage and perhaps, through the demanded sacrifice of the individual, brought about its own destruction. But as soon as the neighbour (or society) recommends altruism &lt;em&gt;for the sake of its utility,&lt;/em&gt; it is using the directly opposed principle, ‘You shall seek your advantage even at the expense of everything else’ – and thus one preaches, in the same breath, a ‘Thou shalt’ and a ‘Thou shalt not’!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>22</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/22/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;*L’ordre du jour pour le roi.*12 – The day begins: let us begin to organize for this day the business and festivities of our most gracious master who is still deigning to repose. His majesty has bad weather today: we shall be careful not to call it bad; we shall not speak of the weather – but we shall be a bit more ceremonious about the business than would otherwise be necessary and a bit more festive about the festivities. His majesty may even be ill: at breakfast we shall present the latest good news of last evening, the arrival of Mr Montaigne, who jokes so agreeably about his illness; he’s suffering from a stone.13 We shall receive a few persons (persons! What that puffed-up old frog who will be among them would say if he heard this word! ‘I am not a person’, he would say, ‘but always the matter itself’14) – and this reception will take longer than anyone finds agreeable: that is reason enough to tell about the poet who wrote on his door, ‘Whoever enters here will pay me an honour; whoever does not – a pleasure.’15 Truly a polite way to express a rudeness! And perhaps this poet is for his part quite right in being rude: they say his poems are better than their maker. Well, then let him write many more and withdraw himself from the world as much as possible – that is after all the meaning of his civil incivility! Conversely, a prince is always worth more than his ‘verse’, even if – but what are we doing? We are gossiping and the whole court thinks we are already working and racking our brains – one sees no light earlier than the one burning in our window. Listen! Wasn’t that the bell? Damn! The day and the dance are beginning and we don’t know the programme! So we have to improvise – the whole world improvises its day. Let’s just do today as the whole world does! And there my strange morning dream vanished, probably the victim of the hard strokes of the tower bell, which just announced the fifth hour with all of its customary importance. It seems to me that this time the god of dreams wanted to poke fun at my habit of starting the day by organizing it and making it tolerable &lt;em&gt;to myself,&lt;/em&gt; and it may well be that I have often done this in too formal and princelike a manner.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>23</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/23/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/23/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The signs of corruption.&lt;/em&gt; – Consider the following signs of those states of society that are necessary from time to time and that are designated by the word ‘corruption’. As soon as corruption sets in anywhere, a colourful &lt;em&gt;superstition&lt;/em&gt; takes over, and the previous common faith of a people becomes pale and powerless against it: for supersitition is free-spiritedness of the second rank – whoever succumbs to it selects certain forms and formulas that appeal to him and allows himself some freedom of choice. The superstitious person is always, compared to the religious person, much more of a ‘person’, and a superstitious society will be one in which there are many individuals and much delight in individuality. From this perspective, superstition always appears as &lt;em&gt;progress&lt;/em&gt; against faith and as a sign that the intellect is becoming more independent and demanding its rights. Those who then complain about corruption are the devotees of the old religion and religiosity – until now they have also determined linguistic usage and given superstition a bad name even among the freest spirits. Let us realize that it is actually a symptom of &lt;em&gt;enlightenment.&lt;/em&gt; Secondly, a society in which corruption spreads is accused of laxity; and it is obvious that the esteem of war and the pleasure in war diminish, while the comforts of life are now desired just as ardently as were warlike and athletic honours formerly. What is usually overlooked, however, is that the ancient civil energy and passion, which received a magnificent visibility through war and competitive games, has now transformed itself into countless private passions and has merely become less visible; indeed, in times of ‘corruption’ the power and force of a people’s expended energies are probably greater than ever, and the individual spends them on a lavish scale which he could not previously have afforded – when he was not yet rich enough! And thus it is precisely in times of ‘laxness’ that tragedy runs through the houses and streets, that great love and great hatred are born and the flame of knowledge blazes up into the sky. Thirdly, it is usually said to the credit of such societies, as if one wanted to compensate for the reproaches of superstition and laxness, that they are milder and that cruelty declines drastically in comparison to the older, stronger, more devout age. But this praise I cannot endorse any more than the reproaches: I concede only that cruelty now &lt;em&gt;refines&lt;/em&gt; itself and that its older forms henceforth offend taste; but wounding and torturing with word and eye reaches its highest cultivation in times of corruption – it is now alone that &lt;em&gt;malice&lt;/em&gt; and the delight in malice are born. People who live in an age of corruption are witty and slanderous; they know that there are other kinds of murder than by dagger or assault; they also know that whatever is &lt;em&gt;well said&lt;/em&gt; is believed. Fourthly, when ‘morals decay’, those beings emerge for the first time who are called tyrants: they are the precursors and as it were the precocious &lt;em&gt;firstling instances of individuals.&lt;/em&gt; Just a little bit longer and this fruit of fruits hangs ripe and yellow on the tree of a people – and this tree existed only for the sake of this fruit! Once decay has reached its peak along with the struggle of all sorts of tyrants, the Caesar always appears, the final tyrant who puts an end to the weary wrestling for sole rule by putting weariness to work for himself. In his age the individual is usually ripest and culture is therefore at its highest and most fruitful stage, but not for the sake of him and not through him, though those of the highest culture like to flatter their Caesar by claiming to be &lt;em&gt;his&lt;/em&gt; work. In truth they need peace from without because they have enough unrest and work within. In these times, bribery and treason are at their peak, for the love of the newly discovered ego is now much mightier than the love of the old, used-up, touted-to-death ‘fatherland’, and the need to secure oneself from the terrible ups and downs of luck opens even noble hands as soon as someone who is mighty and wealthy shows himself willing to pour gold into them. There is now so very little secure future; one lives for today: a state of soul that makes an easy game for all seducers, for one allows oneself to be seduced and bribed only ‘for today’ and reserves the future and virtue for oneself! As is well known the individuals, these true ‘in-and-for-themselves’, care more about the moment than do their opposites, the herd people, for they consider themselves just as unpredictable as the future. They also like to join up with people of violence because they think themselves capable of actions and information which the common people would neither understand nor forgive, while the tyrant or Caesar would understand the rights of the individual even in his excesses and has an interest in advocating and even abetting a bolder private morality. For he thinks of himself and wants his self to be thought of as Napoleon once expressed it in his classic manner : ‘I have the right to answer all charges against me with an eternal “That is me.” I am apart from all the world and accept conditions from no one. I want people to submit even to my fantasies and to find it natural when I yield to this or that distraction.’ That is what Napoleon once replied to his wife when she had reasons to question her husband’s marital fidelity.16Times of corruption are those in which the apples fall from the tree: I mean the individuals, the seed-bearers of the future, the spiritual colonizers and shapers of new states and communities. Corruption is just a rude word for the &lt;em&gt;autumn&lt;/em&gt; of a people.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>24</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/24/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Different forms of dissatisfaction.&lt;/em&gt; – The weak and, as it were, feminine discontented types are those who are innovative at making life more beautiful and profound; the strong discontents – the men among them, to stick with the metaphor – are innovative at making it better and safer. The former show their weakness and femininity by gladly letting themselves be deceived from time to time and occasionally resting content with a bit of intoxication and gushing enthusiasm, though they can never be satisfied entirely and suffer from the incurability of their dissatisfaction; they are also the promoters of all who know how to procure opiates and narcotic consolations, and consequently they resent those who esteem physicians above priests – thus they assure the &lt;em&gt;continuance&lt;/em&gt; of real distress! Had there not been a surplus of these discontents in Europe since the middle ages, the celebrated European capacity for constant &lt;em&gt;transformation&lt;/em&gt; might never have developed, for the demands of the strong discontents are too crude and basically too undemanding not eventually to be brought to a final rest. China, for example, is a country where large-scale discontentment and the capacity for &lt;em&gt;change&lt;/em&gt; became extinct centuries ago; and in Europe too the socialists and state idolaters, with their measures for making life better and safer, might easily establish Chinese conditions and a Chinese ‘happiness’, provided they are first able to extirpate that sicklier, more tender, more feminine discontentment and romanticism that is for the moment still superabundant here. Europe is a patient who owes the utmost gratitude to his incurability and to the perpetual changes in his affliction: these incessantly new conditions, these no less incessantly new dangers, pains, and modes of information have finally generated an intellectual irritability that approximates genius and that is in any case the mother of all genius.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>25</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/25/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Not predestined for knowledge.&lt;/em&gt; – There is a stupid humility that is by no means rare, and those afflicted with it are altogether unfit to become votaries of knowledge. For as soon as a person of this type perceives something striking, he turns on his heel, as it were, and says to himself, ‘You have made a mistake! Where were your senses? This cannot be the truth!’ And then, instead of looking and listening more keenly again, he runs away, as if intimidated, from the striking thing and tries to shake it from his mind as fast as possible. For his inner canon says: ‘I want to see nothing that contradicts the prevalent opinion. Am &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; made to discover new truths? There are already too many old ones.’&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>26</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/26/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/26/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What is life?&lt;/em&gt; – Life – that is: continually shedding something that wants to die; Life – that is: being cruel and inexorable against anything that is growing weak and old in us, and not just in us. Life – therefore means: being devoid of respect for the dying, the wretched, the aged? Always being a murderer? And yet old Moses said: ‘Thou shalt not kill.’17&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>27</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/27/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/27/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The renouncer.&lt;/em&gt; – What does the renouncer do? He strives for a higher world, he wants to fly further and higher than all affirmers – &lt;em&gt;he throws away much&lt;/em&gt; that would encumber his flight, including some things that are not valueless, not disagreeable to him: he sacrifices it to his desire for the heights. This sacrificing, this throwing away, is now precisely what alone becomes visible in him and leads people to call him the renouncer, and thus he stands before us, shrouded in his hood as if he were the soul of a hairshirt. But he is quite satisfied with the impression that he makes on us: he wants to conceal from us his desire, his pride, his intention to soar &lt;em&gt;beyond&lt;/em&gt; us. Yes, he is cleverer than we thought, and so polite towards us – this affirmer! For he is just as we are even in his renunciation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>28</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/28/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/28/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Harming with what is best in oneself.&lt;/em&gt; – At times our strengths propel us so far ahead that we can no longer stand our weaknesses and perish from them. We may even foresee this outcome and still will have it no other way. Thus we become hard against that within us that wants to be spared, and our greatness is also our mercilessness. Such an experience, for which we must in the end pay with our lives, is a parable for the whole effect of great human beings on others and on their age: precisely with what is best in them, with what only they can do, they destroy many who are weak, insecure, in the process of becoming, of willing, and thus they are harmful. It can even happen that, all in all, they are harmful only because what is best in them is accepted and as it were imbibed only by those whom it affects like an overly potent drink: they lose their mind and their selfishness; they become so intoxicated that they are bound to break their limbs on all the wrong paths down which their intoxication drives them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>29</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/29/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/29/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The add-on-liars.&lt;/em&gt; – When people in France started to fight the Aristotelian unities18 and others consequently also started to defend them, one could see again something that is so often apparent but that people are loath to see: &lt;em&gt;one lied to oneself,&lt;/em&gt; inventing reasons for these laws, simply to avoid admitting that one had become &lt;em&gt;used&lt;/em&gt; to them and would no longer have it any other way. And that is what one does, and has always done, within every prevailing morality and religion: the reasons and intents behind habits are invented only when some people start attacking the habits and &lt;em&gt;asking&lt;/em&gt; for reasons and intents. Here we have the great dishonesty of conservatives of all times – they are the add-on-liars.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>30</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/30/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/30/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The comedy of the famous.&lt;/em&gt; – Famous men who &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; their fame, e.g. all politicians, never choose allies and friends without ulterior motives: from one they want a piece of the splendour and reflected splendour of his virtue; from another the fear-inspiring aspects of certain dubious qualities that everyone knows him to have; from another they steal the reputation of his idleness, his lying in the sun, because it serves their own ends to appear inattentive and sluggish at times – it conceals the fact that they actually lie in wait; now they need a visionary around; now an expert; now a thinker; now a pedant, as if he were their present self; but just as quickly they don’t need them any more! And so the surroundings and exteriors of famous men die off continually, even while everything seems to be pushing to get into these surroundings and lend them their character; in this, they are like big cities. Their reputation is continually changing, like their character, for their changing methods demand these changes and push forward now this, now that real or fictitious characteristic onto the stage. Their friends and allies belong, as I said, to these stage properties. What they want, however, must stand all the much more firmly and unshakeably and be splendidly seen from afar; and this, too, sometimes requires its comedy and its theatrics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>31</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/31/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/31/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Trade and nobility.&lt;/em&gt; – Buying and selling are common by now, like the art of reading and writing; everyone has practised it, even if he is not a tradesman, and gets more practice at this technique every day – just as formerly, in the age of a more savage humanity, everyone was a hunter and practised the technique of hunting every day. In that age, hunting was common; but eventually it became a privilege and thereby lost its everyday and common character – because it stopped being necessary and became a thing of moods and luxury. The same thing could happen to buying and selling one day. One can imagine social conditions in which there is no buying and selling and in which this technique gradually becomes unnecessary. Perhaps some individuals who are not as subject to the laws of the general condition will then give themselves permission to buy and sell as a &lt;em&gt;luxury of sentiment.&lt;/em&gt; Only then would trade become something exquisite, and the noble might enjoy trade as much as they hitherto enjoyed war and politics, while conversely the assessment of politics could have changed completely. Even now it is ceasing to be the art of the nobleman, and it is quite possible that some day one will find it so base that, along with all political literature and journalism, one classifies it as a ‘prostitution of the spirit’.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>32</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/32/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/32/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Undesired disciples.&lt;/em&gt; – ‘What can I do with these two young men!’ cried an irritated philosopher who ‘corrupted’ the youth as Socrates once had done;19 they are unwelcome students. This one can’t say ‘no’ and the other one says ‘half and half’ about everything. If they adopted my doctrine, the first would &lt;em&gt;suffer&lt;/em&gt; too much, for my way of thinking requires a warlike soul, a desire to hurt, a delight in saying no, a hard skin; he would languish from open and internal wounds. And the other would strike a compromise with everything he represents and thereby make it into a mediocrity – such a disciple I wish on my enemies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>33</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/33/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/33/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Outside the lecture-room.&lt;/em&gt; – ‘In order to prove to you that man is fundamentally a good-natured animal, I would remind you of how credulous he has been for so long. Only now, quite late and after tremendous self-conquest, has he become a &lt;em&gt;distrustful&lt;/em&gt; animal. Yes, man is now more evil than ever.’ I do not understand this: why should man be more distrustful and evil now? ‘Because he now has a science – needs a science.’&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>34</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/34/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/34/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;*Historia abscondita.*20 – Every great human being exerts a retroactive force: for his sake all of history is put on the scale again, and a thousand secrets of the past crawl out of their hiding places – into &lt;em&gt;his&lt;/em&gt; sunshine. There is no telling what may yet become a part of history. Maybe the past is still essentially undiscovered! So many retroactive forces are still needed!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>35</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/35/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/35/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Heresy and witchcraft.&lt;/em&gt; – To think otherwise than is customary is much less the effect of a superior intellect than of strong, evil inclinations – detaching, isolating, defiant, gloating, and malicious inclinations. Heresy is the adjunct of witchcraft and surely no more harmless and least of all anything venerable. Heretics and witches are two species of evil people; what they have in common is that they also feel evil but are impelled by an unconquerable lust to harm what is prevailing (people or opinions). The Reformation, which was a kind of redoubling of the medieval spirit at a time when it was no longer accompanied by a good conscience, produced both in the greatest abundance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>36</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/36/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/36/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Last words.&lt;/em&gt; – One will recall that the emperor Augustus, that frightful man who had as much self-control and who could be as silent as any wise Socrates, became indiscreet against himself with his last words: he let his mask fall for the first time when he made it clear that he had worn a mask and acted a comedy – he had played the father of the fatherland and the wisdom on the throne well enough to create the proper illusion! *Plaudite amici, comoedia finita est!*21 The thought of the dying Nero – *qualis artifex pereo!*22 – was also the thought of the dying Augustus: actor’s vanity! Actor’s prolixity! And truly the opposite of the dying Socrates!23 But Tiberius died silently, this most tormented of all self-tormentors – &lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt; was genuine and no actor! What might have passed through his mind at the end? Maybe this: ‘Life – that is a long death. What a fool I was to shorten so many lives! Was &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; made to be a benefactor? I should have given them eternal &lt;em&gt;life:&lt;/em&gt; that way, I could have &lt;em&gt;seen them die&lt;/em&gt; forever. &lt;em&gt;That’s&lt;/em&gt; why I had such good eyes: *qualis spectator pereo!’*24 When after a long death-struggle he seemed to recover his strength, it was considered advisable to smother him with pillows – he died a double death.25&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>37</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/37/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/37/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Because of three errors.&lt;/em&gt; – One has promoted science during the last centuries partly because it was through science that one hoped best to understand God’s goodness and wisdom – the main motive in the soul of the great Englishmen (such as Newton);26 partly because one believed in the absolute usefulness of knowledge, especially in the most intimate affiliation between morality, knowledge, and happiness – the main motive in the soul of the French (such as Voltaire);27 and partly because one believed that in science one had and loved something selfless, harmless, self-sufficient, and truly innocent in which the evil drives of humanity had no part at all – the main motive in the soul of Spinoza,28who felt divine in attaining knowledge – in sum, because of three errors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>38</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/38/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/38/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The explosive ones.&lt;/em&gt; – When one considers how the energy of young men needs to explode, one is not surprised to see them decide so unsubtly and so unselectively for this or that cause: what thrills them is the sight of the zeal surrounding a cause and, so to speak, the sight of the burning match – not the cause itself. The subtler seducers therefore know how to create in them the expectation of an explosion and to disregard justifying their cause: reasons are not the way to win over these powder kegs!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>39</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/39/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/39/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Changed taste.&lt;/em&gt; – Change in common taste is more important than that in opinions; opinions along with proofs, refutations, and the whole intellectual masquerade are only symptoms of a changed taste and most certainly &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; what they are so often taken to be, its causes. How does common taste change? Through individuals – powerful, influential, and without any sense of shame – who announce and tyrannically enforce &lt;em&gt;their hoc est ridiculum, hoc est absurdum&lt;/em&gt;,29 i.e. the judgement of their taste and disgust: thus they put many under pressure, which gradually turns into a habit among even more and finally becomes a &lt;em&gt;need of everyone.&lt;/em&gt; The reason why these individuals sense and ‘taste’ differently is usually found in a peculiarity of their lifestyle, nutrition, digestion, maybe a deficit or excess of inorganic salts in their blood and brains – in short, in their *physis:*30 they have the courage to own up to their &lt;em&gt;physis&lt;/em&gt; and to heed its demands down to its subtlest tones. Their aesthetic and moral judgements are such ‘subtlest tones’ of the &lt;em&gt;physis.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>40</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/40/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/40/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On the lack of noble style.&lt;/em&gt; – Soldiers and leaders still have a far higher relation to one another than do workers and employers. So far at least, all cultures with a military basis are still high above so-called industrial culture: the latter in its present form is altogether the most vulgar form of existence that has ever been. Here it is simply the law of need operating: one wants to live and has to sell oneself, but one despises those who exploit this need and &lt;em&gt;buy&lt;/em&gt; the worker. It is strange that submission to powerful, frightening, yes, terrifying persons, to tyrants and generals, is experienced to be not nearly as distressing as this submission to unknown and uninteresting persons, which is what all the greats of industry are: the worker usually sees in the employer only a cunning, bloodsucking dog of a man who speculates on all distress and whose name, figure, manner, and reputation are completely indifferent to him. So far the manufacturers and large-scale commercial entrepreneurs have apparently been much too lacking in all the manners and signs of &lt;em&gt;higher race&lt;/em&gt; that alone enable a person to become &lt;em&gt;interesting;&lt;/em&gt; if they had the refinement of noble breeding in their eye and gesture, there might not be any socialism of the masses. For the masses are basically prepared to submit to any kind of &lt;em&gt;slavery&lt;/em&gt; provided that the superiors constantly legitimize themselves as higher, as &lt;em&gt;born&lt;/em&gt; to command – through refined demeanour! The commonest man senses that refinement cannot be improvised and that one has to honour in it the fruit of long ages – but the absence of the higher demeanour and the notorious manufacturer’s vulgarity with ruddy, plump hands give him the idea that it is only accident and luck that elevated one above the other in this case: well, then, he infers, let &lt;em&gt;us&lt;/em&gt; try accident and luck! Let &lt;em&gt;us&lt;/em&gt; throw the dice! – and socialism begins.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>41</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/41/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/41/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Against remorse.&lt;/em&gt; – The thinker sees his own actions as experiments and questions, as seeking explanations of something: to him, success and failure are primarily &lt;em&gt;answers.&lt;/em&gt; To be vexed or even to feel remorse because something goes wrong – he leaves that to those who act because they were ordered to do so and who expect a beating when his gracious lordship is not pleased with the result.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>42</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/42/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/42/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Work and boredom.&lt;/em&gt; – Seeking work for the sake of wages – in this, nearly all people in civilized countries are alike; to all of them, work is just a means and not itself the end, which is why they are unrefined in their choice of work, provided it yields an ample reward. Now there are rare individuals who would rather perish than work without taking &lt;em&gt;pleasure&lt;/em&gt; in their work: they are choosy, hard to please, and have no use for ample rewards if the work is not itself the reward of rewards. To this rare breed belong artists and contemplative men of all kinds, but also men of leisure who spend their lives hunting, travelling, in love affairs, or on adventures. All of them want work and misery as long as it is joined with pleasure, and the heaviest, hardest work, if need be. Otherwise they are resolutely idle, even if it spells impoverishment, dishonour, and danger to life and limb. They do not fear boredom as much as work without pleasure; indeed, they need a lot of boredom if &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; work is to succeed. For the thinker and for all inventive spirits, boredom is that disagreeable ‘lull’ of the soul that precedes a happy voyage and cheerful winds; he has to endure it, must &lt;em&gt;await&lt;/em&gt; its effect on him – precisely &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; is what lesser natures are totally unable to achieve! To fend off boredom at any price is vulgar, just as work without pleasure is vulgar. Perhaps Asians are distinguished as above Europeans by their capacity for a longer, deeper calm; even their narcotics work slowly and require patience, in contrast to the revolting suddenness of the European poison, alcohol.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>43</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/43/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/43/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What the laws betray.&lt;/em&gt; – It is a grave error to study a people’s penal code as if it were an expression of its character; the laws do not betray what a people is but rather what appears to it as foreign, strange, uncanny, outlandish. The laws concern the exceptions to the morality of custom (&lt;em&gt;Sittlichkeit der&lt;/em&gt; Sitte)31, and the severest punishments are for things that accord with the customs of the neighbouring people. Thus the Wahanabis32 have only two mortal sins: having a god other than the Wahanabi god and – smoking (which they call ‘the disgraceful way of drinking’). ‘And what about murder and adultery?’ asked the Englishman, amazed, who found this out. ‘God is gracious and merciful’, the old chief replied. Thus the old Romans had the notion that a woman could commit only two mortal sins: adultery and – drinking wine. Old Cato thought that kissing among relatives had been made into a custom only in order to keep the women under control in this regard; a kiss meant, ‘Does she smell of wine?’33 Women caught with wine were actually put to death; and certainly not just because sometimes women under the influence of wine completely forgot how to say no; above all, the Romans feared the orgiastic and Dionysian cult which afflicted the women of southern Europe from time to time when wine was still new in Europe – feared it as a foreign monster that overthrew the basis of Roman sensibility; to them it seemed like a betrayal of Rome, like the embodiment of the foreign.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>44</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/44/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/44/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The supposed motives.&lt;/em&gt; – Important as it may be to know the motives from which humanity has acted so far, it might be even more essential to know the &lt;em&gt;belief&lt;/em&gt; people had in this or that motive, i.e. what humanity has imagined and told itself to be the real lever of its conduct so far. For people’s inner happiness and misery has come to them depending on their belief in this or that motive – &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; through the actual motives. The latter are of second-order interest.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>45</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/45/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/45/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Epicurus&lt;/em&gt;.34 – Yes, I am proud to experience Epicurus’ character in a way unlike perhaps anyone else and to enjoy, in everything I hear and read of him, the happiness of the afternoon of antiquity: I see his eye gaze at a wide whitish sea, across shoreline rocks bathed in the sun, as large and small creatures play in its light, secure and calm like the light and his eye itself. Only someone who is continually suffering could invent such happiness – the happiness of an eye before which the sea of existence has grown still and which now cannot get enough of seeing the surface and this colourful, tender, quivering skin of the sea: never before has voluptuousness been so modest.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>46</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/46/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/46/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our amazement.&lt;/em&gt; – It is a deep and fundamental stroke of luck that science discovers things that &lt;em&gt;stand up&lt;/em&gt; under examination and that furnish the basis, again and again, for further discoveries – after all, it could be otherwise! Indeed, we are so convinced of the uncertainty and the fantastical quality of our judgements and of the eternal change of human laws and concepts that it actually amazes us &lt;em&gt;how well&lt;/em&gt; the results of science stand up! Formerly, one knew nothing of the changeableness of everything human; the habit of attachment to customary morality (&lt;em&gt;Sitte der Sittlichkeit&lt;/em&gt;) sustained the faith that the entire inner life of humanity was fastened to iron necessity with eternal clamps; perhaps people then experienced a similarly voluptuous amazement when they told each other stories and fairy tales. The miraculous did a lot of good to those who at times grew weary of the rule and of eternity. To lose firm ground for once! To float! To err! To be mad! – that was part of the paradise and debauchery of former ages, whereas our bliss is like that of the shipwrecked man who has climbed ashore and is standing with both feet on the firm old earth – marvelling because it does not bob up and down.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>47</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/47/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/47/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On the suppression of the passions.&lt;/em&gt; – If one constantly forbids oneself the expression of the passions, as if that were something to be left for the ‘common’, coarser, middle-class, peasant types – i.e. if one wants to suppress not the passions themselves but only their language and gesture – one still attains &lt;em&gt;in addition&lt;/em&gt; what one did not desire: the suppression of the passions themselves, at least their weakening and alteration – the most instructive example being furnished by the court of Louis XIV and everything that depended on it. The age that &lt;em&gt;followed,&lt;/em&gt; brought up in the suppression of expression, no longer had the passions themselves and had in their place a graceful, shallow, playful manner – an age marked by an incapacity for bad manners, so that even an insult was accepted and returned with obliging words. Perhaps the present age supplies the most notable counterpart: everywhere, in life and on the stage, and not the least in everything written, I see the delight in all the &lt;em&gt;coarser&lt;/em&gt; outbursts and gestures of passion: what is demanded these days is a certain convention of the passionate – but not passion itself! Nevertheless, eventually passion &lt;em&gt;itself&lt;/em&gt; will be reached this way, and our progeny will be &lt;em&gt;genuinely savage&lt;/em&gt; and not just savage and unruly in demeanour.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>48</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/48/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/48/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Knowledge of distress.&lt;/em&gt; – Perhaps nothing separates human beings or ages from each other more than the different degrees of their knowledge of distress – distress of the soul as well as of the body. Regarding the latter we moderns may well, in spite of our frailties and fragilities, be bunglers and dreamers owing to lack of ample first-hand experience, compared with an age of fear, the longest of all ages, when individuals had to protect themselves against violence and to that end had themselves to become men of violence. In those days, a man received ample training in bodily torments and deprivations and understood that even a certain cruelty towards himself, as a voluntary exercise in pain, was a necessary means of his preservation; in those days, one trained one’s surroundings to endure pain; in those days, one gladly inflicted pain and saw the most terrible things of this kind happen to others without any other feeling than that of one’s own safety. As regards the distress of the soul, however, I look at each person today to see whether he knows it through experience or description; whether he still considers it necessary to fake this knowledge, say, as a sign of refined cultivation, or whether at the bottom of his soul he no longer believes in great pains of the soul and reacts to its mention in much the same way as to the mention of great bodily sufferings, which make him think of his toothaches and stomachaches. But that is how most people seem to me to be these days. The general inexperience with both sorts of pain and the relative rarity of the sight of suffering individuals have an important consequence: pain is hated much more now than formerly; one speaks much worse of it; indeed, one can hardly endure the presence of pain &lt;em&gt;as a thought&lt;/em&gt; and makes it a matter of conscience and a reproach against the whole of existence. The emergence of pessimistic philosophers is in no way the sign of great, terrible states of distress; rather, these question marks about the value of all life are made in times when the refinement and ease of existence make even the inevitable mosquito bites of the soul and the body seem much too bloody and malicious, and the poverty of real experiences of pain makes one tend to consider &lt;em&gt;painful general ideas&lt;/em&gt; as already suffering of the highest rank. There is a recipe against pessimistic philosophies and excessive sensitivity, things which seem to me to be the real ‘distress of the present’ – but this recipe may sound too cruel and would itself be counted among the signs that lead people to judge, ‘existence is something evil’. Well, the recipe against this ‘distress’ is: &lt;em&gt;distress.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>49</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/49/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/49/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Magnanimity and related things.&lt;/em&gt; – Those paradoxical phenomena, like the sudden coldness in the behaviour of the emotional person, or the humour of the melancholy person, or above all &lt;em&gt;magnanimity&lt;/em&gt; as a sudden renunciation of revenge or a satisfaction of envy, appear in people who have a powerful inner centrifugal force, in people of sudden satiety and sudden nausea. Their satisfactions are so quick and strong that they are immediately followed by weariness and aversion and a flight into the opposite taste: in this opposite, the cramp of feeling is resolved – in one person by sudden cold, in another by laughter, in a third by tears and self-sacrifice. The magnanimous person – at least the type of magnanimous person who has always made the strongest impression – strikes me as a person with a most extreme thirst for vengeance, who sees satisfaction nearby and drinks it down &lt;em&gt;already in imagination&lt;/em&gt; so fully, thoroughly and to the last drop that a tremendous, quick nausea follows this quick excess and he now rises ‘above himself’, as they say, and forgives his enemy, indeed blesses and honours him. With this rape of himself, with this mockery of his drive for revenge he only gives in to the new drive which just now has become powerful in him (disgust), and he does so just as impatiently and excessively as just a moment ago he imaginatively &lt;em&gt;anticipated&lt;/em&gt; and, as it were, exhausted his delight in revenge. Magnanimity has the same degree of egoism as revenge, only egoism of a different quality.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>50</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/50/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/50/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The argument from growing solitary.&lt;/em&gt; – The reproach of conscience is weak in even the most conscientious people compared to the feeling: ‘This or that is against the morals (&lt;em&gt;die gute Sitte&lt;/em&gt;) of &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; society.’ Even the strongest person still &lt;em&gt;fears&lt;/em&gt; a cold look or a sneer on the face of those among whom and for whom he has been brought up. What is he really afraid of? Growing solitary! This is the argument that refutes even the best arguments for a person or a cause. – Thus the herd instinct speaks out in us.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>51</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/51/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/51/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sense of truth.&lt;/em&gt; – I approve of any form of scepticism to which I can reply, ‘Let’s try it!’ But I want to hear nothing more about all the things and questions that don’t admit of experiment. This is the limit of my ‘sense of truth’; for there, courage has lost its right.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>52</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/52/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/52/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What others know about us.&lt;/em&gt; – What we know about ourselves and remember is not as decisive to our life’s happiness as it is believed to be. One day, what &lt;em&gt;others&lt;/em&gt; know (or think they know) about us assails us – and then we realize that that is more powerful. It is easier to deal with a bad conscience than a bad reputation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>53</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/53/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/53/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Where the good begins.&lt;/em&gt; – At the point where the poor power of the eye is no longer able to see the evil drive as such, owing to its increasing subtlety, man posits the realm of goodness; and the feeling of now having stepped into the land of goodness excites all those impulses that had been threatened and limited by the evil drive, such as the feeling of security, of comfort, of benevolence. So: the duller the eye, the more extensive the good! Hence the eternal cheerfulness of the common people and of children! Hence the gloominess and grief – akin to a bad conscience – of the great thinkers!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>54</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/54/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/54/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The consciousness of appearance.&lt;/em&gt; – How wonderful and new and yet how fearful and ironic my new insight makes me feel towards all of existence! I have &lt;em&gt;discovered&lt;/em&gt; for myself that the ancient humanity and animality, indeed the whole prehistory and past of all sentient being, continues within me to fabulate, to love, to hate, and to infer – I suddenly awoke in the middle of this dream, but only to the consciousness that I am dreaming and that I &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; go on dreaming lest I perish – as the sleepwalker has to go on dreaming in order to avoid falling down. What is ‘appearance’ to me now! Certainly not the opposite of some essence – what could I say about any essence except name the predicates of its appearance! Certainly not a dead mask that one could put on an unknown x and probably also take off x! To me, appearance is the active and living itself, which goes so far in its self-mockery that it makes me feel that here there is appearance and a will-o’-the-wisp and a dance of spirits and nothing else – that among all these dreamers, even I, the ‘knower’, am dancing my dance; that the one who comes to know is a means of prolonging the earthly dance and thus is one of the masters of ceremony of existence, and that the sublime consistency and interrelatedness of all knowledge may be and will be the highest means to &lt;em&gt;sustain&lt;/em&gt; the universality of dreaming, the mutual comprehension of all dreamers, and thereby also &lt;em&gt;the duration of the dream.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>55</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/55/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/55/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The ultimate noblemindedness.&lt;/em&gt; – So what makes a person ‘noble’? Certainly not making sacrifices; even those burning with lust make sacrifices. Certainly not following some passion, for there are contemptible passions. Certainly not that one does something for others without selfishness: perhaps no one is more consistently selfish than the noble one. – Rather, the passion that overcomes the noble one is a singularity, and he fails to realize this: the use of a rare and singular standard and almost a madness; the feeling of heat in things that feel cold to everyone else; a hitting upon values for which the scale has not yet been invented; a sacrifice on altars made for an unknown god; a courage without any desire for honours; a self-sufficiency that overflows and communicates to men and things. Hitherto, then, it was rarity and the unawareness of this rarity that made noble. Note, however, that by means of this standard everything usual, near, and indispensable, in short, that which most preserved the species, and in general the &lt;em&gt;rule&lt;/em&gt; of humanity hitherto, was inequitably judged and on the whole slandered in favour of the exceptions. To become the advocate of the rule – that might be the ultimate form and refinement in which noblemindedness manifests itself on earth.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>56</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/56/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/1_Book_One/56/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The desire for suffering.&lt;/em&gt; – When I think of the desire to do something, how it continually tickles and goads the millions of young Europeans who cannot endure boredom and themselves, I realize that they must have a yearning to suffer something in order to make their suffering a likely reason for action, for deeds. Neediness is needed! Hence the clamour of the politicians; hence the many false, fictitious, exaggerated ‘emergencies’ of all kinds and the blind readiness to believe in them. This young world demands that not happiness, but unhappiness should approach or become visible &lt;em&gt;from outside;&lt;/em&gt; and its imagination is already busy turning this unhappiness into a monster ahead of time so that afterwards it can fight a monster. Were these distress-addicts to feel within themselves the power to do themselves good from within, to do something for themselves, they would know how to create their very own distress. Their inventions could then become more refined and their satisfactions sound like good music, while they now fill the world with their clamour about distress, and consequently, all too often with the &lt;em&gt;feeling of distress!&lt;/em&gt; They do not know what to do with themselves – and so they paint the unhappiness of others on the wall; they always need others! And continually other others! – Pardon me, my friends, I have ventured to paint my &lt;em&gt;happiness&lt;/em&gt; on the wall.35&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
