<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;5 Book Five on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;5 Book Five on Vishvas&#39;s English lit</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>343</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/343/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/343/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How to understand our cheerfulness.&lt;/em&gt; – The greatest recent event – that ‘God is dead’; that the belief in the Christian God has become unbelievable – is already starting to cast its first shadow over Europe. To those few at least whose eyes – or the &lt;em&gt;suspicion&lt;/em&gt; in whose eyes is strong and subtle enough for this spectacle, some kind of sun seems to have set; some old deep trust turned into doubt: to them, our world must appear more autumnal, more mistrustful, stranger, ‘older’. But in the main one might say: for many people’s power of comprehension, the event is itself far too great, distant, and out of the way even for its tidings to be thought of as having arrived yet. Even less may one suppose many to know at all &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; this event really means – and, now that this faith has been undermined, how much must collapse because it was built on this faith, leaned on it, had grown into it – for example, our entire European morality. This long, dense succession of demolition, destruction, downfall, upheaval that now stands ahead: who would guess enough of it today to play the teacher and herald of this monstrous logic of horror, the prophet of deep darkness and an eclipse of the sun the like of which has probably never before existed on earth? Even we born guessers of riddles who are so to speak on a lookout at the top of the mountain, posted between today and tomorrow and stretched in the contradiction between today and tomorrow, we firstlings and premature births of the next century, to whom the shadows that must soon envelop Europe really &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; have become apparent by now – why is it that even we look forward to this darkening without any genuine involvement and above all without worry and fear for &lt;em&gt;ourselves?&lt;/em&gt; Are we perhaps still not too influenced by the &lt;em&gt;most immediate consequences&lt;/em&gt; of this event – and these immediate consequences, the consequences for &lt;em&gt;ourselves,&lt;/em&gt; are the opposite of what one might expect – not at all sad and gloomy, but much more like a new and barely describable type of light, happiness, relief, amusement, encouragement, dawn&amp;hellip; Indeed, at hearing the news that ‘the old god is dead’, we philosophers and ‘free spirits’ feel illuminated by a new dawn; our heart overflows with gratitude, amazement, forebodings, expectation – finally the horizon seems clear again, even if not bright; finally our ships may set out again, set out to face any danger; every daring of the lover of knowledge is allowed again; the sea, &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; sea, lies open again; maybe there has never been such an ‘open sea’.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>344</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/344/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/344/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In what way we, too, are still pious.&lt;/em&gt; – In science, convictions have no right to citizenship, as one says with good reason: only when they decide to step down to the modesty of a hypothesis, a tentative experimental standpoint, a regulative fiction,1 may they be granted admission and even a certain value in the realm of knowledge – though always with the restriction that they remain under police supervision, under the police of mistrust. But doesn’t this mean, on closer consideration, that a conviction is granted admission to science only when it &lt;em&gt;ceases&lt;/em&gt; to be a conviction? Wouldn’t the cultivation of the scientific spirit begin when one permitted oneself no more convictions? That is probably the case; only we need still ask: &lt;em&gt;in order that this cultivation begin,&lt;/em&gt; must there not be some prior conviction – and indeed one so authoritative and unconditional that it sacrifices all other convictions to itself? We see that science, too, rests on a faith; there is simply no ‘presuppositionless’ science. The question whether &lt;em&gt;truth&lt;/em&gt; is necessary must get an answer in advance, the answer ‘yes’, and moreover this answer must be so firm that it takes the form of the statement, the belief, the conviction: &lt;em&gt;‘Nothing&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; necessary than truth; and in relation to it, everything else has only secondary value.’ This unconditional will to truth – what is it? Is it the will not to let oneself be deceived? Is it the will &lt;em&gt;not to deceive?&lt;/em&gt; For the will to truth could be interpreted in this second way, too – if ‘I do not want to deceive &lt;em&gt;myself&lt;/em&gt;’ is included as a special case under the generalization ‘I do not want to deceive.’ But why not deceive? But why not allow oneself to be deceived? Note that the reasons for the former lie in a completely different area from those for the latter: one does not want to let oneself be deceived because one assumes it is harmful, dangerous, disastrous to be deceived; in this sense science would be a long-range prudence, caution, utility, and to this one could justifiably object: How so? Is it really less harmful, dangerous, disasterous not to want to let oneself be deceived? What do you know in advance about the character of existence to be able to decide whether the greater advantage is on the side of the unconditionally distrustful or of the unconditionally trusting? But should both be necessary – a lot of trust &lt;em&gt;as well as&lt;/em&gt; a lot of mistrust – then where might science get the unconditional belief or conviction on which it rests, that truth is more important than anything else, than every other conviction? Precisely this conviction could never have originated if truth &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; untruth had constantly made it clear they they were both useful, as they are. So, the faith in science, which after all undeniably exists, cannot owe its origin to such a calculus of utility; rather it must have originated &lt;em&gt;in spite of&lt;/em&gt; the fact that the disutility and dangerousness of ‘the will to truth’ or ‘truth at any price’ is proved to it constantly. ‘At any price’: we understand this well enough once we have offered and slaughtered one faith after another on this altar! Consequently, ‘will to truth’ does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; mean ‘I do not want to let myself be deceived’ but – there is no alternative – ‘I will not deceive, not even myself’; &lt;em&gt;and with that we stand on moral ground.&lt;/em&gt; For you have only to ask yourself carefully, ‘Why do you not want to deceive?’ especially if it should seem – and it does seem! – as if life aimed at semblance, i.e. error, deception, simulation, blinding, self-blinding, and when life on the largest scale has actually always shown itself to be on the side of the most unscrupulous *polytropoi.*2 Charitably interpreted, such a resolve might perhaps be a quixotism, a slight, enthusiastic folly; but it could also be something worse, namely a principle that is hostile to life and destructive. ‘Will to truth’ – that could be a hidden will to death. Thus the question ‘Why science?’ leads back to the moral problem: &lt;em&gt;Why morality at all,&lt;/em&gt; if life, nature, and history are ‘immoral’? No doubt, those who are truthful in that audacious and ultimate sense which faith in science presupposes &lt;em&gt;thereby affirm another world&lt;/em&gt; than that of life, nature, and history; and insofar as they affirm this ‘other world’, must they not by the same token deny its counterpart, this world, &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; world?&amp;hellip;But you will have gathered what I am getting at, namely, that it is still a &lt;em&gt;metaphysical faith&lt;/em&gt; upon which our faith in science rests – that even we knowers of today, we godless anti-metaphysicians, still take &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; fire, too, from the flame lit by the thousand-year old faith, the Christian faith which was also Plato’s faith, that God is truth; that truth is divine&amp;hellip; But what if this were to become more and more difficult to believe, if nothing more were to turn out to be divine except error, blindness, the lie – if God himself were to turn out to be our longest lie?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>345</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/345/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/345/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Morality as a problem.&lt;/em&gt; – The lack of personality always takes its revenge: a weakened, thin, extinguished personality, one that denies itself and its own existence, is no longer good for anything good – least of all for philosophy. ‘Selflessness’ has no value in heaven or on earth; all great problems demand &lt;em&gt;great love,&lt;/em&gt; and only strong, round, secure minds who have a firm grip on themselves are capable of that. It makes the most telling difference whether a thinker has a personal relationship to his problems and finds in them his destiny, his distress, and his greatest happiness, or an ‘impersonal’ one, meaning he is only able to touch and grasp them with the antennae of cold, curious thought. In the latter case nothing will come of it, that much can be promised; for even if great problems should let themselves be &lt;em&gt;grasped&lt;/em&gt; by them, they would not allow frogs and weaklings to &lt;em&gt;hold on&lt;/em&gt; to them; such has been their taste from time immemorial – a taste, incidentally, that they share with all doughty females. Why, then, have I never yet encountered anyone, not even in books, who approached morality in this personal way and who knew morality as a problem, and this problem as his own personal distress, torment, voluptuousness, and passion? It is clear that up to now, morality has been no problem at all but rather that on which, after all mistrust, discord, and contradiction, one could agree – the hallowed place of peace where thinkers took a rest from themselves, took a deep breath, and felt revived. I see no one who has ventured a &lt;em&gt;critique&lt;/em&gt; of moral valuations; I miss even the slightest attempts of scientific curiosity, of the coddled, experimental imagination of psychologists and historians that easily anticipates a problem and seizes it in flight without knowing what it has caught. I have hardly detected a few meagre preliminary efforts to explore the &lt;em&gt;history of origins&lt;/em&gt; of these feelings and valuations (which is something quite different from a critique and again different from a history of ethical systems): in one single case I did everything to encourage a sympathy and talent for this kind of history – in vain, as it seems to me today.3 These historians of morality (particularly, the Englishmen) do not amount to much: usually they themselves unsuspectingly stand under the command of a particular morality and, without knowing it, serve as its shield-bearers and followers, for example, by sharing that popular superstition of Christian Europe which people keep repeating so naively to this day, that what is characteristic of morality is selflessness, self-denial, self-sacrifice, or sympathy (&lt;em&gt;Mitgefühl&lt;/em&gt;) and compassion (&lt;em&gt;Mitleiden).&lt;/em&gt; Their usual mistaken premise is that they affirm some consensus among peoples, at least among tame peoples, concerning certain moral principles, and then conclude that these principles must be unconditionally binding also for you and me – or, conversely, they see that among different peoples moral valuations are &lt;em&gt;necessarily&lt;/em&gt; different and infer from this that &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; morality is binding – both of which are equally childish. The mistake of the more subtle among them is that they uncover and criticize the possibly foolish opinions of a people about their morality, or of humanity about all human morality – opinions about its origin, its religious sanction, the myth of the free will and such things – and then think they have criticized the morality itself. But the value of the injunction ‘Thou Shalt’ is still fundamentally different from and independent of such opinions about it and the weeds of error that may have overgrown it – just as surely as the value of a medication for someone sick is totally independent of whether he thinks about medicine scientifically or the way an old woman thinks about it. A morality could even have grown &lt;em&gt;out of&lt;/em&gt; an error, and the realization of this fact would not as much as touch the problem of its value. Thus no one until now has examined the &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt; of that most famous of all medicines called morality; and for that, one must begin by &lt;em&gt;questioning&lt;/em&gt; it for once. Well then! Precisely that is our task.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>346</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/346/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/346/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our question mark.&lt;/em&gt; – But you do not understand this? Indeed, people will have trouble understanding us. We are searching for words, perhaps also for ears. Who are we anyway? If we simply called ourselves godless (to use an old expression), or unbelievers, or even immoralists, we would not think that these words came near to describing us: we are all three of them, at too advanced a stage for anyone to comprehend – for &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; to comprehend, my curious gentlemen – how it feels. No! No longer with the bitterness and passion of the one who has torn himself away and must turn his unbelief into another faith, a goal, a martyrdom! We have become hard-boiled, cold, and tough in the realization that the way of the world is not at all divine – even by human standards it is not rational, merciful, or just. We know it: the world we live in is ungodly, immoral, ‘inhuman’; for far too long we have interpreted it falsely and mendaciously, though according to our wish and will for veneration, that is, according to a &lt;em&gt;need.&lt;/em&gt; For man is a venerating animal! But he is also a mistrustful one; and that the world is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; worth what we thought is about the most certain thing our mistrust has finally gotten hold of. The more mistrust, the more philosophy. We take care not to claim that the world is worth &lt;em&gt;less;&lt;/em&gt; indeed, it would seem laughable to us today if man were to aim at inventing values that were supposed to &lt;em&gt;surpass&lt;/em&gt; the value of the real world. That is exactly what we have turned away from, as from an extravagant aberration of human vanity and unreason that for long was not recognized as such. It found its final expression in modern pessimism, and an older and stronger expression in the teaching of Buddha; but also Christianity includes it, more doubtfully and ambiguously, to be sure, but not for that reason less seductively. The whole attitude of ‘man &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; the world’, of man as a ‘world-negating’ principle, of man as the measure of the value of things, as judge of the world who finally places existence itself on his scales and finds it too light – the monstrous stupidity of this attitude has finally dawned on us and we are sick of it; we laugh we soon as we encounter the juxtaposition of ‘man &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; world’, separated by the sublime presumptuousness of the little word ‘and!’ But by laughing, haven’t we simply taken contempt for man one step further? And thus also pessimism, the contempt for that existence which is knowable to &lt;em&gt;us?&lt;/em&gt; Have we not exposed ourselves to the suspicion of an opposition – an opposition between the world in which until now we were at home with our venerations – and which may have made it possible for us to &lt;em&gt;endure&lt;/em&gt; life – and another world &lt;em&gt;that we ourselves are:&lt;/em&gt; a relentless, fundamental, deepest suspicion concerning ourselves that is steadily gaining more and worse control over us Europeans and that could easily confront coming generations with the terrible Either/Or: ‘Either abolish your venerations or – &lt;em&gt;yourselves!’&lt;/em&gt; The latter would be nihilism; but would not the former also be – nihilism? That is &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; question mark.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>347</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/347/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/347/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Believers and their need to believe.&lt;/em&gt; – The extent to which one needs a &lt;em&gt;faith&lt;/em&gt; in order to flourish, how much that is ‘firm’ and that one does not want shaken because one &lt;em&gt;clings&lt;/em&gt; to it – that is a measure of the degree of one’s strength (or, to speak more clearly, one’s weakness). Christianity, it seems to me, is still needed by most people in old Europe even today; hence it still finds believers. For that is how man is: an article of faith could be refuted to him a thousand times; as long as he needed it, he would consider it ‘true’ again and again, in accordance with that famous ‘proof of strength’4 of which the Bible speaks. Metaphysics is still needed by some, but so is that impetuous &lt;em&gt;demand for certainty&lt;/em&gt; that today discharges itself in scientific-positivistic form among great masses – the demand that one &lt;em&gt;wants&lt;/em&gt; by all means something to be firm (while owing to the fervour of this demand one treats the demonstration of this certainty more lightly and negligently): this is still the demand for foothold, support – in short, the &lt;em&gt;instinct of weakness&lt;/em&gt; that, to be sure, does not create sundry religions, forms of metaphysics, and convictions but does – preserve them. Indeed, around all these positivistic systems hover the fumes of a certain pessimistic gloom, something of a weariness, fatalism, disappointment, fear of new disappointment – or else self-dramatizing rage, a bad mood, the anarchism of exasperation and whatever other symptoms or masquerades there are of the feeling of weakness. Even the vehemence with which our cleverest contemporaries get lost in pitiful nooks and crevices such as patriotism (I refer to what the French call &lt;em&gt;chauvinisme&lt;/em&gt;5 and the Germans ‘German’), or in petty aesthetic creeds such as French naturalism (which enhances and exposes only the part of nature that simultaneously disgusts and amazes – today one likes to call it &lt;em&gt;la verité vraie&lt;/em&gt;6 –), or in Petersburg-style nihilism7 (meaning &lt;em&gt;faith in unbelief&lt;/em&gt; to the point of martyrdom), always indicates primarily the &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; for faith, a foothold, backbone, support&amp;hellip; Faith is always most desired and most urgently needed where will is lacking; for will, as the affect of command, is the decisive mark of sovereignty and strength. That is, the less someone knows how to command, the more urgently does he desire someone who commands, who commands severely – a god, prince, the social order, doctor, father confessor, dogma, or party conscience. From this one might gather that both world religions, Buddhism and Christianity, may have owed their origin and especially their sudden spread to a tremendous &lt;em&gt;sickening of the will.&lt;/em&gt; And that is actually what happened: both religions encountered a demand for a ‘Thou Shalt’ that, through a sickening of the will, had increased to an absurd level and bordered on desperation; both religions were teachers of fanaticism in times of a slackening of the will and thereby offered innumerable people support, a new possibility of willing, a delight in willing. For fanaticism is the only ‘strength of the will’ that even the weak and insecure can be brought to attain, as a type of hypnosis of the entire sensual-intellectual system to the benefit of the excessive nourishment (hypertrophy) of a single point of view and feeling which is now dominant – the Christian calls it his &lt;em&gt;faith.&lt;/em&gt; Once a human being arrives at the basic conviction that he &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be commanded, he becomes ‘a believer’; conversely, one could conceive of a delight and power of self-determination, a &lt;em&gt;freedom&lt;/em&gt; of the will, in which the spirit takes leave of all faith and every wish for certainty, practised as it is in maintaining itself on light ropes and possibilities and dancing even beside abysses. Such a spirit would be the &lt;em&gt;free spirit&lt;/em&gt; par excellence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>348</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/348/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/348/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On the origin of scholars.&lt;/em&gt; – In Europe the scholar grows out of all kinds of classes and social conditions like a plant that requires no particular kind of soil: thus he belongs, essentially and involuntarily, to the bearers of the democratic idea. But this origin betrays itself. Once one has somewhat trained one’s eye to recognize in a scholarly book, in a scientific treatise, the scholar’s intellectual &lt;em&gt;idiosyncrasy&lt;/em&gt; – every scholar has one – and catch it in the act, one will almost always behind it come face to face with the scholar’s ‘prehistory’, his family, especially its occupations and crafts. Where the feeling, ‘This is now proven; I am done with it,’ is expressed, it is usually the ancestor in the blood and instincts of the scholar who from his standpoint approves of ‘the finished job’ – the faith in a proof is only the symptom of what in a hard-working family for ages has been considered ‘good work’. An example: the sons of all types of clerks and office workers, whose main task was always to organize various different kinds of material, to compartmentalize and in general to schematize, when they become scholars, show a tendency to consider a problem practically solved when they have merely schematized it. There are philosophers who are basically just schematizers – for them, the formal aspect of their fathers’ occupation has become content. The talent for classifications, for tables of categories, reveals something: one pays the price for being the child of one’s parents. The son of a lawyer will also, as a researcher, have to be a lawyer; he primarily wants his cause to win; secondarily perhaps also for it to be right. The sons of Protestant ministers and schoolteachers one recognizes by the naive certainty with which, as scholars, they take their case already to have been proven when they have merely stated it heartily and warmly; they are thoroughly used to being &lt;em&gt;believed,&lt;/em&gt; as that was part of their father’s craft. A Jew, on the other hand, in keeping with the characteristic occupations and the past of his people, is not at all used to being believed. Consider Jewish scholars in this light: they all have a high regard for logic, that is for &lt;em&gt;compelling&lt;/em&gt; agreement by force of reasons; they know that with logic, they are bound to win even when faced with class and race prejudices, where people do not willingly believe them. For nothing is more democratic than logic: it knows no regard for persons and takes even the crooked nose for straight. (Incidentally, Europe owes the Jews no small thanks for making its people more logical, for &lt;em&gt;cleanlier&lt;/em&gt; intellectual habits – none more so than the Germans, as a lamentably &lt;em&gt;déraisonnable&lt;/em&gt;8 race that even today first needs to be given a good mental drubbing. Wherever Jews have gained influence, they have taught people to make finer distinctions, draw more rigorous conclusions, and to write more clearly and cleanly; their task was always ‘to make a people “listen to &lt;em&gt;raison&lt;/em&gt;” ’.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>349</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/349/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/349/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Once again, the origin of the scholars.&lt;/em&gt; – To wish to preserve oneself is a sign of distress, of a limitation of the truly basic life-instinct, which aims at &lt;em&gt;the expansion of power&lt;/em&gt; and in so doing often enough risks and sacrifices self-preservation. It is symptomatic that certain philosophers, such as the consumptive Spinoza, took and indeed had to take just the so-called self-preservation instinct to be decisive:9 – they were simply people in distress. That today’s natural sciences have become so entangled with the Spinozistic dogma (most recently and crudely in Darwinism with its incredibly one-sided doctrine of ‘the struggle for existence’ –) is probably due to the descent of most natural scientists: in this regard they belong to ‘the people’, their ancestors were poor and lowly folks who knew all too intimately the difficulty of scraping by. English Darwinism exudes something like the stuffy air of English overpopulation, like the small people’s smell of indigence and overcrowding. As a natural scientist, however, one should get out of one’s human corner; and in nature, it is not distress which &lt;em&gt;rules,&lt;/em&gt; but rather abundance, squandering – even to the point of absurdity. The struggle for survival is only an &lt;em&gt;exception,&lt;/em&gt; a temporary restriction of the will to life; the great and small struggle revolves everywhere around preponderance, around growth and expansion, around power and in accordance with the will to power, which is simply the will to life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>350</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/350/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/350/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;*In honour of the homines religiosi.*10 – The struggle against the church is certainly, among other things – for it means many things – also the struggle of the baser, meaner, more cheerful, more confiding, more superficial natures against the dominion of the graver, deeper, and more contemplative, that is, more evil and distrustful individuals who, with a long-standing suspicion about the value of existence, also brooded over their own worth: the base instinct of the people, its sensuality, its ‘good heart’, rebelled against them. The entire Roman Church rests on a Southern distrust of human nature which is always misunderstood in the North. The European South has inherited this suspicion from the deep Orient, from ancient mysterious Asia and its contemplation. Protestantism is, to be sure, an uprising in favour of the upright, the guileless, the shallow (the North has always been more good-natured and superficial than the South); but it was the French Revolution that finally and ceremoniously handed over the sceptre to the ‘good people’ (to the sheep, the donkey, the goose, and everything that is incurably shallow and loudmouthed and ripe for the madhouse of ‘modern ideas’).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>351</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/351/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/351/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In honour of the priestly type:&lt;/em&gt; – I think that what the people mean by wisdom (and who today is not ‘people’?) – that prudent, cowlike serenity, piety and country parson meekness which lies in the meadow and earnestly and ruminantly &lt;em&gt;observes&lt;/em&gt; life – is also that from which precisely the philosophers have always felt the most remote, probably because they were not ‘people’ enough, not country parsons enough. They will presumably also be the last to learn to believe that the people &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; come to understand something of that which is most remote from them, something of the great &lt;em&gt;passion&lt;/em&gt; of the knowledge-seeker who steadfastly lives, must live, in the thundercloud of the highest problems and the weightiest responsibilities (and thus in no way as an observer, outside, indifferent, secure, objective&amp;hellip;). The people venerate quite another type of person when they construct for themselves an ideal of the ‘sage’, and they have a thousandfold right to adore just this type of person with the best words and honours – the mild, serious/simple-minded and chaste priestly natures and whatever is related to them: they are the ones who are the objects of approbation when the common people reveres wisdom. And towards whom would the people have more reason to show themselves grateful than these men, who belong to and come from them, though as consecrated, chosen, sacrificed for the common good – they believe themselves sacrificed to God – , to whom the people can spill their hearts with impunity and &lt;em&gt;get rid of&lt;/em&gt; their secrets, worries and worse (– for he who ‘unbosoms’ himself is relieved of himself, and he who has ‘confessed’, forgets). Here reigns a great necessity: drainages and their clean, cleansing waters are needed also for the spiritual refuse; swift streams of love are needed, and strong, humble, pure hearts who prepare and sacrifice themselves for such an office of non-public health care – for it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a sacrifice; a priest is and remains a human sacrifice&amp;hellip;The people see such sacrificed, subdued, serious persons of ‘faith’ as &lt;em&gt;wise,&lt;/em&gt; that is, as having become knowing, as ‘certain’ in relation to their own uncertainty; and who would want to deprive them of this word and of their awe? But as is conversely fair, among philosophers a priest, too, is considered to be one of ‘the people’ and not a knower, primarily because philosophers do not themselves believe in ‘men of knowledge’ and already smell ‘the people’ in this belief and superstition. It was &lt;em&gt;modesty&lt;/em&gt; that in Greece coined the word ‘philosopher’ and left the extraordinary insolence of calling oneself wise to the actors of the spirit – the modesty of such monsters of pride and conceit as Pythagoras, as Plato –.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>352</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/352/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/352/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The extent to which morality is hardly dispensable.&lt;/em&gt; – The naked human being is generally a disgraceful sight – I am talking about us Europeans (and not even about female Europeans!). Supposing that by the mischievous trick of a sorcerer, the merriest dinner party suddenly saw itself exposed and undressed; I think not only the mirth would be lost but also the strongest appetite discouraged, – it seems we Europeans are utterly unable to dispense with that masquerade called clothing. But why should there not be equally good reasons for the disguise of ‘moral men’, for their veil of moral formulas and notions of decency, for the whole benevolent concealment of our actions behind the concepts of duty, virtue, public spirit, respectability, self-denial? I am not supposing that something like human malice and perfidy – in short, the bad wild beast in us – is thereby disguised; my thought is, quite on the contrary, that it is precisely as &lt;em&gt;tame animals&lt;/em&gt; that are we a disgraceful sight and need the disguise of morality, – that the ‘inner man’ in Europe is not nearly evil enough to be able to ‘show himself’ that way (and be &lt;em&gt;beautiful&lt;/em&gt; that way –). The European disguises himself &lt;em&gt;with morality&lt;/em&gt; because he has become a sick, sickly, maimed animal which has good reasons for being ‘tame’; because he is almost a monstrosity, something half, weak, awkward&amp;hellip;It is not the ferocity of the beast of prey that needs a moral disguise, but the herd animal with its deep mediocrity, fear, and boredom with itself. &lt;em&gt;Morality dresses up the European&lt;/em&gt; – let’s admit it! – into something nobler, grander, goodlier, something ‘divine’ –&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>353</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/353/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/353/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On the origin of religions.&lt;/em&gt; – The true invention of the religion-founders is first to establish a certain way of life and everyday customs that work as a &lt;em&gt;disciplina voluntatis&lt;/em&gt;11 while at the same time removing boredom; and then to give just this life an &lt;em&gt;interpretation&lt;/em&gt; that makes it appear illuminated by the highest worth, so that henceforth it becomes a good for which one fights and under certain circumstances even gives one’s life. Actually, the second invention is the more important: the first, the way of life, was usually already in place, though alongside other ways of life and without any consciousness of its special worth. The significance, the originality of the religion-founder usually lies in his &lt;em&gt;seeing&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;selecting&lt;/em&gt; this way of life, in his &lt;em&gt;guessing&lt;/em&gt; for the first time what it can be used for and how it can be interpreted. Jesus (or Paul), for example, discovered the life of the small people in the Roman province, a humble, virtuous, depressed life: he explained it, he put the highest meaning and value into it – and thereby also the courage to despise every other way of life, the silent Moravian brotherhood12 fanaticism, the clandestine subterranean self-confidence that grows and grows and is finally ready to ‘overcome the world’ (i.e. Rome and the upper classes throughout the empire). Buddha likewise discovered, scattered indeed among all classes and social strata of his people, that type of person who is good and gracious (above all, inoffensive) out of laziness and who, also from laziness, lives abstinently and with nearly no needs at all: he understood how such a type of person would inevitably, with all of his &lt;em&gt;vis inertiae&lt;/em&gt;,13 have to roll into a faith that promises to &lt;em&gt;prevent&lt;/em&gt; the return of earthly toil (i.e. of work and action in general), – this ‘understanding’ was his genius. The religion-founder must be psychologically infallible in his knowledge of a certain average breed of souls who have not yet &lt;em&gt;recognized&lt;/em&gt; one another as allies. He is the one who brings them together; and to that extent, the establishment of a religion always turns into a long festival of recognition. –&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>354</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/354/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/354/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On ‘the genius of the species’.&lt;/em&gt; – The problem of consciousness (or rather, of becoming conscious of something) first confronts us when we begin to realize how much we can do without it; and now we are brought to this initial realization by physiology and natural history (which have thus required two hundred years to catch up with &lt;em&gt;Leibniz’s&lt;/em&gt; precocious suspicion).14 For we could think, feel, will, remember, and also ‘act’ in every sense of the term, and yet none of all this would have to ‘enter our consciousness’ (as one says figuratively). All of life would be possible without, as it were, seeing itself in the mirror; and still today, the predominant part of our lives actually unfolds without this mirroring – of course also our thinking, feeling, and willing lives, insulting as it may sound to an older philosopher. &lt;em&gt;To what end&lt;/em&gt; does consciousness exist at all when it is basically superfluous? If one is willing to hear my answer and its possibly extravagant conjecture, it seems to me that the subtlety and strength of consciousness is always related to a person’s (or animal’s) &lt;em&gt;ability to communicate;&lt;/em&gt; and the ability to communicate, in turn, to the &lt;em&gt;need to communicate.&lt;/em&gt; The latter should not to be taken to mean that precisely that individual who is a master at expressing his needs and at making them understood must also be the most dependent on others in his needs. But for entire races and lineages, this seems to me to hold: where need and distress have for a long time forced people to communicate, to understand each other swiftly and subtly, there finally exists a surplus of this power and art of expression, a faculty, so to speak, which has slowly accumulated and now waits for an heir to spend it lavishly (the so-called artists are the heirs, as well as the orators, preachers, writers – all of them people who come at the end of a long chain, each of them ‘born late’ in the best sense of the term, and each of them, again, &lt;em&gt;squanderers&lt;/em&gt; by nature). Assuming this observation is correct, I may go on to conjecture that &lt;em&gt;consciousness in general has developed only under the pressure of the need to communicate;&lt;/em&gt; that at the outset, consciousness was necessary, was useful, only between persons (particularly between those who commanded and those who obeyed); and that it has developed only in proportion to that usefulness. Consciousness is really just a net connecting one person with another – only in this capacity did it have to develop; the solitary and predatory person would not have needed it. That our actions, thoughts, feelings, and movements – at least some of them – even enter into consciousness is the result of a terrible ‘must’ which has ruled over man for a long time: as the most endangered animal, he &lt;em&gt;needed&lt;/em&gt; help and protection, he needed his equals; he had to express his neediness and be able to make himself understood – and to do so, he first needed ‘consciousness’, i.e. even to ‘know’ what distressed him, to ‘know’ how he felt, to ‘know’ what he thought. For, once again: man, like every living creature, is constantly thinking but does not know it; the thinking which becomes &lt;em&gt;conscious&lt;/em&gt; is only the smallest part of it, let’s say the shallowest, worst part – for only that conscious thinking &lt;em&gt;takes place in words, that is, in communication symbols;&lt;/em&gt; and this fact discloses the origin of consciousness. In short, the development of language and the development of consciousness (&lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; of reason but strictly of the way in which we become conscious of reason) go hand in hand. One might add that not only language serves as a bridge between persons, but also look, touch, and gesture; without our becoming conscious of our sense impressions, our power to fix them and as it were place them outside of ourselves, has increased in proportion to the need to convey them &lt;em&gt;to others&lt;/em&gt; by means of signs. The sign-inventing person is also the one who becomes ever more acutely conscious of himself; for only as a social animal did man learn to become conscious of himself – he is still doing it, and he is doing it more and more. My idea is clearly that consciousness actually belongs not to man’s existence as an individual but rather to the community- and herd-aspects of his nature; that accordingly, it is finely developed only in relation to its usefulness to community or herd; and that consequently each of us, even with the best will in the world to &lt;em&gt;understand&lt;/em&gt; ourselves as individually as possible, ‘to know ourselves’, will always bring to consciousness precisely that in ourselves which is ‘non-individual’, that which is ‘average’; that due to the nature of consciousness – to the ‘genius of the species’ governing it – our thoughts themselves are continually as it were &lt;em&gt;outvoted&lt;/em&gt; and translated back into the herd perspective. At bottom, all our actions are incomparably and utterly personal, unique, and boundlessly individual, there is no doubt; but as soon as we translate them into consciousness, &lt;em&gt;they no longer seem to be&lt;/em&gt;&amp;hellip;This is what &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; consider to be true phenomenalism and perspectivism: that due to the nature of &lt;em&gt;animal consciousness,&lt;/em&gt; the world of which we can become conscious is merely a surface- and sign-world, a world turned into generalities and thereby debased to its lowest common denominator, – that everything which enters consciousness thereby &lt;em&gt;becomes&lt;/em&gt; shallow, thin, relatively stupid, general, a sign, a herd-mark; that all becoming conscious involves a vast and thorough corruption, falsification, superficialization, and generalization. In the end, the growing consciousness is a danger; and he who lives among the most conscious Europeans even knows it is a sickness. As one might guess, it is not the opposition between subject and object which concerns me here; I leave that distinction to those epistemologists who have got tangled up in the snares of grammar (of folk metaphysics). Even less am I concerned with the opposition between ‘thing in itself’ and appearance: for we ‘know’ far too little to even be entitled to &lt;em&gt;make&lt;/em&gt; that distinction. We simply have no organ for &lt;em&gt;knowing,&lt;/em&gt; for ‘truth’: we ‘know’ (or believe or imagine) exactly as much as is &lt;em&gt;useful&lt;/em&gt; to the human herd, to the species: and even what is here called ‘usefulness’ is finally also just a belief, a fiction, and perhaps just that supremely fatal stupidity of which we some day will perish.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>355</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/355/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/355/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The origin of our concept of ‘knowledge’&lt;/em&gt;. – I take this explanation from the street; I heard one of the common people say ‘he knew me right away’ – and I asked myself: what do the people actually take knowledge to be? what do they want when they want ‘knowledge’? Nothing more than this: something unfamiliar is to be traced back to something &lt;em&gt;familiar.&lt;/em&gt; And we philosophers – have we really meant anything &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; by knowledge? The familiar means what we are used to, so that we no longer marvel at it; the commonplace; some rule in which we are stuck; each and every thing that makes us feel at home: – And isn’t our need for knowledge precisely this need for the familiar, the will to uncover among everything strange, unusual, and doubtful something which no longer unsettles us? Is it not the &lt;em&gt;instinct of fear&lt;/em&gt; that bids us to know? And isn’t the rejoicing of the person who attains knowledge just rejoicing from a regained sense of security?&amp;hellip;Take the philosopher who imagined the world to be ‘known’ when he had reduced it to the ‘idea’; wasn’t it precisely because the ‘idea’ was so familiar to him and he was so used to it? because he no longer feared the ‘idea’? – How little these men of knowledge demand! Just look at their principles and their solutions to the world riddle with this in mind! When they find something in, under, or behind things which unfortunately happens to be very familiar to us, such as our multiplication table or our logic or our willing and desiring, how happy they are right away! For ‘what is familiar is known’: on this they agree. Even the most cautious among them assume that the familiar can at least be &lt;em&gt;more easily known&lt;/em&gt; than the strange; that for example sound method demands that we start from the ‘inner world’, from the ‘facts of consciousness’, because this world is &lt;em&gt;more familiar to us.&lt;/em&gt; Error of errors! The familiar is what we are used to, and what we are used to is the most difficult to ‘know’ – that is, to view as a problem, to see as strange, as distant, as ‘outside us’&amp;hellip;The great certainty of the natural sciences in comparison with psychology and the critique of the elements of consciousness – with the &lt;em&gt;unnatural&lt;/em&gt; sciences, one might almost say – rests precisely on the fact that they take the &lt;em&gt;strange&lt;/em&gt; as their object, while it is nearly contradictory and absurd even to &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to take the not-strange as one’s object&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>356</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/356/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/356/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The extent to which things will become ever more ‘artistic’ in Europe.&lt;/em&gt; – Even today, in this transitional period in which so many forms of coercion have lost their power, the need to make a living still forces nearly all European men to adopt a particular role – their so-called profession. A few retain the freedom, an apparent freedom, to choose this role themselves; for most of them it is chosen. The result is strange enough. Almost all Europeans, at an advanced age, confuse themselves with their role; they become the victims of their ‘good performance’; they themselves have forgotten how much they were determined by accidents, moods, and arbitrariness at the time that their ‘profession’ was decided – and how many other roles they may have been &lt;em&gt;able&lt;/em&gt; to play; for now it is too late! Upon deeper consideration, the role has actually &lt;em&gt;become&lt;/em&gt; character; and artifice, nature. There were times when men believed with unyielding confidence, even with piety, in their predestination for just this business, just this way of making a living, and utterly refused to acknowledge the element of accident, role, and caprice. With the help of this faith, estates, guilds, and inherited trade privileges were able to establish those monsters, the broad-based social pyramids that distinguished the middle ages and to which one can credit at least one thing: durability (and durability is a first-rank value on earth). But there are contrary ages, the truly democratic ones, in which people unlearn this faith and a certain audacious faith and opposite viewpoint moves steadily into the foreground – the Athenian faith that first became noticeable in the Periclean age;15 the American faith which is increasingly becoming the European faith as well, where the individual is convinced he can do just about anything &lt;em&gt;and is up to playing any role;&lt;/em&gt; and everyone experiments with himself, improvises, experiments again, enjoys experimenting, where all nature ends and becomes art&amp;hellip;When the Greeks had fully accepted this &lt;em&gt;faith in roles&lt;/em&gt; – the faith of artistes, if you will – they underwent, as is well known, step by step an odd metamorphosis that is not in every respect worthy of imitation: &lt;em&gt;they really became actors;&lt;/em&gt; as such they captivated and overcame the whole world – finally even the ‘power that overcame the whole world’ itself (for it was not, as innocents tend to say, Greek culture that conquered Rome, but the &lt;em&gt;graeculus histrio16).&lt;/em&gt; But what I fear, what even today one could grasp with one’s hands if one felt like grasping it, is that we modern men are pretty much on the same road; and every time man starts to discover the extent to which he is playing a role and the extent to which he &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be an actor, he &lt;em&gt;becomes&lt;/em&gt; an actor&amp;hellip;With this, a new human flora and fauna emerges that cannot grow in firmer and more limited ages – or that would at least be formally condemned and suspected of lacking honour; it is thus that the most interesting and maddest ages always emerge, in which ‘the actors’, &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; types of actors, are the real masters. Precisely because of this, another human type becomes ever more disadvantaged and is finally made impossible; above all, the great ‘architects’: the strength to build is now paralysed; the courage to make far-reaching plans is discouraged; the organizational geniuses become scarce – who still dares to undertake works that would &lt;em&gt;require&lt;/em&gt; millennia to complete? For what is dying out is that fundamental faith on the basis of which someone could calculate, promise, anticipate the future in a plan on that grand scale, and sacrifice the future to his plan – namely, the basic faith that man has worth and sense only in so far as he is &lt;em&gt;a stone in a great edifice;&lt;/em&gt; to this end he must be &lt;em&gt;firm&lt;/em&gt; above all, a ‘stone’&amp;hellip;above all not an actor! To put it briefly – oh, people will keep silent about it for a long time! – what from now on will never again be built, &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; never again be built, is – a society in the old sense of the term; to build that, everything is lacking, mainly the material. &lt;em&gt;We are all no longer material for a society;&lt;/em&gt; this is a timely truth! It is a matter of indifference to me that at present the most shortsighted, perhaps the most honest, at any rate the noisiest human type that we have today – our good socialists – believe, hope, dream, and above all shout and write pretty much the opposite. For even now one reads their slogan for the future ‘free society’ on all tables and walls. Free society? Well, well! But surely you know, gentlemen, what one needs to build that? Wooden iron!17 The famous wooden iron! And it need not even be wooden&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>357</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/357/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/357/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On the old problem: ‘What is German?’&lt;/em&gt; – Add up for yourself the real achievements in philosophical thinking that can be attributed to Germans: is there any legitimate sense in which one can credit them to the entire race? Can we say that they are also the work of the ‘German soul’, or at least symptoms of it in the same sense in which we are accustomed to take Plato’s ideomania, his nearly religious lunacy about forms, as a development and testimony of ‘the Greek soul’? Or would the opposite be true? Would they be just so individual, just so much &lt;em&gt;exceptions&lt;/em&gt; to the spirit of the race as was, for instance, Goethe’s paganism with a good conscience? Or as is Bismarck’s Machiavellianism with a good conscience, his so-called &lt;em&gt;Realpolitik,&lt;/em&gt; among Germans? Might our philosophers perhaps even contradict the &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; of the ‘German soul’? In short, were the German philosophers really – philosophical &lt;em&gt;Germans?&lt;/em&gt; I recall three cases. First, &lt;em&gt;Leibniz’s&lt;/em&gt; incomparable insight18 that has been vindicated not only against Descartes but also against everyone who had philosophized before him – that consciousness (&lt;em&gt;Bewutheit&lt;/em&gt;)19 is merely an &lt;em&gt;accidens&lt;/em&gt;20 of the power of representation (&lt;em&gt;Vorstellung&lt;/em&gt;) and &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; its necessary and essential attribute; so that what we call consciousness (&lt;em&gt;Bewutsein&lt;/em&gt;) constitutes only one state of our spiritual and psychic world (perhaps a sick state) and &lt;em&gt;by no means the whole of it&lt;/em&gt; – is there something German to this idea, the profundity of which has not been exhausted to this day? Is there reason to surmise that no Latin could easily have thought of this reversal of appearances? For it is a reversal. Let us recall, secondly, &lt;em&gt;Kant’s&lt;/em&gt; colossal question mark that he placed on the concept ‘causality’21 – without, like Hume, doubting its legitimacy altogether: he started much more cautiously to delimit the realm in which this concept makes any sense whatsoever (and to this day we have not yet come to terms with this marking out of the boundaries). Let us take, thirdly, &lt;em&gt;Hegel’s&lt;/em&gt; astonishing move, with which he struck through all logical habits and indulgences when he dared to teach that species concepts develop *out of each other:*22 with this proposition the minds of Europe were preformed for the last great scientific movement, Darwinism – for without Hegel there could be no Darwin. Is there anything German in this Hegelian innovation which first introduced the decisive concept of ‘development’ into science? Yes, without any doubt: in all three cases we feel that something in ourselves has been ‘uncovered’ and figured out, and we are grateful and at the same time surprised. Each of these three propositions is a thoughtful piece of German self-knowledge, self-experience, and self-conception. ‘Our inner world is much richer, more comprehensive, more hidden’, we feel with Leibniz. As Germans, we doubt with Kant the ultimate validity of the discoveries of the natural sciences and altogether of everything that &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be known &lt;em&gt;causaliter&lt;/em&gt;23 – what is knowable already seems to us of &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; value on that account. We Germans are Hegelians even had there been no Hegel, insofar as we (as opposed to all Latins) instinctively attribute a deeper meaning and greater value to becoming and development than to what ‘is’; we hardly believe in the justification of the concept ‘being’ – and also insofar as we are not inclined to concede that our human logic is logic as such or the only kind of logic (we would rather persuade ourselves that it is only a special case and perhaps one of the oddest and stupidest). A fourth question would be whether &lt;em&gt;Schopenhauer,&lt;/em&gt; too, with his pessimism – that is, the problem of the &lt;em&gt;value of existence&lt;/em&gt;24 – had to be precisely a German. I believe not. The event &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; which this problem was to be expected with certainty, so that an astronomer of the soul could have calculated the very day and hour for it – the decline of the faith in the Christian god, the triumph of scientific atheism – is a pan-European event in which all races had their share and for which all deserve credit and honour. Conversely, one might charge precisely the Germans – those Germans who were contemporaries of Schopenhauer – with having &lt;em&gt;delayed&lt;/em&gt; this triumph of atheism most dangerously for the longest time. Hegel in particular was a delayer par excellence, in accordance with his grandiose attempt to persuade us of the divinity of existence, appealing as a last resort to our sixth sense, ‘the historical sense’. As a philosopher, Schopenhauer was the &lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt; admitted and uncompromising atheist among us Germans: this was the background of his enmity towards Hegel. The ungodliness of existence counted for him as something given, palpable, indisputable; he always lost his philosopher’s composure and became indignant when he saw anyone hesitate or beat around the bush on this point. This is the locus of his whole integrity; unconditional and honest atheism is simply the &lt;em&gt;presupposition&lt;/em&gt; of his way of putting the problem, as a victory of the European conscience won finally and with great difficulty; as the most fateful act of two thousand years of discipline for truth that in the end forbids itself the &lt;em&gt;lie&lt;/em&gt; of faith in God&amp;hellip;One can see &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; it was that actually triumphed over the Christian god: Christian morality itself, the concept of truthfulness that was taken ever more rigorously; the father confessor’s refinement of the Christian conscience, translated and sublimated into a scientific conscience, into intellectual cleanliness at any price. Looking at nature as if it were proof of the goodness and care of a god; interpreting history in honour of some divine reason, as a continual testimony of a moral world order and ultimate moral purposes; interpreting one’s own experiences as pious people have long interpreted theirs, as if everything were providential, a hint, designed and ordained for the sake of salvation of the soul – that is &lt;em&gt;over&lt;/em&gt; now; that has conscience &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; it; every refined conscience considers it to be indecent, dishonest, a form of mendacity, effeminacy, weakness, cowardice. With this severity, if with anything, we are simply &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; Europeans and heirs of Europe’s longest and most courageous self-overcoming. As we thus reject Christian interpretation and condemn its ‘meaning’ as counterfeit, &lt;em&gt;Schopenhauer’s&lt;/em&gt; question immediately comes at us in a terrifying way: &lt;em&gt;Does existence have any meaning at all?&lt;/em&gt; A few centuries will be needed before this question can ever be heard completely and in its full depth. What Schopenhauer himself said in answer to this question was – forgive me – something hasty, youthful, a mere compromise, a way of remaining and staying stuck in precisely those Christian and ascetic moral perspectives in which one had &lt;em&gt;renounced faith&lt;/em&gt; along with the faith in God. But he &lt;em&gt;posed&lt;/em&gt; the question – as a good European, as I said before, and &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; as a German. Or is it possible that at least the manner in which the Germans appropriated Schopenhauer’s question proves that the Germans did have an inner affinity and relation, preparation, and &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; for this problem? That after Schopenhauer one thought and printed things in Germany, too – by the way, late enough – about the problem he had posed is certainly not sufficient to decide in favour of this closer affinity. One might rather adduce the peculiar &lt;em&gt;ineptitude&lt;/em&gt; of this post-Schopenhauerian pessimism &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; the thesis; clearly the Germans did not behave in this affair as if they were in their element. This is by no means an allusion to Eduard von Hartmann.25 On the contrary, to this day I have not shaken off my old suspicion that he is too &lt;em&gt;apt&lt;/em&gt; for us. I mean that he may have been a real rogue from the start who perhaps made fun not only of German pessimism – but in the end he might even reveal to the Germans in his last will and testament to what extent it was possible to make fools of them, even in an era of economic initiative and success.26 But let me ask you: should we perhaps consider that old humming-top Bahnsen27 as a credit to the Germans, seeing how voluptuously he revolved his life around his real-dialectical misery and ‘personal bad luck’? Might precisely that be German? (I herewith recommend his writings to the end for which I have used them myself, as an anti-pessimistic diet, especially on account of their &lt;em&gt;elegantiae psychologicae,28&lt;/em&gt; with which, I think, they should be effective also for the most constipated bowels and temperaments.) Or could one count such dilettantes and old spinsters as that mawkish apostle of virginity, Mainlander,29 as a genuine German? In the end he must have been a Jew (all Jews become mawkish when they moralize). Neither Bahnsen nor Mainlander, nor even Eduard von Hartmann, gives us any clear evidence regarding the question whether Schopenhauer’s pessimism, his horrified look into a de-deified world that had become stupid, blind, crazed, and questionable, his &lt;em&gt;honest&lt;/em&gt; horror&amp;hellip;was not merely an exception among Germans but a &lt;em&gt;German&lt;/em&gt; event. Everything else that is otherwise in the foreground – our brave politics, our merry fatherlandishness which resolutely enough consider all matters with a view to a not very philosophical principle (‘Deutschland, Deutschland über alles’30), i.e. *sub specie speciei,*31 namely the German species, bears emphatic witness to the opposite. No, the Germans of today are &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; pessimists. And Schopenhauer was a pessimist, to repeat, as a good European and &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; as a German. –&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>358</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/358/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/358/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The peasant rebellion of the spirit.&lt;/em&gt; – We Europeans confront a world of tremendous ruins. A few things are still towering; much looks decayed and uncanny, while most things are already lying on the ground: picturesque enough – where has one ever seen more beautiful ruins? – and overgrown by large and small weeds. The Church is this city of decline: we see the religious society of Christianity shaken to its lowest foundations; faith in God has collapsed; faith in the Christian-ascetic ideal is still fighting its last battle. An edifice such as Christianity that had been built so carefully over such a long period – it was the last Roman construction! – could of course not be destroyed all at once. All kinds of earthquakes had to shake it; all kinds of minds (&lt;em&gt;Geist&lt;/em&gt;) that drill, dig, gnaw, and moisten have had to help. But the oddest thing is: those who exerted themselves the most to preserve and conserve Christianity have become its best destroyers – the Germans. It seems that the Germans do not understand the nature of a church. Are they not spiritual enough for that? Not mistrustful enough? The edifice of the Church rests, at any rate, on a &lt;em&gt;Southern&lt;/em&gt; freedom and liberality of the mind as well as on a Southern suspicion against nature, man, and spirit; it rests on an altogether different knowledge and experience of man than the North has had. The Lutheran Reformation was, in its whole breadth, the indignation of simplicity against ‘multiplicity’, to speak cautiously, a crude, naively narrow-minded misunderstanding in which there is much to forgive. One failed to understand the expression of a &lt;em&gt;victorious&lt;/em&gt; church and saw only corruption; one misunderstood the noble scepticism, that &lt;em&gt;luxury&lt;/em&gt; of scepticism and tolerance which every victorious, self-confident power permits itself&amp;hellip;Today one overlooks easily enough how in all cardinal questions of power Luther was dangerously short-sighted, superficial, incautious – mainly as a man of the common people who lacked any inheritance from a ruling caste and instinct for power; thus his work, his will to restore that work of the Romans only became the beginning of a work of destruction, without his wanting and knowing it. With honest wrath he unravelled, he tore up what the old spider had woven so carefully for such a long time. He surrendered the holy books to everyone – thus they finally ended up in the hands of the philologists, who are the destroyers of every faith that rests on books. He destroyed the concept of the ‘Church’ by throwing away the belief in the inspiration of the church councils; for the concept of the ‘Church’ retains power only under the condition that the inspiring spirit that founded the Church still lives in, builds, and continues to build its house. He gave back to the priest sexual intercourse with a woman; but three-quarters of the reverence of which the people, especially the women of the people, are capable rests on the faith that a person who is an exception in this regard will be an exception in other regards as well – it is here precisely that the popular faith in something superhuman in man, in the miracle, in the redeeming god in man, finds its subtlest and most insidious advocate. Having given the priest woman, Luther had to &lt;em&gt;take&lt;/em&gt; from him auricular confession; that was psychologically right, but with that development the Christian priest was basically abolished, since his deepest utility has always been that he was a holy ear, a silent well, a grave for secrets. ‘Everyone his own priest’ – behind such formulas and their peasant cunning was hidden in Luther the abysmal hatred of ‘the higher human beings’ and the dominion of ‘the higher human beings’ as conceived by the Church; he smashed an ideal that he could not attain, while he seemed to fight and abhor the degeneration of this ideal. Actually he, the impossible monk, pushed away the &lt;em&gt;dominion&lt;/em&gt; of the *homines religiosi,*32 and thus he himself brought about within the &lt;em&gt;ecclesiastical&lt;/em&gt; social order what in relation to the &lt;em&gt;civil&lt;/em&gt; social order he attacked so intolerantly – a ‘peasants’ rebellion’. What grew out of his Reformation afterwards, good as well as bad, might be roughly calculated today; but who would be naive enough to praise or blame Luther on account of these consequences? He is innocent of everything; he did not know what he was doing. The flattening of the European mind, particularly in the North – its &lt;em&gt;becoming more good-natured,&lt;/em&gt; if one prefers a moral term – advanced a large step with the Lutheran Reformation, there is no doubt; and owing to it also the flexibility and restlessness of the mind, its thirst for independence, its faith in a right to liberty, its ‘naturalness’. If in connection with this last point one wanted to give it the credit for having prepared and favoured what we today honour as ‘modern science’, one must surely add that it also shares the blame for the degeneration of the modern scholar, for his lack of reverence, shame, and depth, for the whole naive guilelessness and conventionality in matters of knowledge – in short for that &lt;em&gt;plebeianism of the spirit&lt;/em&gt; that is peculiar to the last two centuries and from which even pessimism has not yet liberated us. ‘Modern ideas’ also belong to this peasant rebellion of the North against the colder, more ambiguous, mistrustful spirit of the South that built its greatest monument in the Christian Church. Let us not forget in the end what a church is, specifically as opposed to any ‘state’. A church is above all a structure for ruling that secures the highest rank to the &lt;em&gt;more spiritual&lt;/em&gt; human beings and that &lt;em&gt;believes&lt;/em&gt; in the power of spirituality to the extent of forbidding itself the use of all cruder instruments of force; and on that score alone the Church is under all circumstances a &lt;em&gt;nobler&lt;/em&gt; institution than the state.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>359</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/359/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/359/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The revenge against the spirit and other ulterior motives of morality.&lt;/em&gt; – Morality – where do you suppose that it finds its most dangerous and insidious advocates?&amp;hellip;There is a human being who has turned out badly, who does not have spirit enough to be able to enjoy it and just enough education to know this; bored, weary, a self-despiser; wealthy through inheritance, he is deprived even of the last comfort, ‘the blessings of work’, self-forgetfulness in ‘daily labour’. Such a person who is basically ashamed of his existence – perhaps he also harbours a few small vices – and on the other hand cannot keep himself from becoming more spoiled and touchy as a result of reading books he has no right to or through more spiritual company than he can digest: such a thoroughly poisoned human being – for spirit becomes poison, education becomes poison; ownership becomes poison, loneliness becomes poison in persons who have turned out badly in this way – eventually ends up in a state of habitual revenge, the will to revenge&amp;hellip;&lt;em&gt;What&lt;/em&gt; do you think he finds necessary, absolutely necessary, to give himself in his own eyes the appearance of superiority over more spiritual people and to obtain the pleasure of an &lt;em&gt;accomplished revenge&lt;/em&gt; at least in his own imagination? Always &lt;em&gt;morality;&lt;/em&gt; you can bet on that. Always big moral words. Always the boom-boom of justice, wisdom, holiness, virtue. Always the Stoicism of gesture (how well Stoicism conceals what one lacks!). Always the cloak of prudent silence, of affability, of mildness, and whatever the other idealistic cloaks may be called under which incurable self-despisers, as well as the incurably vain, go about. Do not misunderstand me: among such born &lt;em&gt;enemies of the spirit&lt;/em&gt; emerges occasionally the rare piece of humanity that the people revere under such names as saint and sage. From among such men come those monsters of morality who make noise, who make history – St Augustine33 is among them. Fear of spirit, revenge against spirit – oh how often have these propelling vices become the roots of virtues! Indeed, &lt;em&gt;become&lt;/em&gt; virtues! And, as a question asked in confidence: even that philosopher’s claim to &lt;em&gt;wisdom&lt;/em&gt; which has been made here and there on earth; the maddest and most immodest of all claims – was it not always, in India as well as in Greece, &lt;em&gt;primarily a hiding place?&lt;/em&gt; At times perhaps a hiding place chosen with pedagogical intent, which hallows so many lies; one has a tender regard for those who are still becoming, growing – for disciples who must often be defended against themselves through faith in a person (through an error)&amp;hellip;In most cases, however, it is a hiding place in which the philosopher saves himself owing to weariness, age, growing cold, hardening – as a wisdom of that instinct which the animals have before death – they go off alone, become silent, choose solitude, crawl into caves, become &lt;em&gt;wise&lt;/em&gt;&amp;hellip;What? Wisdom as a hiding place in which the philosopher hides himself from – spirit?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>360</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/360/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/360/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Two kinds of causes that are often confused.&lt;/em&gt; – This seems to me to be one of my most essential steps forward: I learned to distinguish the cause of acting from the cause of acting in a certain way, in a certain direction, with a certain goal. The first kind of cause is a quantum of dammed-up energy waiting to be used somehow, for something; the second kind, by contrast, is something quite insignificant, mostly a small accident in accordance with which this quantum ‘discharges’ itself in one particular way: the match versus the powder keg. Among these small accidents and matches I consider all so-called ‘purposes’ as well as the even more so-called ‘vocations’: they are relatively random, arbitrary, nearly indifferent in relation to the enormous force of energy that presses on, as I said, to be used up somehow. The usual view is different: one is used to seeing the &lt;em&gt;driving&lt;/em&gt; force precisely in the goals (purposes, professions, etc.), in keeping with a very ancient error; but it is only the &lt;em&gt;directing&lt;/em&gt; force – one has mistaken the helmsman for the stream. And not even always the helmsman, the directing force&amp;hellip;Is the ‘goal’, the ‘purpose’, not often enough a beautifying pretext, a self-deception of vanity after the fact that does not want to acknowledge that the ship is &lt;em&gt;following&lt;/em&gt; the current into which it has entered accidentally? That it ‘wills’ to go that way &lt;em&gt;because it – must?&lt;/em&gt; That it certainly has a direction but – no helmsman whatsoever? We still need a critique of the concept of ‘purpose’.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>361</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/361/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/361/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On the problem of the actor.&lt;/em&gt; – The problem of the actor has troubled me for a very long time; I was unsure (and still sometimes am) whether it is only from this angle that one can approach the dangerous concept of the ‘artist’ – a concept that has heretofore been treated with unpardonable generosity. Falseness with a good conscience; the delight in pretence erupting as a power that pushes aside, floods, and at times extinguishes one’s so-called ‘character’; the inner longing for a role and mask, for an &lt;em&gt;appearance (Schein);&lt;/em&gt; an excess of capacities for all kinds of adaptation that can no longer be satisfied in the service of the nearest, most narrowly construed utility – perhaps all of this is distinctive not &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; of the actor? Such an instinct will have developed most easily in lower-class families who had to survive under fluctuating pressures and coercions, in deep dependency; who had nimbly to cut their coats according to their cloth, always readapting to new circumstances, always having to act and pose differently until they slowly learned to turn their coats with &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; wind and thus almost turned into coats themselves – and masters of an art which they have fully assimilated so that it is an integral part of themselves, that art of perpetually playing at self-concealment which in animals we call mimicry – until finally this capacity, accumulated from generation to generation, becomes domineering, unreasonable, intractable, an instinct that learns to command other instincts and produces the actor, the ‘artist’ (the buffoon, the teller of lies, the fool, the jester, the clown primarily, but also the classical servant, Gil Blas;34 for it is in such types that we find the prehistory of the artist and often enough even of ‘genius’). In more elevated social conditions, too, a similar human type develops under similar pressures; only here, the histrionic instinct is usually just barely kept in check by another instinct, as in the case of ‘diplomats’. Incidentally, I would think that a good diplomat would be free at any time to become a good actor – provided, of course, that he were ‘free’ to do this. But as for the &lt;em&gt;Jews,&lt;/em&gt; that people possessing the art of adaptability par excellence, one might, according to this train of thought, immediately see in them a world-historical organization for the cultivation of actors, a veritable breeding ground for actors; and indeed it is really high time to ask: what good actor today is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; – a Jew? Also the Jew as a born literary man, as the true master of the European press, exercises this power by virtue of his histrionic ability, for the literary man is essentially an actor: he plays the ‘expert’, the ‘specialist’. Finally, &lt;em&gt;women:&lt;/em&gt; consider the whole history of women – &lt;em&gt;mustn’t&lt;/em&gt; they be actresses first and foremost? Listen to doctors who have hypnotized womenfolk; finally, love them – let yourself be ‘hypnotized’ by them! What is always the result? That they try to be ‘taken for something’ even when they are being taken&amp;hellip; Woman is so artistic&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>362</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/362/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/362/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our faith in the masculinization of Europe.&lt;/em&gt; – We owe it to Napoleon (and not at all to the French Revolution, which aimed at the ‘brotherhood’ of peoples and a general, blooming exchange of hearts) that a few warlike centuries, incomparable to any other in history, are likely to follow in succession – in short, that we have entered the &lt;em&gt;classic age of war,&lt;/em&gt; of sophisticated yet popular war on the largest scale (in terms of weapons, talents, discipline); all coming ages will look back on this kind of war with envy and deep respect as something perfect, for the national movement out of which this war glory is growing is merely the countershock against Napoleon and would not exist without Napoleon. He should be credited one day for having enabled &lt;em&gt;man&lt;/em&gt; in Europe to become the master over the businessman and the philistine – perhaps even over ‘woman’, who has been spoiled by Christianity and the enthusiastic spirit of the eighteenth century, and even more by ‘modern ideas’. Napoleon, who saw something of a personal enemy in modern ideas and in civilization itself,35 proved through this enmity to be one of the greatest continuators of the Renaissance: he brought back a whole piece, a block of granite, perhaps the decisive one, of antiquity’s essence. And who knows whether this piece of antiquity’s essence will finally again become master of the national movement, and whether it must not make itself the heir and protractor in an &lt;em&gt;affirmative&lt;/em&gt; sense of Napoleon – who wanted one Europe, as is known, and wanted it as &lt;em&gt;mistress of the earth.&lt;/em&gt; –&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>363</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/363/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/363/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How each sex has its own prejudice about love.&lt;/em&gt; – Despite all the concessions I am willing to make to the prejudice favouring monogamy, I will never admit talk of &lt;em&gt;equal&lt;/em&gt; rights for man and woman in love: there are none. For man and woman have different conceptions of love – and it belongs to the conditions of love in each sex that &lt;em&gt;neither&lt;/em&gt; presupposes the same feeling, the same concept of ‘love’ in the other. What woman means by love is clear enough: total devotion (and not mere surrender) with soul and body, without any consideration or reserve, rather with shame and horror at the thought of a devotion that might be tied to special clauses or conditions. In this absence of conditions her love is a &lt;em&gt;faith:&lt;/em&gt; woman has no other. Man, when he loves a woman, &lt;em&gt;wants&lt;/em&gt; precisely this love from her and is thus himself as far as can be from the presupposition of female love; supposing, however, that there should also be men to whom the desire for complete surrender is not alien, well, then they are – not men. A man who loves like a woman becomes a slave, but a woman who loves like a woman becomes a &lt;em&gt;more perfect&lt;/em&gt; woman&amp;hellip; The passion of a woman, in its unconditional renunciation of her own rights, presupposes precisely that on the other side there is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; an equal pathos, not an equal will to renunciation; for if both should renounce themselves from love, the result would be – well, I don’t know, maybe an empty space? Woman wants to be taken, adopted as a possession, wants to be absorbed in the concept ‘possession’, ‘possessed’; consequently, she wants someone who &lt;em&gt;takes,&lt;/em&gt; who does not himself give or give himself away; who on the contrary is supposed precisely to be made richer in ‘himself’ – through the increase in strength, happiness, and faith given him by the woman who gives herself. Woman gives herself away; man takes more – I do not believe one can get around this natural opposition through any social contracts or with the best will to justice, desirable as it may be not to remind oneself constantly how harsh, terrible, enigmatic, and immoral this antagonism is. For love, when one considers it in its perfect, fully developed state, is nature, and nature is eternally ‘immoral’. Faithfulness is then implicit in woman’s love, and follows from its definition; in a man’s case it &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; perhaps arise as a consequence of his love, for instance as gratitude or as an idiosyncrasy of taste, a so-called ‘elective affinity’, but it does not belong to the &lt;em&gt;essence&lt;/em&gt; of his love. Indeed this is so little the case that one might almost speak with some justification of a natural back-and-forth between love and faithfulness in a man: his love is desire for possession and &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a renunciation or giving away, but with &lt;em&gt;possession&lt;/em&gt; desire for possession always ceases&amp;hellip; In fact it is the highly refined and suspicious thirst for possession on the part of a man who rarely and only after a long time admits that he has ‘possession’, which allows his love to endure. Thus it is possible that his love continues to grow even after surrender – he will not easily admit that a woman has nothing more to ‘give up’ to him.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>364</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/364/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/364/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The hermit speaks.&lt;/em&gt; – The art of dealing with people depends essentially on the skill (requiring much practice) to accept and eat a meal prepared in a kitchen you don’t trust. If you come to the table ravenous, all is easy (‘the worst company makes itself &lt;em&gt;felt&lt;/em&gt;’ – as Mephistopheles says);36 but one is never that hungry when one needs to be! Oh, how hard it is to digest one’s fellow men! First principle: as in the face of misfortune, to engage your courage, to spring boldly to action, to admire yourself in the process, to sink your teeth into your reluctance, to swallow your disgust. Second principle: to ‘improve’ your fellow man, e.g. by praising him so as to make him start sweating out his pleasure in himself, or by taking hold of a corner of his good or ‘interesting’ qualities and pulling at it until all the virtue comes out and you can hide your fellow man in its folds. Third principle: self-hypnosis. To fixate on your object of association as if on a glass button until you stop feeling pleasure and displeasure in this activity and fall asleep without noticing it, become rigid, and attain equanimity: a home remedy amply tested in marriage and friendship, praised as indispensable but not yet scientifically analysed. Its popular name is – patience.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>365</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/365/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/365/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The hermit speaks again.&lt;/em&gt; – We, too, deal with ‘people’; we, too, modestly don the cloak in which (&lt;em&gt;as&lt;/em&gt; which) others know us, respect us, seek us, and so we appear in company, i.e. among others who are disguised but don’t want to admit it. Like all clever masks we, too, politely prop up a chair against the door when confronted with curiosity about anything but our ‘cloak’. But there are other ways and tricks for ‘wandering amongst’, for ‘associating with’, people: for instance, as a ghost – which is highly advisable if one desires to get rid of them quickly and make them afraid. Example: others reach for us and can’t get a hold of us. That’s frightening. Or we enter through a closed door. Or when all the lights are out. Or when we’re already dead. The latter is the trick of &lt;em&gt;posthumous&lt;/em&gt; people par excellence. (‘And what were you thinking?’ one of them once said impatiently; ‘Would we wish to endure this estrangement, coldness, and sepulchral silence enveloping us, this entire subterranean, hidden, mute, undiscovered loneliness that we call life but might as well be called death unless we knew what will &lt;em&gt;become&lt;/em&gt; of us and that it is only after death that we come into &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; life and become alive oh, very much alive, we posthumous ones!’)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>366</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/366/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/366/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Faced with a scholarly book.&lt;/em&gt; – We are not among those who have ideas only between books, stimulated by books – our habit is to think outdoors, walking, jumping, climbing, dancing, preferably on lonely mountains or right by the sea where even the paths become thoughtful. Our first question about the value of a book, a person, or a piece of music is: ‘Can they walk?’ Even more, ‘Can they dance?’ We rarely read; but are none the worse on that account – and oh, how quickly we guess how someone has come to his ideas; whether seated before the inkwell, stomach clenched, head bowed over the paper; and oh, how soon we’re done with his book! Cramped intestines betray themselves – you can bet on it – no less than stuffy air, closed ceilings, cramped spaces. – Those were my feelings just now as I closed a decent, scholarly book – grateful, very grateful, but also relieved&amp;hellip; In a scholar’s book there is nearly always something oppressive, oppressed: the ‘specialist’ emerges somehow – his eagerness, his seriousness, his ire, his overestimation of the nook in which he sits and spins, his hunchback – every specialist has his hump. Every scholarly book also reflects a soul that has become crooked; every craft makes crooked. Look at the friends of your youth again, after they have taken possession of their speciality (&lt;em&gt;Wissenschaft&lt;/em&gt;) Alas, in every case the reverse has also taken place! How they are now for all time possessed and obsessed by it! Grown into their corner, squashed beyond recognition, unfree, unstable, completely emaciated and jagged except for one spot that is paradigmatically round – one is moved and silenced when one sees them again that way. Above every craft, even one with a golden floor, is also a leaden ceiling that presses and presses on the soul until it becomes strangely and crookedly pressed. There is nothing to do about this. Don’t think you can evade such crippling through some educational artifice. One pays dearly for any kind of &lt;em&gt;mastery&lt;/em&gt; on earth, where perhaps one pays too dearly for everything; one is master of one’s trade at the price of also being its victim. But you want things to be different – ‘cheaper’, above all more comfortable – not so, my dear contemporaries? Well, if so, you instantly get something different: instead of the craftsman and master, you get the man of letters, the dexterous, ‘polydexterous’ literary man who of course lacks the hunched back – notwithstanding the posture he assumes before you as the shop attendant of spirit and the ‘bearer’ of culture – the literary man of letters, who really &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; nothing but who ‘represents’ nearly everything, who acts and ‘stands in for’ the expert, who takes it upon himself in all modesty to &lt;em&gt;make&lt;/em&gt; himself paid, honoured, and celebrated in place of the expert. No, my scholarly friends, I bless you even for your hunched backs! And for despising, as do I, the ‘literary men’ and culture parasites! And for not knowing how to make a business of the spirit! And for having opinions that cannot be translated into monetary terms! And for not representing anything that you are &lt;em&gt;not!&lt;/em&gt; And because your only desire (&lt;em&gt;Wille&lt;/em&gt;) is to become masters of your craft, with reverence for every type of mastery and competence and with ruthless rejection of anything specious, semi-genuine, meretricious, virtuoso-like, demagogical, or histrionic &lt;em&gt;in litteris et artibus37&lt;/em&gt; – of anything that cannot give you proof of its unconditional &lt;em&gt;probity&lt;/em&gt; in discipline and prior training. (Not even genius can compensate for such a deficiency, however much it may blind people to it. One grasps this once one has watched our most talented painters and musicians up close, who nearly without exception manage through a cunning inventiveness of manners, stop-gap devices, and even principles, to acquire artificially and belatedly the &lt;em&gt;appearance&lt;/em&gt; of such probity, such solidity of schooling and culture – without, of course, managing to deceive themselves, to silence forever their bad conscience. For surely you know? All great contemporary artists suffer from a bad conscience&amp;hellip;)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>367</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/367/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/367/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The first distinction to draw regarding artworks.&lt;/em&gt; – Everything that is thought, written, painted, composed, even built and sculpted, belongs either to monologue art or to art before witnesses. The second category must also include the seemingly monologue art involving faith in God, the entire lyricism of prayer; for solitude does not yet exist to the pious – this invention was first made by us, the godless. I know no deeper distinction in an artist’s entire optics than this: whether he views his budding artwork (‘himself’) from the eye of the witness, or whether he ‘has forgotten the world’, which is the essential feature of all monologue art – it is based &lt;em&gt;on forgetting;&lt;/em&gt; it is the music of forgetting.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>368</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/368/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/368/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The cynic speaks.&lt;/em&gt; – My objections to Wagner’s music are physiological objections: why disguise them with aesthetic formulas? My ‘fact’ is that I stop breathing easily once this music starts affecting me; that my &lt;em&gt;foot&lt;/em&gt; immediately gets angry at it and revolts – it has a need for tempo, dance, march; it demands chiefly from music the raptures found in &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; walking, striding, leaping, and dancing – but doesn’t my stomach protest, too? My heart? My circulation? My intestines? Do I not unnoticeably grow hoarse as I listen? And so I ask myself: what does my whole body actually &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; from music? Its own &lt;em&gt;relief,&lt;/em&gt; I believe, as if all animal functions should be quickened by easy, bold, exuberant, self-assured rhythms; as if iron, leaden life should be gilded by golden, good, tender harmonies. My melancholy wants to rest in the hiding-places and abysses of &lt;em&gt;perfection:&lt;/em&gt; that’s what I need music for. &amp;ldquo;What is the drama to me! The cramps of its moral ecstasies that give the ‘people’ satisfaction! The whole hocus-pocus of gestures of the actor! You will guess that I am essentially anti-theatrical – but Wagner was, conversely, essentially a man of the theatre and an actor, the most enthusiastic mimomaniac that ever existed, also as a musician. And, incidentally, if it was Wagner’s theory that ‘the drama is the end; the music is always merely its means’,38 his &lt;em&gt;practice&lt;/em&gt; was always, from beginning to end, ‘the attitude is the end; the drama, and music, too, is always merely &lt;em&gt;its&lt;/em&gt; means’. Music as a means of clarification, strengthening, internalization of the dramatic gesture and the actor’s appeal to the senses; and the Wagnerian drama a mere occasion for many dramatic attitudes! Beside all other instincts, he had the commanding instinct of a great actor in absolutely everything – and, as I said, also as a musician. I once made this clear to an upright Wagnerian, with some trouble; and I had reasons to add: ‘Do be a bit more honest with yourself – after all, we’re not at the theatre! At the theatre, one is honest only as a mass; as an individual one lies, lies to oneself. One leaves oneself at home when one goes to the theatre; one relinquishes the right to one’s own tongue and choice, to one’s taste, even to one’s courage as one has it and exercises it within one’s own four walls against god and man. No one brings the finest senses of his art to the theatre; nor does the artist who works for the theatre: there, one is people, public, herd, woman, pharisee, voting cattle, democrat, neighbour, fellow man; there, even the most personal conscience is vanquished by the levelling magic of the “greatest number”; there, stupidity breeds lasciviousness and is contagious; there, the “neighbour” reigns; there, one &lt;em&gt;becomes&lt;/em&gt; a neighbour’. (I forgot to mention my enlightened Wagnerian’s retort to the physiological objections: ‘So, you simply aren’t healthy enough for our music?’)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>369</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/369/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/369/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our coexistence.&lt;/em&gt; – Don’t we have to admit to ourselves, we artists, that there exists an uncanny disparity within us; that in an odd way our taste and on the other hand our creative power stand each distinct from the other; each remains the way it is by itself, and each grows by itself; I mean each of these has completely different degrees and &lt;em&gt;tempi&lt;/em&gt; of old, young, ripe, overblown, rotten? A musician, for instance, could spend a lifetime creating things that &lt;em&gt;contradict&lt;/em&gt; what his spoiled listener’s ear, listener’s heart values, savours, prefers – he needn’t even be aware of this contradiction! As experience shows with almost embarrassing regularity, one’s taste can easily outgrow the taste of one’s powers, even without thereby paralysing them and hindering their continued productivity. But the opposite can happen, too – and this is precisely what I’d like to call artists’ attention to. A perpetually creative person, a ‘mother’ type in the grand sense of the term, someone who doesn’t hear or know anything but the pregnancies and child-beds of his spirit anymore, who simply has no time to reflect on himself and on his work and to make comparisons, who no longer wants to exercise his taste and simply forgets it, i.e. lets it stand, lie, or fall – maybe such a person would finally produce works &lt;em&gt;that far excel his own judgement,&lt;/em&gt; so that he utters inanities about them and himself – utters them and believes them. This seems to me to be almost the norm among fertile artists – nobody knows a child less well than his parents – and this is true, to take a colossal example, even in the case of the whole world of Greek art and poetry: it never ‘knew’ what it had done.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>370</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/370/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/370/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What is romanticism?&lt;/em&gt; – It may be recalled, at least among my friends, that initially I approached the modern world with a few crude errors and over-estimations and, in any case, with hope. I understood – on the basis of who knows what personal experiences? – the philosophical pessimism of the nineteenth century as if it were a symptom of a higher force of thought, of more audacious courage, and of more victorious &lt;em&gt;fullness&lt;/em&gt; of life than had characterized the eighteenth century, the age of Hume, Kant, Condillac,39 and the sensualists: thus, tragic insight struck me as the distinctive &lt;em&gt;luxury&lt;/em&gt; of our culture, its most precious, noblest and most dangerous squandering; but still, in view of its over-richness, as its &lt;em&gt;permitted&lt;/em&gt; luxury. Similarly, I explained German music to myself as the expression of a Dionysian might of the German soul: I believed I heard in it the earthquake through which some pent-up primordial force is finally released – indifferent about whether it sets everything else which is called culture atremble.40 You see that what I misjudged both in philosophical pessimism and in German music was what constitutes its actual character – its &lt;em&gt;romanticism.&lt;/em&gt; What is romanticism? Every art, every philosophy can be considered a cure and aid in the service of growing, struggling life: they always presuppose suffering and sufferers. But there are two types of sufferers: first, those who suffer from a &lt;em&gt;superabundance of life&lt;/em&gt; – they want a Dionysian art as well as a tragic outlook and insight into life; then, those who suffer from an &lt;em&gt;impoverishment of life&lt;/em&gt; and seek quiet, stillness, calm seas, redemption from themselves through art and insight, or else intoxication, paroxysm, numbness, madness. All romanticism in art and in knowledge fits the dual needs of the latter type, as did (and do) Schopenhauer and Richard Wagner, to name the most famous and prominent romantics that I &lt;em&gt;misunderstood&lt;/em&gt; at the time – &lt;em&gt;not,&lt;/em&gt; incidentally, to their disadvantage, one might in all fairness concede. He who is richest in fullness of life, the Dionysian god and man, can allow himself not only the sight of what is terrible and questionable but also the terrible deed and every luxury of destruction, decomposition, negation; in his case, what is evil, nonsensical, and ugly almost seems acceptable because of an overflow in procreating, fertilizing forces capable of turning any desert into bountiful farmland. Conversely, he who suffers most and is poorest in life would need mainly mildness, peacefulness, goodness in thought and in deed – if possible, also a god who truly would be a god for the sick, a ‘saviour’; as well as logic, the conceptual comprehensibility of existence – for logic soothes, gives confidence – in short, a certain warm, fear-repelling narrowness and confinement to optimistic horizons. Thus I gradually came to understand Epicurus, the antithesis of a Dionysian pessimist, and equally the ‘Christian’, who really is simply a kind of Epicurean and, like him, essentially a romantic; and my vision grew keener for that most difficult and insidious form of &lt;em&gt;backward inference&lt;/em&gt; with which the most mistakes are made – the inference from the work to the maker, from the ideal to the one who &lt;em&gt;needs it,&lt;/em&gt; from every manner of valuation to the commanding &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; behind it. Nowadays I avail myself of this primary distinction concerning all aesthetic values: in every case I ask, ‘Is it hunger or superabundance that have become creative here?’ At first glance, a different distinction may appear more advisable – it’s far more noticeable – namely, the question of whether the creation was caused by a desire for fixing, for immortalizing, for &lt;em&gt;being,&lt;/em&gt; or rather by a desire for destruction, for change, for novelty, for future, for &lt;em&gt;becoming.&lt;/em&gt; However, both types of desires prove ambiguous upon closer examination, and can be interpreted under the first scheme, which seems preferable to me. The desire for &lt;em&gt;destruction,&lt;/em&gt; for change and for becoming can be the expression of an overflowing energy pregnant with the future (my term for this is, as is known, ‘Dionysian’); but it can also be the hatred of the ill-constituted, deprived, and underprivileged one who destroys and &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; destroy because what exists, indeed all existence, all being, outrages and provokes him. To understand this feeling, take a close look at our anarchists. The will to &lt;em&gt;immortalize&lt;/em&gt; also requires a dual interpretation. It can be prompted, first, by gratitude and love; art of such origin will always be an art of apotheosis, dithyrambic perhaps like Rubens;41 blissfully mocking like Hafis;42 bright and gracious like Goethe, spreading a Homeric light and splendour over all things. But it can also be the tyrannical will of someone who suffers deeply, who struggles, is tortured, and who would like to stamp as a binding law and compulsion what is most personal, singular, narrow, the real idiosyncrasy of his suffering, and who as it were takes revenge on all things by forcing, imprinting, branding &lt;em&gt;his&lt;/em&gt; image on them, the image of &lt;em&gt;his&lt;/em&gt; torture. The latter is &lt;em&gt;romantic pessimism&lt;/em&gt; in its most expressive form, be it Schopenhauer’s philosophy of will or Wagner’s music – romantic pessimism, the last &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt; event in the fate of our culture. (That there &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be a completely different pessimism, a classical one – this intuition and vision belongs to me as inseparable from me, as my &lt;em&gt;proprium&lt;/em&gt;43 and &lt;em&gt;ipsissimum;44&lt;/em&gt; only the word ‘classical’ offends my ears; it has become far too trite, round, and indistinct. I call this pessimism of the future – for it is coming! I see it coming! – &lt;em&gt;Dionysian&lt;/em&gt; pessimism.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>371</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/371/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/371/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We incomprehensible ones.&lt;/em&gt; – Have we ever complained about being misunderstood, misjudged, misidentified, defamed, misheard, and ignored? This is precisely our lot – oh, for a long time yet! Let’s say until 1901, to be modest – this is also our distinction; we wouldn’t honour ourselves enough if we wanted it otherwise. We are misidentified – for we ourselves keep growing, changing, shedding old hides; we still shed our skins every spring; we become increasingly younger, more future-oriented, taller, stronger; we drive our roots ever more powerfully into the depths – into evil – while at the same time embracing the heavens ever more lovingly and broadly, and absorbing their light ever more thirstily with all our sprigs and leaves. Like trees we grow – it’s hard to understand, like all life! – not in one place, but everywhere; not in one direction, but upwards and outwards and inwards and downwards equally; our energy drives trunk, branches, and roots all at once; we are no longer free to do anything individual, to &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; anything individual&amp;hellip; This is our lot, as I have said: we grow in &lt;em&gt;height;&lt;/em&gt; and even if this should be our dark fate – for we dwell ever closer to the lightning! – well, we do not honour it less on that account; it remains that which we do not want to share, to impart: the dark fate of height, &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; fate.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>372</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/372/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/372/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why we are not idealists.&lt;/em&gt; – Formerly, philosophers feared the senses: is it possible that we have unlearned this fear all too much? Today we are all sensualists, we philosophers of the present and future, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; in theory but in &lt;em&gt;praxis,&lt;/em&gt; in practice.45 The former, however, saw the senses as trying to lure them away from &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; world, from the cold kingdom of ‘ideas’, to a dangerous Southern isle where they feared their philosophers’ virtues would melt away like snow in the sun. ‘Wax in the ear’ was virtually a condition of philosophizing; a true philosopher didn’t listen to life insofar as life is music; he &lt;em&gt;denied&lt;/em&gt; the music of life – it is an old philosopher’s superstition that all music is siren-music.46 Today we are inclined to make the opposite judgement (which could itself be just as mistaken), namely, that &lt;em&gt;ideas&lt;/em&gt; are worse seductresses than the senses, for all their cold, anaemic appearance and not even despite that appearance – they always lived off the ‘blood’ of the philosopher; they always drained his senses and even, if you believe it, his ‘heart’. These old philosophers were heartless: philosophizing was always a kind of vampirism. When considering such figures, including even Spinoza, don’t you feel something deeply enigmatic and strange? Don’t you see the spectacle unfolding, this steady &lt;em&gt;growing paler&lt;/em&gt; – this ever more ideally construed desensualization? Don’t you sense in the background some long-concealed blood-sucker who starts with the senses and finally leaves behind and spares only bones and rattling? – I refer to categories, formulas, &lt;em&gt;words&lt;/em&gt; (for, forgive me, what &lt;em&gt;remained&lt;/em&gt; of Spinoza, &lt;em&gt;amor intellectualis dei,47&lt;/em&gt; is mere rattle, nothing more! What is &lt;em&gt;amor;&lt;/em&gt; what &lt;em&gt;deus,&lt;/em&gt; when they are missing every drop of blood?). In sum: all philosophical idealism until now was something like an illness, except where, as in Plato’s case, it was the caution of an overabundant and dangerous health; the fear of &lt;em&gt;overpowerful&lt;/em&gt; senses; the shrewdness of a shrewd Socratic. – Maybe we moderns are not healthy enough &lt;em&gt;to need&lt;/em&gt; Plato’s idealism? And we don’t fear the senses because –&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>373</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/373/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/373/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘Science’ as prejudice.&lt;/em&gt; – It follows from the laws that govern rank-ordering (&lt;em&gt;Rangordnung&lt;/em&gt;) that scholars, insofar as they belong to the intellectual middle class, are not even allowed to catch sight of the truly &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt; problems and question marks; moreover, their courage and eyes simply don’t reach that far – and above all, the need that makes them scholars, their inner expectations and wish that things might be &lt;em&gt;such and such,&lt;/em&gt; their fear and hope, too soon find rest and satisfaction. What makes, for instance, the pedantic Englishman Herbert Spencer48 rave in his own way and makes him draw a line of hope, a horizon which defines what is desirable; that definitive reconciliation of ‘egoism and altruism’ about which he spins fables – this almost nauseates the likes of us: a human race that adopts as its ultimate perspective such a Spencerian perspective would strike us as deserving of contempt, of annihilation! But &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; he had to view as his highest hope what to others counts and should count only as a disgusting possibility is a question mark that Spencer would have been unable to foresee. So, too, it is with the faith with which so many materialistic natural scientists rest content: the faith in a world that is supposed to have its equivalent and measure in human thought, in human valuations – a ‘world of truth’ that can be grasped entirely with the help of our four-cornered little human reason – What? Do we really want to demote existence in this way to an exercise in arithmetic and an indoor diversion for mathematicians? Above all, one shouldn’t want to strip it of its &lt;em&gt;ambiguous&lt;/em&gt; character: that, gentlemen, is what &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; taste demands – above all, the taste of reverence for everything that lies beyond your horizon! That the only rightful interpretation of the world should be one to which &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; have a right; one by which one can do research and go on scientifically in &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; sense of the term (you really mean &lt;em&gt;mechanistically?&lt;/em&gt;) – one that permits counting, calculating, weighing, seeing, grasping, and nothing else – that is a crudity and naiveté, assuming it is not a mental illness, an idiocy. Would it not be quite probable, conversely, that precisely the most superficial and external aspect of existence – what is most apparent; its skin and its sensualization – would be grasped first and might even be the only thing that let itself be grasped? Thus, a ‘scientific’ interpretation of the world, as you understand it, might still be one of the &lt;em&gt;stupidest&lt;/em&gt; of all possible interpretations of the world, i.e. one of those most lacking in significance. This to the ear and conscience of Mr Mechanic, who nowadays likes to pass as a philosopher and insists that mechanics is the doctrine of the first and final laws on which existence may be built, as on a ground floor. But an essentially mechanistic world would be an essentially &lt;em&gt;meaningless&lt;/em&gt; world! Suppose one judged the &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt; of a piece of music according to how much of it could be counted, calculated, and expressed in formulas – how absurd such a ‘scientific’ evaluation of music would be! What would one have comprehended, understood, recognized? Nothing, really nothing of what is ‘music’ in it!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>374</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/374/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/374/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our new ‘infinite’.&lt;/em&gt; – How far the perspectival character of existence extends, or indeed whether it has any other character; whether an existence without interpretation, without ‘sense’, doesn’t become ‘nonsense’; whether, on the other hand, all existence isn’t essentially an &lt;em&gt;interpreting&lt;/em&gt; existence – that cannot, as would be fair, be decided even by the most industrious and extremely conscientious analysis and self-examination of the intellect; for in the course of this analysis, the human intellect cannot avoid seeing itself under its perspectival forms, and &lt;em&gt;solely&lt;/em&gt; in these. We cannot look around our corner: it is a hopeless curiosity to want to know what other kinds of intellects and perspectives there &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; be; e.g. whether other beings might be able to experience time backwards, or alternately forwards and backwards (which would involve another direction of life and a different conception of cause and effect). But I think that today we are at least far away from the ridiculous immodesty of decreeing from our angle that perspectives are &lt;em&gt;permitted&lt;/em&gt; only from this angle. Rather, the world has once again become infinite to us: in so far as we cannot reject the possibility &lt;em&gt;that it includes infinite interpretations.&lt;/em&gt; Once again the great shudder seizes us – but who again would want immediately to deify in the old manner &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; monster of an unknown world? And to worship from this time on the unknown (&lt;em&gt;das Unbekannte&lt;/em&gt;) as ‘the Unknown One’ (&lt;em&gt;den Unbekannten)?&lt;/em&gt; Alas, too many &lt;em&gt;ungodly&lt;/em&gt; possibilities of interpretation are included in this unknown; too much devilry, stupidity, foolishness of interpretation – our own human, all too human one, even, which we know&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>375</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/375/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/375/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why we seem to be Epicureans.&lt;/em&gt; – We are cautious, we modern men, about ultimate convictions; our mistrust lies in wait for the enchantments and deceptions of the conscience involved in every strong faith, every unconditional Yes and No. How can this be explained? Maybe what is to be found here is largely the caution of ‘once bitten, twice shy’; of the disappointed idealist; but there is also another, superior component: the gleeful curiosity of the one who used to stand in the corner and was driven to despair by his corner and who now delights and luxuriates in the opposite of a corner, in the boundless, in ‘the free as such’. Thus an almost Epicurean bent of knowledge develops that will not easily let go of the questionable character of things; also an aversion to big moral words and gestures; a taste that rejects all crude, four-square oppositions and is proudly aware of its practice in entertaining doubts. For &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; constitutes our pride, this slight tightening of the reins as our urge for certainty races ahead, this self-control of the rider on his wildest rides – for we still ride spirited and fiery animals; and when we hesitate, it is danger least of all that makes us hesitate.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>376</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/376/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/376/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our slow periods.&lt;/em&gt; – This is how all artists and people of ‘works’ feel, the motherly type: at every chapter of their lives – which is always marked by a work – they always think they’ve reached their goal; they would always patiently take death with the feeling ‘we are ripe for it’. This is not the expression of weariness – rather that of a certain autumnal sunniness and mildness that the work itself, the fact that the work has become ripe, always leaves behind in its creator. Then the pace of life slows down and becomes thick and flows like honey – to the point of a long &lt;em&gt;fermata&lt;/em&gt;,49 of the faith in &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; long &lt;em&gt;fermata.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>377</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/377/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/377/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We who are homeless.&lt;/em&gt; – Among Europeans today there is no lack of those who have a right to call themselves homeless in a distinctive and honourable sense: it is to them in particular that I commend my secret wisdom and *gaya scienza.*50 For their lot is hard; their hope uncertain; it is a feat to invent a form of comfort for them – but to what avail! We children of the future – how &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; we be at home in this today! We are unfavourably disposed towards all ideals that might make one feel at home in this fragile, broken time of transition; as for its ‘realities’, we don’t believe they are &lt;em&gt;lasting.&lt;/em&gt; The ice that still supports people today has already grown very thin; the wind that brings a thaw is blowing; we ourselves, we homeless ones, are something that breaks up the ice and other all too thin ‘realities’&amp;hellip;We ‘conserve’ nothing; neither do we want to return to any past; we are by no means ‘liberal’; we are not working for ‘progress’; we don’t need to plug our ears to the marketplace’s sirens of the future: what they sing – ‘equal rights’, ‘free society’, ‘no more masters and no servants’ – has no allure for us. We hold it absolutely undesirable that a realm of justice and concord should be established on earth (because it would certainly be the realm of the most profound levelling down to mediocrity and *chinoiserie);*51 we are delighted by all who love, as we do, danger, war, and adventure; who refuse to compromise, to be captured, to reconcile, to be castrated; we consider ourselves conquerors; we contemplate the necessity for new orders as well as for a new slavery – for every strengthening and enhancement of the human type also involves a new kind of enslavement – doesn’t it? With all this, can we really be at home in an age that loves to claim the distinction of being the most humane, the mildest, and most righteous age the sun has ever seen? It is bad enough that precisely when we hear these beautiful words, we have the ugliest misgivings. What we find in them is merely an expression – and the masquerade – of a deep weakening, of weariness, of old age, of declining energies! What can it matter to us what sequins the sick may use to cover up their weakness? Let them parade it as their &lt;em&gt;virtue;&lt;/em&gt; after all, there is no doubt that weakness makes us mild, so righteous, so inoffensive, so ‘humane’! The ‘religion of compassion’ to which one would like to convert us – oh, we know these hysterical little men and women well enough who today need just this religion as a veil and finery. We are no humanitarians; we should never dare to allow ourselves to speak of ‘our love of humanity’ – our type is not actor enough for that! Or not Saint-Simonist52 enough; not French enough. One really has to be afflicted with a &lt;em&gt;Gallic&lt;/em&gt; excess of erotic irritability and enamoured impatience to approach humanity honestly with one’s lust&amp;hellip; Humanity! Has there ever been a more hideous old woman amongst all old women? (Unless it were ‘the truth’: a question for philosophers.) No, we do not love humanity; but on the other hand we are not nearly ‘German’ enough, in the sense in which the word ‘German’ is constantly used nowadays, to advocate nationalism and racial hatred and to be able to take pleasure in the national scabies of the heart and blood poisoning with which European peoples nowadays delimit and barricade themselves against each other as if with quarantines. For that, we are too uninhibited, too malicious, too spoiled, also too well-informed, too ‘well-travelled’: we far prefer to live on mountains, apart, ‘untimely’, in past or future centuries, merely in order to avoid the silent rage to which we know we should be condemned as eyewitnesses of politics that are destroying the German spirit by making it vain and which are, moreover, &lt;em&gt;petty&lt;/em&gt; politics – to keep its creation from falling apart again, doesn’t it need to plant it between two deadly hatreds? &lt;em&gt;Mustn’t&lt;/em&gt; it desire the eternalization of the European system of many petty states? We who are homeless are too diverse and racially mixed in our descent, as ‘modern men’, and consequently we are not inclined to participate in the mendacious racial self-admiration and obscenity that parades in Germany today as a sign of a German way of thinking and that is doubly false and indecent among the people of the ‘historical sense’. In a word – and let this be our word of honour – we are &lt;em&gt;good Europeans,&lt;/em&gt; the rich heirs of millennia of European spirit, with too many provisions but also too many obligations. As such, we have also outgrown Christianity and are averse to it – precisely because we have grown &lt;em&gt;out&lt;/em&gt; of it, because our ancestors were Christians who in their Christianity were mercilessly upright: for their faith they willingly sacrificed possessions, blood, position, and fatherland. We – do the same. But for what? For our unbelief? For every kind of unbelief? No, you know better than that, my friends! The hidden Yes in you is stronger than all Nos and Maybes that afflict you and your age like a disease; and you must sail the seas, you emigrants, you too are compelled to this by – a &lt;em&gt;faith!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>378</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/378/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/378/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘Andbecome bright again’.&lt;/em&gt; – We who are generous and rich in spirit, who stand by the road like open wells with no intention to fend off anyone who feels like drawing from us – we unfortunately do not know how to defend ourselves where we want to: we have no way of preventing people from &lt;em&gt;clouding&lt;/em&gt; us, from darkening us; the time in which we live throws into us what is most time-bound; its dirty birds drop their filth into us; its boys their knick-knacks; and exhausted wanderers who come to us to rest, their small and great miseries. But we will do what we have always done: we take down into our depths whatever one casts into us – for we are deep; we do not forget – &lt;em&gt;and become bright again&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>379</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/379/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/379/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The fool’s interlude.&lt;/em&gt; – The writer of this book is no misanthrope; today one pays too dearly for hatred of man. In order to hate the way one formerly hated &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; human being, Timonically,53 wholly, without exception, with one’s whole heart, with the whole &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; of hatred, one would have to renounce contempt. And how much fine joy, how much patience, how much graciousness even do we owe precisely to our contempt! Moreover, it makes us ‘God’s elect’: refined contempt is our taste and privilege, our art, our virtue perhaps, and we are the most modern of moderns&amp;hellip;Hatred, in contrast, places people on a par, vis-à-vis; in hatred there is honour; finally, in hatred there is &lt;em&gt;fear,&lt;/em&gt; an ample good piece of fear. We fearless ones, however, we more spiritual men of this age, we know our advantage well enough to live without fear of this age precisely because we are more spiritual. We will hardly be decapitated, imprisoned, or exiled; not even our books will be banned or burned. The age loves the spirit; it loves and needs us, even if we should have to make clear to it that we are artists of contempt; that every association with human beings makes us shudder slightly; that for all our mildness, patience, congeniality, and politeness, we cannot persuade our noses to give up their prejudices against the proximity of a human being; that we love nature the less humanly it behaves, and art &lt;em&gt;if it&lt;/em&gt; is the artist’s escape from man or the artist’s mockery of man, or the artist’s mockery of himself&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>380</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/380/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/380/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘The wanderer’ speaks.&lt;/em&gt; – In order to see our European morality for once as it looks from a distance, and to measure it up against other past or future moralities, one has to proceed like a wanderer who wants to know how high the towers in a town are: he &lt;em&gt;leaves&lt;/em&gt; the town. ‘Thoughts about moral prejudices’, if they are not to be prejudices about prejudices, presuppose a position &lt;em&gt;outside&lt;/em&gt; morality, some point beyond good and evil to which one has to rise, climb, or fly – and in the present case, at least a point beyond &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; good and evil, a freedom from everything ‘European’, by which I mean the sum of commanding value judgements that have become part of our flesh and blood. That one &lt;em&gt;wants&lt;/em&gt; to go precisely out there, up there, may be a slight rashness, a peculiar and unreasonable ‘you must’ – for we seekers of knowledge also have our idiosyncrasies of ‘unfree will’ – the question is whether one really &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; get up there. This may depend on manifold conditions. Mainly, the question is how light or heavy we are – the problem of our ‘specific gravity’. One has to be &lt;em&gt;very light&lt;/em&gt; to drive one’s will to knowledge into such a distance and, as it were, beyond one’s time; to create for oneself eyes to survey millennia and, moreover, clear skies in these eyes. One must have liberated oneself from many things that oppress, inhibit, hold down, and make heavy precisely us Europeans today. The human being of such a beyond who wants to catch a glimpse of the highest measures of value of his time must first of all ‘overcome’ this time in himself – this is the test of his strength – and consequently not only his time but also his aversion and opposition &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; this time, his suffering from this time, his untimeliness, his &lt;em&gt;romanticism.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>381</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/381/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/381/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On the question of being understandable.&lt;/em&gt; – One does not only wish to be understood when one writes; one wishes just as surely &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to be understood. It is by no means necessarily an objection to a book when anyone finds it incomprehensible: perhaps that was part of the author’s intention – he didn’t &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to be understood by just ‘anybody’. Every nobler spirit and taste selects his audience when he wants to communicate; in selecting it, he simultaneously erects barriers against ‘the others’. All subtler laws of a style originated therein: they simultaneously keep away, create a distance, forbid ‘entrance’, understanding, as said above – while they open the ears of those whose ears are related to ours. And let me say this amongst ourselves and about my own case: I want neither the inexperience nor the liveliness of my temperament to keep me from being understandable to &lt;em&gt;you,&lt;/em&gt; my friends – not the liveliness, as much as it forces me to deal with a matter swiftly in order to deal with it at all. For I approach deep problems such as I do cold baths: fast in, fast out. That this is no way to get to the depths, to get deep &lt;em&gt;enough,&lt;/em&gt; is the superstition of those who fear water, the enemies of cold water; they speak without experience. Oh, the great cold makes one fast! And incidentally: does a matter stay unrecognized, not understood, merely because it has been touched in flight; is only glanced at, seen in a flash? Does one absolutely have to sit firmly on it first? Have brooded on it as on an egg? *Diu noctuque incubando,*54 as Newton said of himself? At least there are truths that are especially shy and ticklish and can’t be caught except suddenly – that one must &lt;em&gt;surprise&lt;/em&gt; or leave alone. Finally, my brevity has yet another value: given the questions that occupy me, I must say many things briefly so that they will be heard even more briefly. For, as an immoralist, one needs to avoid corrupting innocents – I mean, asses and old maids of both sexes to whom life offers nothing but their innocence; even more, my writing should inspire, elevate, and encourage them to be virtuous. I can’t imagine a funnier sight on earth than inspired old asses and maids who get aroused by the sweet sentiments of virtue: and ‘this I have seen’ – thus spoke Zarathustra. Enough about brevity; things stand worse with my ignorance, which I don’t try to hide from myself. There are hours when I am ashamed of it to be sure, also hours when I am ashamed of this shame. Maybe we philosophers are all in a bad position regarding knowledge these days: science is growing, and the most scholarly of us are close to discovering that they know too little. But it would be even worse if things were different – if we knew &lt;em&gt;too much;&lt;/em&gt; our task is and remains above all not to mistake ourselves for someone else. We &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; different from scholars, although we are inevitably also, among other things, scholarly. We have different needs, grow differently; have a different digestion: we need more; we also need less. There is no formula for how much a spirit needs for its nourishment; but if it has a taste for independence, for quick coming and going, for wandering, perhaps for adventures of which only the swiftest are capable, it would rather live free with little food than unfree and stuffed. It is not fat but the greatest possible suppleness and strength that a good dancer wants from his nourishment and I wouldn’t know what the spirit of a philosopher might more want to be than a good dancer. For the dance is his ideal, also his art, and finally also his only piety, his ‘service of God’.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>382</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/382/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/382/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The great health.&lt;/em&gt; – We who are new, nameless, hard to understand; we premature births of an as yet unproved future – for a new end, we also need a new means, namely, a new health that is stronger, craftier, tougher, bolder, and more cheerful than any previous health. Anyone whose soul thirsts to experience the whole range of previous values and aspirations, to sail around all the coasts of this ‘inland sea’ (&lt;em&gt;Mittelmeer&lt;/em&gt;) of ideals, anyone who wants to know from the adventures of his own experience how it feels to be the discoverer or conqueror of an ideal, or to be an artist, a saint, a lawmaker, a sage, a pious man, a soothsayer, an old-style divine loner – any such person needs one thing above all – &lt;em&gt;the great health,&lt;/em&gt; a health that one doesn’t only have, but also acquires continually and must acquire because one gives it up again and again, and must give it up!&amp;hellip;And now, after being on our way in this manner for a long time, we argonauts of the ideal – braver, perhaps, than is prudent and often suffering shipwreck and damage but, to repeat, healthier than one would like to admit, dangerously healthy; ever again healthy – it seems to us as if, in reward, we face an as yet undiscovered land the boundaries of which no one has yet surveyed, beyond all the lands and corners of the ideal heretofore, a world so over-rich in what is beautiful, strange, questionable, terrible, and divine that our curiosity and our thirst to possess it have veered beyond control – alas, so that nothing will sate us anymore! After such vistas and with such a burning hunger in our conscience and science, how could we still be satisfied with &lt;em&gt;modern-day man?&lt;/em&gt; Too bad – but it’s inevitable that we look at his worthiest goals and hopes with a seriousness which is difficult to maintain; maybe we don’t even look at all any more. Another ideal runs before us, a peculiar, seductive, dangerous ideal to which we wouldn’t want to persuade anyone, since we don’t readily concede &lt;em&gt;the right to it&lt;/em&gt; to anyone: the ideal of a spirit that plays naively, i.e. not deliberately but from overflowing abundance and power, with everything that was hitherto called holy, good, untouchable, divine; a spirit which has gone so far that the highest thing which the common people quite understandably accepts as its measure of value would signify for it danger, decay, debasement, or at any rate recreation, blindness, temporary self-oblivion: the ideal of a human, superhuman well-being and benevolence that will often enough appear &lt;em&gt;inhuman&lt;/em&gt; – for example, when it places itself next to all earthly seriousness heretofore, all forms of solemnity in gesture, word, tone, look, morality, and task as if it were their most incarnate and involuntary parody – and in spite of all this, it is perhaps only with it that &lt;em&gt;the great seriousness&lt;/em&gt; really emerges; that the real question mark is posed for the first time; that the destiny of the soul changes; the hand of the clock moves forward; the tragedy begins.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>383</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/383/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/english/prose/nietzsche/gay-science/5_Book_Five/383/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Epilogue.&lt;/em&gt; – But as I finally slowly, slowly paint this gloomy question mark and am still willing to remind my readers of the virtues of reading in the right way – oh, what forgotten and unknown virtues! – it strikes me that I hear all around myself most malicious, cheerful, hobgoblinlike laughter: the spirits of my book are themselves descending upon me, pulling my ears and calling me to order. ‘We can’t stand it anymore’, they shout, ‘stop, stop this raven-black music! Are we not surrounded by bright mid-morning? And by soft ground and green grass, the kingdom of the dance? Was there ever a better hour for gaiety? Who will sing us a song, a morning song, so sunny, so light, so full-fledged that it does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; chase away the crickets55 but instead invites them to join in the singing and dancing? And even plain, rustic bagpipes would be better than the mysterious sounds, such bog-cries, voices from the crypt, and marmot whistles with which you have so far regaled us in your wilderness, my Mr. Hermit and Musician of the Future!56 No! Not such sounds! Let us rather strike up more pleasant, more joyous tones!’57 Does it please you &lt;em&gt;now,&lt;/em&gt; my impatient friends? Well then, who wouldn’t like to please you? My bagpipes are already waiting; my throat, too – it may sound a bit rough, but put up with it; after all, we’re in the mountains. At least what you are about to hear is new; and if you don’t understand it, if you misunderstand the &lt;em&gt;singer,&lt;/em&gt; what does it matter? This happens to be ‘the singer’s curse’.58 You will be able to hear his music and tune so much the better, and so much the better will you be able to dance to his pipe. Is that what you &lt;em&gt;want?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
